<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</title>
    <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/tags/opinion/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>jits</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jitshappens.com/tags/opinion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Sense on Training</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/common-sense/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/common-sense/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-students&#34;&gt;For Students&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life isn&amp;rsquo;t fair; distinguish yourself with intense training. Remember when your coach told you size and strength don&amp;rsquo;t matter? He was wrong: strength matters. When all else is equal between opponents, whoever has the edge in the smallest way will distinguish themselves in victory. Oh, and size matters too. A big guy with like skills will crush a little guy. Sorry little guys. Coming from a featherweight, I share your pain. Literally. On the other hand, technique, stamina, and aggression can imbalance a much greater differential in size and strength. I have beaten much bigger guys than me, but there was always a reason: no magic, just training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cross Train - If you want to be a good martial artist, you need to be a good athlete. I don&amp;rsquo;t care what you choose to do, but cross train in something. Swim, lift weights, run, bike, rock climb, play soccer. It will help your strength and endurance. It&amp;rsquo;s also fun. Don&amp;rsquo;t be a martial arts nerd: get outside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a Good Student; Take notes. Good students take notes. Committing your training to personal notes is an important step in memorizing your training, and recording a permanent document of what you may end up spending a lifetime acquiring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test yourself. Good students test themselves to get a fair measurement of how they stack up against others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things Need to Change: Keep an Open Mind. Don&amp;rsquo;t get stuck in the same old habits. Find new positions to fight from. Take off your gi and fight. Put on a blindfold and fight. Don&amp;rsquo;t ever ask permission to try something new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question all assumptions made by students and teachers. Any teacher that can&amp;rsquo;t deal with curiosity is in the wrong business. The only dumb question is the one you didn&amp;rsquo;t ask.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust your experience. Have faith in your accumulated mat time and experience in fights. Clear your head and go with your reflexes. If you can&amp;rsquo;t do this, get back on the mats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let yourself heal. Don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to be a hero if you have an injury. Take time off from training, and don&amp;rsquo;t let anyone talk you back until you are better. But, know when it is time to get back on the mats. The longer you are gone, the harder it is to get back out there. [Read more about injuries here]().&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break the rules, and don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid of (or surprised by) the consequences. Non-conformists drive people nuts, so be prepared to go it alone if you have to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-instructors&#34;&gt;For Instructors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward the most curious. Be prepared to learn something from your students. Support an atmosphere of creativity and openness, so everyone feels comfortable asking questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t beat your dog and don&amp;rsquo;t beat your students with your dogma. Never ask your students to have faith in you or &amp;ldquo;just trust&amp;rdquo; you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody has all the answers. Admit when you don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer, but be ready to get in there and figure it out with sweat and hard work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have fun. If you can&amp;rsquo;t have fun and make fun of yourself every day, you&amp;rsquo;ve lost yourself in your own self-importance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge is wealth; Share it with others. If you don&amp;rsquo;t spend at least 51% of your time coaching others in something, you are adding no net value to your time on Earth. Don&amp;rsquo;t get self-absorbed. Give it away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your students aren&amp;rsquo;t your property. Don&amp;rsquo;t whine if they go to another school. [Read more about this]().&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compete, or don&amp;rsquo;t push your students into competition. If you can&amp;rsquo;t be a positive role model for the courage required to step on the mats and potentially lose in front of them, then don&amp;rsquo;t be a hypocrite and encourage them to compete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn from other sports. Develop training tools. Drill, drill, drill. Videotape student fights and analyze them with your students. Introduce circuit training. Get your students into shape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t expect respect; earn it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bane of Freedom</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-bane-of-freedom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-bane-of-freedom/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;a-warning-about-instructors-who-put-themselves-before-you&#34;&gt;A warning about instructors who put themselves before you.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many instructors treat their knowledge as a treasure that is only bestowed upon those in their inner circle: their most trusted students who have shown loyalty, their knights. All the other students are serfs who have not yet proven their worth to the king. All live within his kingdom. No bonds are made or allowed with other neighboring kingdoms. You can join the king, but you must move within the walls, and never leave again. Anyone who strays outside the walls of the kingdom are banished forever. They are suspected as spies who may have sold the keys of the castle to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the kingdom-building realities of an egomaniacal instructor with a distorted world-view of the purpose of knowledge. Knowledge is to be set free. Allow your students to seek it anywhere they may. The borders must be porous to allow for great relationships with your neighbors, sharing of knowledge, and creation of new knowledge from old. Encourage cross training anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sign of kingdom-building is the treatment of questions from the students. I have seen instructors who don&amp;rsquo;t answer questions or do so in such an oblique fashion that over time, questions stop from the students. I have had one instructor who would answer some questions with &amp;ldquo;That will cost $100 and one hour of your time,&amp;rdquo; meaning the student could get an answer only if they paid for a private lesson with the high-priced black belt. When a new student joins, they wonder why nobody else is asking questions. They soon learn their lesson with a belittling experience in front of the class. Why create secrets, mystery, and intrigue? In doing this, the knowledge instructors hold is locked in the castle tower. Foster innovation, research, exploration, and inquisitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build a school that is about building students, not about building a kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-the-lesson-from-another-service&#34;&gt;Learning the Lesson From Another Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try a simple analogy. Forget martial arts for a minute. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you want to be a doctor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You pick the best medical school around, because you want to be the best doctor you can be. You want to save lives and you believe you can be a success. After doing a great job in pre-med, you have envisioned a dream of opening a small medical clinic where you can better the lives of a small community. Your friends and family believe in you. But more than anything, you feel compelled by your principles to pursue this dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You go to the medical school and do a great job, year after year. You expand your knowledge and arm yourself with the tools to save lives. The dean of the college counsels you, shares with you his profound knowledge, and treats you like family. Your professors are top notch. You take an internship with a small clinic to diversify and deepen your experience. It turns out that this is more fulfilling than your class work because it demonstrates you understand real world application of what you have learned. You take other internships.  As you come closer to the end of med school, you organize opening your own clinic. You have imagined this whole time how this would work, and now it is becoming real. You excitedly share with others around you the slow process of creating this clinic as it unfolds. Your family, friends, and other students are happy for you and wish you the best. Your college dean and professors are proud. You embark on the greatest dream of your life and are blessed to actually love your job and the benefits your work bestows upon those you touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During your years of practice, other doctors join you. You share your knowledge freely, discover new methods, and publish these for all to learn from. Years later, a young doctor joins you. You mentor this doctor until he knows enough to go out and open a clinic of his own. You are sad to see him go. But much more than this, you are proud of their accomplishment and bless him as he makes his way onward. This young doctor considers you their lifelong friend and mentor. Their successes transitively become your successes. You unlocked the door for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instructors-unlock-the-door&#34;&gt;Instructors: Unlock the Door&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the dream of many martial artists to know enough to teach someday: to give back what they have been given. It is a shame that some martial arts instructors put more focus on protecting their knowledge than creating an environment of limitless growth. Instructors: know what your students seek. Put their goals before you or get out of the business. &lt;a href=&#34;(http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/train-for-yourself/)&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s what service is all about&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Students are customers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Many-Faceted Fighter</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-faceted-fighter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-faceted-fighter/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do You Have What it Takes to Succeed in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and Submission Grappling?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;for-students-new-to-the-sport&#34;&gt;For Students New to The Sport&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are asking yourself: &amp;ldquo;Do I have what it takes to train in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and Submission Grappling?&amp;rdquo; you are not alone. It&amp;rsquo;s a daunting sport to enter. Watching your first class from the sidelines will give you a mixture of excitement and dread. You will be questioning every aspect of yourself as you make a decision. In short, you will discover that for every aspect of skill required in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu, there are people who persevere in the sport due to strengths in a variety of areas. Be prepared for something completely different, but understand that despite your best efforts, it may not work out. Here are some characteristics to consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fitness and Weight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strength&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aggression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical Skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fearlessness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Competitiveness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical Intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical Creativity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of your Opponent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of Yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Showmanship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;characteristics-that-define-the-fighter&#34;&gt;Characteristics that Define the Fighter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these characteristics can be improved upon with work, such as strength, fitness level, and technical skill. Others can be changed slightly with substantial work, such as competitiveness. Others are difficult to change or control, such as aggression, agility, and physical creativity. I just scratch the surface of each of these characteristics. One could dedicate chapters and books on these subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;fitness-level-and-weight&#34;&gt;Fitness Level and Weight*&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It almost always starts here. People who are &amp;ldquo;out of shape&amp;rdquo; often think they need to get into shape before joining. I suggest that you really are never going to be in shape enough to start grappling unless you are already grappling. Paradoxical, but it&amp;rsquo;s the same in every sport. Until you use the muscles and move in the way the sport demands, you won&amp;rsquo;t discover them though some other cross-training regimen. Get on the mats and get in shape there. Regarding weight control, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen more pounds shed on these mats than I can count. It&amp;rsquo;s hard work, but it can be done. And why not learn how to fight while you go through the hard labor of weight loss?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our mats, the overweight train side by side with the super-fit. We&amp;rsquo;re all in it together. Fitness as a way of life, practiced through the sport of submission grappling. In the professional fighting context, mixed martial artists are well regarded as some of the most well rounded athletes out there. It is rare to find a successful fighter who doesn&amp;rsquo;t have an incredible fitness level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As great as fighters Ken Shamrock and BJ Penn are, they have both lost fights because their opponent was better conditioned, not more technical. Ortiz did it to Shamrock and Matt Hughes did it to Penn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;strength&#34;&gt;Strength&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount strength matters depends on the situation. If two opponents of similar skill faced off, strength would matter and would absolutely define the victor. Since it is rarely the case that two people are that closely matched in a fight, especially an unplanned street altercation, strength really doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the lion&amp;rsquo;s share of consideration. In training for competition, anything an athlete can do to legally improve their ability to win should be focused on. There is no doubt that strength training improves the overall athlete. If you are not naturally strong, you should weight train, use kettle bells, etc. If you are naturally strong, you can put it off, but eventually, you should consider resistance training to improve your game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;size&#34;&gt;Size&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve said in other articles, size matters. While many proponents of this sport will point to great champions who overcame larger opponents, they neglect to say that those larger opponents had less skill, agility, or stamina than the smaller opponent. Taking a single factor into play against a like opponent in all other aspects, size matters. Like strength, the happy news is that most large guys out there don&amp;rsquo;t know a lot about fighting. Paradoxically, larger (or stronger) guys tent to learn the finer points of ground fighting slower than smaller guys since they can rely on their other assets. Technique comes later, and only when their size (or strength) is neutralized by an opponent of greater skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While nobody denies that MFS fighter Tim Sylvia is great, his size has clearly contributed to his success. Holland&amp;rsquo;s Semmy Schilt has experienced almost as much fame as Sylvia (from my biased North American perspective), with less talent and much more height. Bob Sapp is perhaps the most hyperbolically huge person with surprisingly little technical skill, stamina, fearlessness, or agility on the K-1 scene. His sheer size draws crowds as if to a freak show and help him smash unwitting opponents to pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;aggressiveness&#34;&gt;Aggressiveness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggression is an interesting quality, and one that surprisingly doesn&amp;rsquo;t help a refined fighter much. Aggression, simply stated, is the ease with which a fighter is willing to be violent or harmful. It is completely different from the desire to win, or more accurately, the complete distain for defeat. This attribute is the competitiveness, or the Desire to Win. Don&amp;rsquo;t confuse the two. An aggressive man may lose all desire to win at the slightest sign of pain, loss of position, or exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t need to be a naturally aggressive person to love the challenge of competition. I&amp;rsquo;m a very passive individual. I would never fight unless cornered or defending a loved one. Yet I love the combination of competition and challenge that comes when grappling on the mats. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to overstate my case, but there may actually be a negative correlation. Overly aggressive guys generally clumsily hurt people. When this happens, they get ostracized (other guys don&amp;rsquo;t want to train with them) or even physically beaten by the senior students repeatedly to scare them off. It is rare that someone with the singular skill of aggression distinguishes themselves in the sport. On the other hand, a nice dose of controlled aggression combined with several other factors can make for a great fighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;technical-skill&#34;&gt;Technical Skill&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical skill is the accumulated knowledge of a student and their ability to draw upon it when needed, with appropriate speed, strength, distancing, and precision. The sports of submission grappling and Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu celebrate technical skill like most martial arts and sports. Those with the most technical skill tend to be those who have accumulated the most realistic mat time against strong opponents and have been lucky enough to have solid coaching. Clearly being able to demonstrate technical skill requires significant agility, technical intelligence, and usually requires flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical skill is by far the most important of the characteristics that make a fighter great. When Randy Couture wore out Gonzaga against the fence in UFC 74, it was his technical skill that kept Gonzaga at bay. Sure, other aspects of the fighter helped (strength, fitness, fearlessness, desire to win), but it was Couture&amp;rsquo;s skill that allowed his much heralded body lock to disable Gonzaga. By far the most spectacularly technical fighters out there is Marcelo Garcia. Garcia has won the pinnacle competition, the ADCC, in his 66-76 kg weight division three times in a row. He has only lost against much larger opponents in the absolute division, generally in the finals. How Garcia wins is important: he almost always wins by submission rather than points, this is a key indicator of technical advantage over his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;fearlessness&#34;&gt;Fearlessness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a bit of bravery to face off with an opponent on the mats. It takes even more bravery to come back to class after getting your butt whooped a few times. I recall my early days as a white belt. I&amp;rsquo;d miss a couple of classes and think how easy it would be to never go back. I knew if I went back in, I&amp;rsquo;d get obliterated by the more advanced students. I think the pure excitement of learning such an effective fighting system kept me coming back. It overcame the fear. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be fearless to be great. In fact, there is a fine line between bravado and stupidity. Knowing when to tap and when to back down in an unwinnable match will keep the injuries at bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically skilled students may become more fearless, simply because fear is all about the unknown. An advanced student knows what every submission feels like and knows their limits. An advanced student has a greater chance of winning a fight. Both of these greatly diminish fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearlessness is closely related to Desire to Win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;flexibility&#34;&gt;Flexibility&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flexibility is completely independent of all the other factors. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen overweight, physically unfit people with incredible flexibility. Conversely, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen some amazing fighters with significant limits to their range of motion in various limbs. Some people are naturally inflexible in certain parts. No amount of stretching, yoga, or conditioning will improve this more than a few percentage points. More flexible people can get out of tighter jams and can stay calm in very nasty physical situations. But I&amp;rsquo;ve got some very good fighters who are very tight. It matters, but won&amp;rsquo;t make or break your game on the mats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eddie Bravo&amp;rsquo;s flexibility has helped him redefine the sport of submission grappling. I also credit Eddie&amp;rsquo;s physical creativity in creating scores of new moves. Not everyone can succeed with the rubber guard. More flexible fighters have more options to put their body into shapes that help them succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;agility-and-balance&#34;&gt;Agility and Balance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agility is by far the most important characteristic of this sport. Agility, in context with this sport, is defined as the ability to move your body smoothly and precisely on command, from a multitude of angles, both with or without the full weight and strength of your opponent borne upon you. That&amp;rsquo;s a tall order for many students. Prospective students who ask me if they have what it takes to succeed on the mats are often times answered with this question: &amp;ldquo;Can you dance?&amp;rdquo; This is a good indication of agility, balance, physical creativity, and physical intelligence. After training over a hundred students at Austin Jiu-Jitsu, it is quite clear that the most agile students bubble quickly to the top of the stack of the group. Agile students fly past awkward ones. In the end, gyms that train in fighting sports have a pecking order. The most agile are often on top. It is rare that someone without agility will dominate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diego Sanchez&amp;rsquo; balance and agility have helped him become one of the most successful fighters in his weight class. He outclassed Karo Parisyan, one of the most dangerous fighters in the world, in UFC Fight Night 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;desire-to-win&#34;&gt;Desire to Win&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(i.e. Will, Competitiveness, Confidence, Mental Strength, Mind Game)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be very afraid of an opponent with copious amounts of competitiveness. An overly competitive personality in a poorly skilled opponent is dangerous to himself. These are they guys who never know when to tap and end up getting hurt and emotional when they lose an unwinnable fight. Conversely, a competitive personality in a highly skilled opponent is a treacherous opponent indeed. A desire to win is an outstanding quality that absolutely makes the difference between chumps and world champions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of the desire to win is the mental strength that allows a fighter to stare into the eyes of another. While some may call it an act, this display of confidence tests the will of the opponent. It&amp;rsquo;s not just a show when Vanderlei Silva stares down his opponent before a fight. It is Silva beginning to impose his will on the opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;physical-intelligence&#34;&gt;Physical Intelligence&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Right-Brained Fighter has Muscle Memory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical intelligence is defined by a rapid ability to recall physical motion. Some people learn physical motion with fewer repetitions than others. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen this as completely independent of other forms intelligence. &amp;ldquo;Book smart&amp;rdquo; intelligent people don&amp;rsquo;t learn physical motion any faster and certainly can&amp;rsquo;t tap into that muscle memory any faster. The difference is how quickly muscle memory latches on and if it can be tapped when needed. If it&amp;rsquo;s not there when you need it, in an instant, you don&amp;rsquo;t have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People with greater muscle memory certainly learn faster in physical sports like Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu. If you don&amp;rsquo;t remember techniques well, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to &amp;ldquo;rep&amp;rdquo; techniques more. In the end, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn it if you commit the time to practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;physical-creativity&#34;&gt;Physical Creativity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Left Brained Fighters define their own moves&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical creativity is the ability to work out new situations with the movement of your body. For example, a physically creative person can discover new submissions or escapes quickly by untangling the numerous positional relationships between the fighter and the opponent. These are the guys who advance the sport and define the fighting system in terms of their own body, rather than simply mimicking the movements of others independent of consideration of the physical aspects of the differences of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The left brained fighter isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily artistic off the mats, but on the mats they take the often times clumsy movements of fighting into something graceful and beautiful. Generally, a physically creative person is highly agile, but an agile person may not be physically creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question to ask is why advanced fighters so often end up making up their own moves? Is it primarily because advanced fighters have so much mat time to have successfully, through trial and error, created new moves? Or is it because only physically creative people make it to the advanced levels of this sport? It is very unusual to see a brown or black belt in the sport of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu who hasn&amp;rsquo;t defined their own special sub-species of the sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;knowledge-of-the-opponent&#34;&gt;Knowledge of the Opponent&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sun Tzu summed it up best &amp;ldquo;If you know the enemy and know yourself, you need not fear the result of a hundred battles.&amp;rdquo; Beyond simple knowledge, you need to know how to adapt your fight. You may know someone has great take-downs, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t work the sprawl, you&amp;rsquo;ll still end up on your back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Randy Couture beat Tim Silvia in UFC 68, he won the fight by knowing how to avoid the punching power of Sylvia. A new Randy Couture emerged at this fight: someone who bobbed and weaved like an experienced boxer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;knowledge-of-your-own-limits&#34;&gt;Knowledge of your Own Limits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t get pulled into a fight you can&amp;rsquo;t possibly win. Fighting an opponent out of your league isn&amp;rsquo;t smart. Of course, the prerequisite to this decision is knowing your opponent. Unless this is a friendly sparring match, if you can compare your skills and you can&amp;rsquo;t win, don&amp;rsquo;t fight. Unfortunately, cornered on the street, you have no choice. No matter what the odds, fight to survive, even if outgunned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Royce Gracie bravely stepped on the mats against Matt Hughes in UFC 60, he dramatically underestimated Hughes, but more significantly, overestimated himself. Royce shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have taken that fight. I&amp;rsquo;d guess it was about the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;showmanship&#34;&gt;Showmanship&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem surprising to hear that showmanship in any way applies to the ability to fight, but showmanship is a mental game designed to get the crowd on your side and to get inside the head of your opponent. Nick Diaz is great at at goading his opponents. He&amp;rsquo;s so good at it, he even confused referee Steve Mazzaggati into mistakenly declaring that Diaz was somehow breaking the rules in the UFC. Nick knows how to piss people off. A pissed off opponent isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily more dangerous, just distracted. Kazushi Sakuraba&amp;rsquo;s showmanship gets the crowd behind him almost every time. When he spanked Ryan Gracie in Pride, it created such a buzz, the media attention alone elevated Sakuraba&amp;rsquo;s stature as a &amp;ldquo;Gracie Killer.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During matches, a fighter&amp;rsquo;s ability to conceal pain, pretend they are less challenged than they really are, and generally show no concern, is generally a successful approach. This poker face tactic prevents the easy &amp;ldquo;read.&amp;rdquo; If you know your opponent is in pain, tired, or afraid, you will pick up the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free Will and the Free Agent</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/free-will/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/free-will/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;student-migration-and-the-search-for-personal-growth&#34;&gt;Student Migration and the Search for Personal Growth&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Treating students as the property of a school or coach demonstrates a lack of understanding of free will.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who train in any sport or martial art are free agents. They should continue to move from training gym to gym until they find a place that suits their needs. Their needs will change over time as they make decisions about what they need to develop, and as they gain skills. Their free will to learn and grow is the driving force behind migration of students across various schools over time. In any given city, you will find numerous students who have trained with a handful of different coaches. Over time, they change coaches because one coach may offer stronger training in an aspect that the student needs more work in. There is no such thing as &amp;ldquo;stealing students.&amp;rdquo; Coaches are in business to grow students and develop their school. Students are involved to find personal growth. Coaches are in competition for students. As student select to change schools, coaches often incorrectly think that their student has been stolen as if the student was the property of the instructor. Treating students as the property of a school or coach is an unfortunate viewpoint that demonstrates a lack of understanding of free will in human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coaches: It&amp;rsquo;s about the students not about you.
Students: if they don&amp;rsquo;t get it, find a new coach.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Man Does Not Live By Theory Alone</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/not-just-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/not-just-theory/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Survival requires much more than irregular and brief seminar training, books, and videotapes. The only knowledge that provides instantaneous recall in an attack situation is reflexive, or muscle memory. This comes with intense, repetitive, long-term training in proper technique with proper coaching. Seminars, books, and videotapes are great to augment regular training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Trust your instincts&amp;rdquo; means let your reflexive response lead you. Don&amp;rsquo;t hobble yourself with thought. An interesting test of this is if you ask someone the question &amp;ldquo;what would you do if someone came up to you and [insert violent attack here]?&amp;rdquo; An answer that includes some detailed description of a counter to this attack isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily the best answer. Someone who trusts their instincts would probably say &amp;ldquo;I have no idea.&amp;rdquo; This is because when the attack starts, so does the autonomous response. You only control this at the most basic level of your brain, far below the cognitive processes that guide those parts of your brain that make you a thinking primate. This is what I call the &amp;ldquo;twitch response.&amp;rdquo; The same level that causes you to blink when something gets flicked in your face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;walk-the-walk&#34;&gt;Walk the Walk&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk all you want, but until you burn the correct movements into your brain and train your moves against a determined opponent, nothing you train in will help you survive an attack. Punch a punching bag and working punching drills will certainly develop a good punch, but what happens when you get smacked or sucker punched? You never know until it happens. Just as an army or nation must be able to survive and immediately respond to a first strike by the enemy, so must you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;adding-insult-to-injury&#34;&gt;Adding Insult to Injury&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the uninitiated, an unexpected punch or slap landing in your face is pretty shocking and usually ends up with one or both of these responses: momentary shock and profound insult. In either case, your mind is wasting precious response time in what apparently has just become a fight (or an ass-kicking if you don&amp;rsquo;t snap out of it). The mental gap created by shock is a perfect opportunity for the attacker to unload a knockout punch on you or shove you to the ground and proceed to kick your head in. The profound insult you felt is a result of the fact that your face is the precious inner circle of your personal space. To have someone breach that space and hit you on touch your face is as bad as telling you your mama is a dog and your dog is your mama. Get over it, because an angry response will interfere with your reaction. Studies have shown that emotion interferes with athletic performance. Sure, it&amp;rsquo;s personal. But don&amp;rsquo;t let it get you emotionally. That&amp;rsquo;s not easy, unless you get hit when you train and understand that it&amp;rsquo;s really not all that insulting after all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Martial Arts Training is Like Swiss Cheese</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/swiss-cheese/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/swiss-cheese/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;While it&amp;rsquo;s cool and somewhat self-indulgent to say I spent 9 years getting 2 black belts in Karate, in reality it&amp;rsquo;s kind of like having a PhD. It looks really good on the wall and it&amp;rsquo;s a great conversation starter, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really mean much on the streets. I have grown much more in training in different arts for shorter timeframes (say, 2 to 6 years). Why? Because no martial art is perfect. Despite what just about every practitioner of every style you have ever known will tell you, each one has core weaknesses that prevent it from being a complete self-defense system, or a complete physical training system (for those who swear they don&amp;rsquo;t train to learn how to kick ass). Several have more weaknesses than strengths. For those who like to keep a balance sheet, these may seem like a complete waste of time. This is actually not so. For example (personal views here), Aikido has far more weaknesses than strengths. It is far from a complete system. A black belt in Aikido would get the crap pummeled out of him by an aggressive boxing student with 9 months of experience or a wiry wrestler with a few seasons under his belt. But, when Aikido skills are aggregated with skills of other arts, positive things happen. Even if all it does for you is teach to to take a mean break fall or apply a nasty wristlock (a technique of pretty limited utility on the streets against a wiggly opponent &amp;ndash; ask any cop), it still is better than not knowing it. But these arts (there are many that fall into this category) should be neither ignored nor focused on with too much intensity. Go in with a skeptical viewpoint, and like Bruce Lee said, take what you can use, discard what is useless to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see these weaknesses as holes, like in Swiss cheese. Where one art has a hole, another one has a perfect plug for it (yet has its own holes elsewhere). The trick is to know where the holes are and know what other arts may fill them. Don&amp;rsquo;t waste time if you discover an art that doesn&amp;rsquo;t fill a hole you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mixed Martial Arts (MMA) has arisen in popularity as more and more coaches and competitors come to grips with the reality of this concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-this-relates-to-austin-jiu-jitsu&#34;&gt;How This Relates to Austin Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encourage all of my students to cross-train. They should get out and train with students from other schools as often as they can, identify holes, and plug them with specific training.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>