<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Austin Jiu-Jitsu</title>
    <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/tags/adaptation/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Austin Jiu-Jitsu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>AustIn JIu-JItsu</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/tags/adaptation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A Small Milestone on a Long Path</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/a-small-milestone/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/a-small-milestone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like most long-term endeavors, there are few significant milestones. In a sport like Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu, where the journey from white to black belt only has 3 intermediate steps, the milestones are literally &amp;ldquo;few and far between.&amp;rdquo; In my case, with 13 years in the making of 2008 black belt promotion, simple math will tell you just how far those milestones were set apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of our time working though intense athletic effort is filled with small challenges, victories, incremental growth, and setbacks. Even if you train 4 times per week, go to every seminar and open mat available, and compete regularly, you will find long periods of time where getting over the smallest obstacle will challenge your resolve to continue the journey ahead. The harder you train, the more likely you will get injured. The more you cross-train with others, the more likely you will find someone who will kick your butt so regularly and with such domination, that you will likely wonder if you can ever get past them. I remember being a white belt, completely sore and beaten up from my previous training day, afraid to face the mats again, wondering if I should return for another brutal work-out. Of course, I returned, but was faced with this constant question for months. The sport is insanely challenging. Everyone you meet on the mats sees you as fresh meat. The target is on your back every single day. As your rank progresses, this target gets bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu rewards people who can get past these big obstacles. The rewards are not just rank, but a knowledge base of skills that are broad and deep.
I remember a karate sensei of mine 20 years ago, in a moment of self-absorption, was boasting about how at his skill level, he could simply toy with his opponents &amp;ldquo;like a cat playing with a mouse.&amp;rdquo; I was simultaneously disappointed that he shared this with his students and intrigued that a level of skill that advanced was attainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than boast that I&amp;rsquo;m the biggest cat in the jungle, this promotion is a time to remember how many phenomenally talented athletes are in this amazing sport; many of them commanding a skill level that I can only hope to attain in my lifetime. I also hope that I have the ability to translate this wonderful sport into words capable of inspiring my students to stay on the long road. Don&amp;rsquo;t focus on the milestones. Focus on the gifts that come from the hard work, every day you are on the mats: friendship, fitness, and the skills of a cat just a little bit bigger than it was yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our System Does Not Coddle Weak Technique</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/discard-what-doesnt-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/discard-what-doesnt-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Never use the closed guard,&amp;rdquo; I tell my students, &amp;ldquo;unless you are stalling or waiting to die.&amp;rdquo; As I state this, I wonder about how this position became so fundamental only to be eventually thrown away so unceremoniously. Then I consider the never-ending stream of new techniques, positions, attacks, counter-attacks, and defenses generated in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and submission grappling over time. I think about some amazing technique I learned years ago as a blue belt and how it has been rendered ineffective and obsolete by the withering juggernaut of a thousand athletes pounding from all angles like velociraptors probing the electrical containment fences in Jurassic Park. I recall some fundamental progenitor move, originally defined in utterly simple steps, that have evolved into a broad category of richly varied options (e.g. the Rubber Guard). I reflect on certain positions, once considered inescapable by all but the most advanced, which are now easily thrown off by less experienced fighters. What&amp;rsquo;s happening here? Is this natural acceleration or the result of a slow evolutionary process? And where are all these great new moves coming from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weak techniques will not survive. We know intuitively that techniques are successful only when they help win fights. Winning techniques are constantly studied by students of the sport. We adopt them, tweak them, make them work for their bodies, and transmit them to others. That&amp;rsquo;s how we spend the bulk of our time on the mats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fighting sport evolves by the influences of social interaction and information theory. In his 1979 Pulitzer Prize-winning novel &lt;em&gt;Gödel. Escher. Bach: An Eternal Golden Braid&lt;/em&gt;, author Douglas R. Hofstadter put a human spin on the mathematical concept of recursive enumeration. People come up with new ideas by watching the results of previous work and adapting. Repeat for a few generations, and some cool things start to happen. All of human civilization has developed using this process, gaining new insights from existing concepts. Over time, systems slowly evolve into more complexity and subtlety. Complexity is increased because past information and existing rules are applied to new situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the mats, we take old ideas and challenge them repeatedly. The weak techniques die off or morph into variations that are more successful in different situations. The media, usually blamed for dumbing down the masses, expands our information horizon and accelerates the speed of ideas flowing through what I call the Jiu-Jitsu diaspora. As it flows through, it is interpreted, tuned, adapted, mutated, then reflected slightly improved, back out the global information channel. New ideas are literally created from old information. Like an infinite tapestry, we weave the fabric of Jiu-Jitsu every time we step on the mats.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>