<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</title>
    <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/tags/mma/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>jits</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jitshappens.com/tags/mma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Punched Will Make You a Better Grappler</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-getting-punched/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-getting-punched/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Do your training buddy a favor and smack the shit out of him next time you spar. Will he forgive you? Hell, he should &lt;em&gt;thank you&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow&#34;&gt;Flow&lt;/a&gt; is great and technique drilling is absolutely important, but&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you aren&amp;rsquo;t regularly putting yourself into the mindset of a real fight, you aren&amp;rsquo;t preparing yourself for a real fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;The easiest way to do that is to get your grapplers to hit each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ground-rules&#34;&gt;Ground Rules&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partner up with someone you trust in your gym. You need to safely take each other just past the limit of your individual skills, but not too far.
Start from a disadvantaged position: a grab or tackle from behind, on the ground under the mount, or wadded up against the wall under a ground and pound assault.
Work this drill from the attacker and defender positions. Attackers will improve their top game and will learn how to control people from scrambling out of an attack. Defenders will improve their confidence and fight success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use a timer. Start at 1:30 and build every couple of weeks to work your way up to 5 minutes. Then add another round. I’ve found when you have a clock, there are fewer tap-outs from exhaustion or beat-down. When you train against the clock, you will typically try to “survive the round” rather than give up.
Keep the “tap out” escape hatch but understand that a tap-out in a real street fight is equivalent to a hospital or morgue trip: it means you gave up against a bad guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;drill-responses&#34;&gt;Drill Responses&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is to win in a encounter like this, or at least survive and escape. We drill these every week in our MMA class at Austin Jiu-Jitsu. Here are tactics in order of a prioritized “survival timeline,” where those you do first are most important to know and more likely to be successful. If you are going to drill one thing on the mat tonight, drill #1!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrambling out from under an attack. As much as we love BJJ and submission grappling, it’s not smart to stay stuck on the bottom. Drilling scrambling out of ground and pound attacks (from mount, side, half guard, and guard) will help you prepare for this. Scrambling out is different from sweeping in one important respect. In a scramble, you are explosively evading and pushing your opponent off before control position is established.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tying up or slowing an attack. If you can’t scramble out, you’ll need to slow down or stop your opponent’s strikes. Do this to buy yourself time to sweep or scramble out.
Escaping control or sweeping your attacker. Once he gets control position, your ability to scramble is reduced. You will need to work hard to defend and tie up your opponent to buy yourself time to technically escape or sweep. This is a much more technical game than an explosive scramble, and as such presents more risk. You need more skill and often more time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submitting the attacker from the bottom. Statistically, this isn’t a great bet, so I’m putting it at the bottom of the list. Sure, a submission specialist and elite-level MMA fighter like Antônio Rodrigo Nogueira has found submissions in &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of his fights, but you shouldn’t spend a lot of time getting hammered from the top unless you are truly great at tying up your attacker and nailing submissions. Submitting from the top is a great plan, so don’t mistake my point here; maintaining bottom position with a plan of submitting your attacker from the bottom is less likely to be successful than the other approaches described above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you drill each of these, make a note of which ones get you beat up the least. You’ll notice that as you go from 1 to 4, you get hit more and take longer to win or escape. Of course, in a real fight, you’ll employ many of these simultaneously. Chain the drills together and switch attackers based on who is on top. This will improve your ability to survive a real fight. Most MMA guys know this, but a lot of pure BJJ folks lack this experience and may make the mistake of focusing on submissions only. This is the same type of myopia that strikers without grappling experience suffer from. Don’t make their mistake in reverse. Prepare for getting hit by grappling with strikes allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallax Error</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-dangerous-assumptions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2010 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-dangerous-assumptions/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I remember being a 1st kyu brown belt in Japanese karate back in the late 1980s. I was to be evaluated for my first black belt very soon. I was steeped in the detail of techniques, training intensity, and constant pressure of a student rising to his first dan promotion. I vividly recall my pride in ability. I felt I could fight off any attack, win any fight, and deliver ikken hissatsu: to kill with a single punch. I would talk to my buddies at the dojo and we’d discuss what we’d do in a real fight.
&amp;gt;One of us would say,&amp;ldquo;I’d drive his eyeball into his brain with an ippon nukite uchi!&amp;rdquo;
The other would respond,&amp;ldquo;Yeah? I’d explode his kidney with a yoko geri then smash his nose into his brain with a bear claw strike!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of this years later, it’s almost as funny and unlikely as Brick Tamland stabbing a guy in the heart with a trident in &lt;em&gt;Anchorman&lt;/em&gt;. Was I skilled in fighting or just good at karate? Was I too deep in one system of fighting to understand my general fighting abilities? Of course I couldn’t fend off any attack, win any fight, or deliver a killing blow. The irony is that deep skill in one fighting art and the lack of perspective about what you don’t know can lead to a dangerous general assumption that you are a good fighter. This is called parallax error, or an inability to see the real picture due to the participant’s point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we fast forward to the 2010s, it seems nostalgic and quaint that karate once dominated the self-defense landscape. Today, we are so much more advanced, aren’t we? We know the ground is where all fights end up, or at least that’s what the brochure said. Wake up: the problem with karate students in the 1980s is likely to be present with students of grappling sports today. Are we good fighters, or just good grapplers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I have a successful gym with a bunch of students who love to grapple, obsess over their matches, and count down the hours to their next training session. They are competitive and intense grapplers who are generally moving up the ranks as they make their way toward mastery. The problem is that, like karateka from the ‘80s, most grapplers today really don’t know how to fight. The good ones own the ground, but many aren’t consistently working on rounding out their fighting skills. I’ve wondered why 4 out of 5 grapplers never really learn the full set of skills to call them a fighter. Sure, these grapplers can thrive and enjoy all the beauty there is to find in BJJ, but don’t make the mistake of considering them fighters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;making-a-grappler-into-a-fighter&#34;&gt;Making a Grappler into a Fighter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grapplers that want to know how to fight should find time to work on these skills with their training partners. The list is ordered as a progression from most fundamental (simple) to most advanced (challenging).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foot work, evasion, feinting, guarding, and blocking skills to avoid strikes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working strikes! Punching, kicking, elbows, and knees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take-downs against a resisting opponent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take-downs against an opponent throwing punches and kicks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defending strikes from the clinch (blocks, underhooks, takedowns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completing takedowns against a wall or corner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Controlling and positioning to throw strikes from a variety of ground positions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standup boxing &amp;ldquo;flow&amp;rdquo; work – low intensity at first – to get accustomed to getting hit and get a different type of cardio workout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting against a wall or in a corner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting near obstacles: walls, furniture, people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting to get out from under a ground and pound attack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting 2 attackers from standing: positioning and exit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting to get up from the ground with multiple attackers are standing above you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weapons defense (sticks, knives, guns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that &amp;ldquo;fighting&amp;rdquo; doesn’t show up until the bottom half of the list. In my MMA program at &lt;a href=&#34;http://austinjiujitsu.com&#34;&gt;Austin Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/a&gt;, we spent over a year working on the top half of the list, just to build the basic skills needed to get to the real fighting drills. Yes, the above drills are a part of many established and successful martial arts systems: Muay Thai, Jeet Kune Do, krav maga, kali, escrima, and boxing. But keep in mind the passion grapplers have for grappling. They want to be a part of a Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and submission grappling program. As a by-product of all their hard work, time, and money spent, they also expect to know how to fight. A fight isn’t just a ground battle, and to be a fighter doesn’t just mean you know how to triangle choke someone. You must drill fighting scenarios that put you into a fight mentality and you have to do it often enough and with enough intensity that the training creates correct responses in a real fight situation. Without opportunity to train for real fighting, we aren’t creating real fighters.
I’m happy that many BJJ schools are creating MMA programs to help blend other fighting skills into their students and to finally correct this parallax error. Grappling students: take advantage of these opportunities. Learn how to fight!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Train For Yourself</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/train-for-yourself/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/train-for-yourself/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your instructor is human. Don&amp;rsquo;t let yourself get sucked into a cult of personality.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental and nearly universal aspects of martial arts training is the intense loyalty students feel to their instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe you should be loyal to those who are loyal to you, meaning you should devote your loyalty where it is earned. In some circumstances the loyalty I have seen students devote to instructors borders on blind zeal. Over the years, I have fallen into this trap from time-to-time.  It is all too easy to carelessly fantasize that your instructor is the toughest martial artist in the planet and that everything he does should be followed with biblical devotion. That&amp;rsquo;s not my viewpoint. While I feel that within a specific school you should respect the authority of an instructor, the instructor is providing a paid service, not unlike a personal trainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;news-flash-self-defense-instruction-is-a-service&#34;&gt;News Flash! Self-Defense Instruction is a Service&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most prevalent problem in martial arts today. Martial arts instructors place their ego before the customer. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it over and over again. Most martial arts instructors will talk the talk of your personal growth, but when push comes to shove, they forget it and put their goals squarely in your path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a service industry. You, the customer (the student), hold the reins. Your instructor may help you navigate, should help you motivate, and will pick you up and redirect you when you crash. But everything you learn belongs to you. You paid for it with sweat, time, and money. It&amp;rsquo;s yours. While you may credit your 4th grade reading teacher for your love of fiction novels, the stories you have read are yours alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;know-when-it-s-time-to-leave&#34;&gt;Know when it&amp;rsquo;s time to leave&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen a pattern in many martial arts schools. As students advance through the ranks, one of three things happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students get &amp;ldquo;fat and complacent&amp;rdquo; and start to mimic the head instructor, barking orders at the new students and taking every opportunity to beat them senseless. They are completely in tune with each others&amp;rsquo; techniques and habits. They rarely, if ever, challenge themselves in competition or against unknown (experienced) opponents. They have a stature they have worked far too hard on to have someone knock them off their pedestal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Others begin to see the weaknesses in their instructor, whether these are moral, political, or physical weaknesses. These students tend to leave, either establishing their own schools or joining a &amp;ldquo;competing&amp;rdquo; school. In this case, an &amp;ldquo;exodus of the awakened&amp;rdquo; sometimes follows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The senior students begin to assist instruction and the head instructor works on diplomacy with other schools, associations, and bridge building to promote growth in the sport. This is the optimal arrangement, but is unfortunately rare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think it is a natural, and even beneficial process that advanced students with an open mind and true passion for experiencing personal growth will either desire to begin to instruct, thus allowing the head instructor to focus on outward-facing activities or fly away from the nest. The only unfortunate thing about this is that, due to the lifelong loyalty expected, a bridge is often burned by leaving. If your instructor has the correct attitude toward growing students, you will be welcomed back for training and you will indeed have a lifelong coach, even after you open your own school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, having the ability to fly doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you should leave the nest. Know when it&amp;rsquo;s time.  There are many schools with solid curriculum, fantastic coaching, and great facilities that can satisfy a decade of martial arts training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;building-bridges-and-fresh-meat&#34;&gt;Building Bridges and Fresh Meat&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of training for yourself involves seeking relationships with other students and instructors in other schools in the area. This helps in many ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gives you access to numerous new training partners, a term I call &amp;ldquo;eating fresh meat.&amp;rdquo; The ones you train with at your primary school are like your brothers. You love them and have fun with them, but when you wrestle with your brothers, there is often times nothing new to learn. Sure, any mat time is better than none at all, but there is either a permanent pecking order in place, or dull and predictable stalemates are the norm.
It allows you to test the waters to make sure that the quality of instruction you are getting really is the best for the money and time you commit to this most important endeavor. Gasp! Did I say money and time are more important than the deep relationship of loyalty you owe to your instructor? Why, yes I did. Remember the topic? &amp;ldquo;Train for yourself, not your instructor.&amp;rdquo;
If the school is training in a different style, it provides valuable cross-training. This may lead to a deeper exploration of the new style if you decide it is right for you. Jiu-Jitsu students should wrestle with wrestlers, play with judoka and samboka, and prepare to learn something new. I have learned wonderful new ideas by shutting my mouth and listening to a wrestling coach instruct a class.
Challenge your instructor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are training at the right school, this may seem like suicide. Most instructors really are much tougher than you. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to imply you want to actually somehow destroy your instructor, but I want to make an important point. After training in traditional Karate and Aikido schools for well over 13 years, I&amp;rsquo;m allowed to make this observation: most students don&amp;rsquo;t try hard enough when testing technique on their instructors, or sparring with them. This is once again the &amp;ldquo;larger than life&amp;rdquo; problem. If an instructor asks you to throw a punch at him and you actually hit him (his demonstration fails), would you feel really bad? Should you? No. When you spar with your instructor, would you feel bad if you beat him? You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t. In reality, if his technique doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, you don&amp;rsquo;t want to walk around with some false sense of security do you? The first time I beat one of my instructors sparring, I experienced mixed emotions. I certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like celebrating. It was a bit awkward, he didn&amp;rsquo;t congratulate me, and I was left wondering what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is a form of dishonesty to not challenge your instructor with your greatest effort and technique. Challenging him will keep you both sharp. I encourage my students to fight to win, and many of them are quite a handful!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snake Oil Salesmen</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/snake-oil-salesmen/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/snake-oil-salesmen/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Know how to distinguish the theatrical, vaudevillian Martial Arts. Unless you seek pure entertainment, these are the charlatans of the martial arts world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of martial arts to stay away from completely. The reasons for these vaudevillian martial arts are as varied as the arts themselves. Some just want to trick you out of your money (snake oil salesmen). Others really believe they are on to something, and often almost never realize they are part of a charade. One reason for this is because their students want to believe it just as much as they do. This is because they never realistically challenge their instructor to prove their technique works in real situations. Whatever you do, don&amp;rsquo;t ever listen to the following 2 groups of people when making a decision about a martial art:
1. A devoted student of the art
+ Someone who has never studied the art&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who does this leave? You. You&amp;rsquo;d never pick a friend this way, and you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pick martial arts this way either. Make your own decision. Be honest.
Evaluate the school and system yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;internal-arts-and-ki-chi&#34;&gt;Internal Arts and Ki [Chi]&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any martial art that calls itself an &amp;ldquo;internal art&amp;rdquo; (such as those that put ki or chi energy at the forefront) has limited benefit in self defense. Note, I said limited. I choose this word carefully because it means that there are clearly defined benefits, but they have definite bounds. These arts may provide students with spiritual training, something of unquestionably good value. There are very few martial qualities to these arts that contribute to physical success in combat situations. Use of ki in martial arts training is beneficial in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As an instructional tool, ki is a metaphor that allows students to learn to direct real physical energy. There is no doubt that the kiai (the union of physical action and emotional direction or focus) is quite valuable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of ki as a technique that catalyzes mental focus. Again, this is a visualization tool, not unlike the Zen meditation practice of complete attention to breathing. It provides a valuable conduit to achieving mental balance. It finds the calm waters in the mind storm. Since panic and fear can defeat you as quickly in battle as improper technique or a more powerful opponent, understanding the use of ki this is clearly of value to martial artists. But I would argue that any mental tool you can employ will provide similar results. A pep talk by a high school football coach before a game can motivate as much, if not more violent direction of force.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>