<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Austin Jiu-Jitsu</title>
    <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Austin Jiu-Jitsu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>AustIn JIu-JItsu</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Location</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/location/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/location/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;austin-jiu-jitsu-is-at&#34;&gt;Austin Jiu-Jitsu is at&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;4220-s-lamar-blvd-400-austin-tx-78704-https-goo-gl-maps-bde7mea3yzt-location&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/bDe7mea3yzt&#34; title=&#34;location&#34;&gt;4220 S Lamar Blvd #400, Austin, TX 78704&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/img/map.png&#34; alt=&#34;Austin Jiu-Jitsu map&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are located in Suite 400, where we share space with Traditional Martial Arts Academy. Look for suite 400 in the right corner of the brown brick retail center.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schedule</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/schedule/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/schedule/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;See the calendar below for our class times. Each program has separate classes, regularly scheduled each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://calendar.google.com/calendar/embed?src=pue2vn7f8sn56onm0kufm0iuh0%40group.calendar.google.com&amp;ctz=America/Chicago&#34; style=&#34;border: 0&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;600&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What We Do</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/services/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 11:43:42 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/services/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brazilian-jiu-jitsu&#34;&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-world-s-most-effective-ground-fighting-system&#34;&gt;The world&amp;rsquo;s most effective ground-fighting system!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popularized by the Gracie and UFC and proven in fights world-wide, Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu will give you an edge over larger, stronger opponents. We&amp;rsquo;ll help you gain an advantage through superior technique, leverage, speed, and stamina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;our-guarantee&#34;&gt;Our Guarantee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training with Austin Jiu-Jitsu is guaranteed to raise your awareness, understanding, and abilities in self-defense. We will help you improve your level of physical fitness and will teach you how to fight successfully. When combined with our strength and wrestling classes, you will be even more fit to win!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;our-specialties&#34;&gt;Our Specialties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/brazilian-jiu-jitsu/&#34;&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; Submission Grappling&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strength and Mobility&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;our-history&#34;&gt;Our History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We have been teaching Austin how to grapple for 14 years!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Austin Jiu-Jitsu was founded in 2003. Our gym is committed to developing student potential through safe, balanced, and effective self-defense training, leveraging the concepts Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and ground fighting (Submission Grappling).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;our-coaches&#34;&gt;Our coaches&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/coaches/&#34;&gt;About our coaches&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact Austin Jiu-Jitsu</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/contact/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;email&#34;&gt;Email&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/img/coach-dtjj.png&#34; alt=&#34;say hi&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;phone-or-text&#34;&gt;Phone or Text&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text preferred, as we get lots of solicitors &lt;img src=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/img/taproll.png&#34; alt=&#34;txt us&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;located-at-4220-s-lamar-blvd-400-austin-tx-78704-https-goo-gl-maps-bde7mea3yzt-location&#34;&gt;Located at &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/bDe7mea3yzt&#34; title=&#34;location&#34;&gt;4220 S Lamar Blvd #400, Austin, TX 78704&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are located in Suite 400, where we share space with Traditional Martial Arts Academy. Look for suite 400 in the right corner of the brown brick retail center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/location/&#34;&gt;Read more about our location here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are only open during class times, so please see our &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/schedule/&#34;&gt;schedule&lt;/a&gt; to plan a visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;social-media&#34;&gt;Social Media&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click one of the links on the left to get to our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/austinjiujitsu.jitshappens&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/austinjiujitsu&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/austinjiujitsu&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;, or other pages.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Membership Plans</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/plans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/plans/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brazilian-jiu-jitsu-and-submission-grappling&#34;&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and Submission Grappling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn more about our &lt;a href=&#34;{{ &amp;lt; ref &amp;quot;post/brazilian-jiu-jitsu.md&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}&#34;&gt;BJJ program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classes are $90 per month for unlimited classes. We have 3 classes per week.
Drop-in fees are $25 per class.
Private lessons with &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/john-martinich/&#34;&gt;John&lt;/a&gt; are $90. Private lessons with &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/dave-thomas/&#34;&gt;Dave&lt;/a&gt; are $105.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our Coaches</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/coaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 11:43:42 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/coaches/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;head-coach-john-martinich&#34;&gt;Head Coach John Martinich&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/john-martinich/&#34;&gt;About John&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;founding-coach-david-thomas&#34;&gt;Founding Coach David Thomas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/dave-thomas/&#34;&gt;About Dave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;coach-dan-borth&#34;&gt;Coach Dan Borth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/dan-borth/&#34;&gt;About Dan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coach John Martinich</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/john-martinich/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/john-martinich/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Austin Jiu-Jitsu Head Coach John Martinich is a Brown Belt under founding coach David Thomas. John is known for his incredible technical ability and passion for dissecting technique and sharing his greatness. As a native Austinite and Computer Science grad from UT, John has balanced his life well between family, work and play. Joining Austin Jiu Jitsu in 2003, he has developed a passion for the sport through coaching and competition. BJJ is a lifestyle for John through stress reduction, exercise and friendships. When he&amp;rsquo;s not at the gym, he&amp;rsquo;s at home with his wife and grappling with his two boys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/img/authors/john-martinich.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;John Martinich&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coach Dave Thomas</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/dave-thomas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/dave-thomas/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is great happiness in the lifelong pursuit of human potential.&amp;rdquo;&lt;cite&gt;-Coach David Thomas&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dave Thomas of Seattle, WA is founding coach at Austin Jiu-Jitsu (Self-Defense Mentor, LLC). While Dave now trains and works out of Seattle, he is proud to have built Austin Jiu-Jitsu from a small group of friends in his garage to a thriving community of dedicated students from 2003 - 2017. He visits the gym when he comes to town to roll with his students and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;some-of-dave-s-contributions-include&#34;&gt;Some of Dave&amp;rsquo;s contributions include&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His student-centric approach, helping them on their personal journey toward mastery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His highly technical skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An unconventional, creative fighting style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Development of a successful women&amp;rsquo;s program, which enjoys a significantly high ratio of women to men &amp;ndash; which is unusual in BJJ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing the talent of his team of coaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His prolific writing on training, coaching, and service toward the student in his blog, &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog&#34;&gt;Jits Happens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The creation of &lt;a href=&#34;bjjtech.com&#34;&gt;BJJTech.com&lt;/a&gt;, the largest single-sourced collection of BJJ techniques on the web.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/img/authors/dave-thomas.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Coach Dave&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dave has been has been training, competing, and coaching since January 1985.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;life-off-the-mats&#34;&gt;Life Off the Mats&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he isn&amp;rsquo;t training and coaching, Dave enjoys a great &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/dcthomas&#34;&gt;career&lt;/a&gt; in software product entrepreneurship, where he is a product leader at &lt;a href=&#34;http://indeed.com&#34;&gt;Indeed&lt;/a&gt;. He has two children, &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/jenny-thomas/&#34;&gt;Jenny&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/budoatemaildotcom/search?query=zach&#34;&gt;Zach&lt;/a&gt;, who both grew up on the mats with him at Austin Jiu-Jitsu. Dave&amp;rsquo;s wife Christine previously led the Austin Jiu-Jitsu women&amp;rsquo;s program and has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/christinegthomas&#34;&gt;career&lt;/a&gt; in high-tech finance. Dave and Christine both studied business at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chicagobooth.edu/&#34;&gt;University of Chicago&amp;rsquo;s Booth School of Business&lt;/a&gt; (2016 and 2017 MBA grads).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;accomplishments-and-qualifications&#34;&gt;Accomplishments and Qualifications&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu Black Belt (under Carlos Gracie Jr. Black Belt Travis Tooke). Coaching since 2003, training since 1995.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2008 North American Grappling (NAGA) Champion, Brown and Black belt Division (160 lb and under, Director, Gi)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Black belts, including BJJ, Japanese Karate (AAKF, JKA Shotokan)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State, national, and international-level competition experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certified USA Wrestling Coach for competitive youth wrestling programs. 3 seasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground fighting trainer for law enforcement, EMT, and military personnel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experienced referee in local and state-level BJJ and Submission Grappling competitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MMA instructor 2008 - 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diverse martial arts training background including MMA, Thai Boxing, Jeet Kune Do, Karate, Aikido, and Judo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Licensed by the Texas Department of Public Safety Private Security Bureau (2005)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Licensed by the Texas Combative Sports/Boxing Commission as an MMA Cornerman (2009)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed BJJTech.com, the largest single-sourced collection of BJJ techniques on the web.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;jits-happens&#34;&gt;Jits Happens&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read Dave&amp;rsquo;s blog, &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog&#34;&gt;Jits Happens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coach Dan Borth</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/dan-borth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/dan-borth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Austin Jiu-Jitsu Coach Dan Borth is a Brown Belt under founding coach David Thomas. Dan is known for his innovative approach that has led to creation of numerous amazing submission moves. He cross trains with some of the best coaches in Austin, including NCAA All American Wrestler &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifeforce-fitness.net/jason-carr/&#34;&gt;Jason Carr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/img/authors/dan-borth.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dan Borth&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Injuries</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/injuries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/injuries/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I share my tips on injury prevention, safety in training, and some of the injuries I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in my time training in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu. It is my personal perspective based on my experience. Use it as a reference only. You will certainly experience your own set of injuries if you train long enough or hard enough. Let me repeat that: if you train long enough and hard enough, you will get injured. No training worth the time or money happens without hard work and long duration. If you intend to get good at this, expect to work through discomfort, pain, and injuries. Some prevention is possible, but if you are going to really improve your game, you are going to put yourself in harm&amp;rsquo;s way. Be prepared for the consequences and the rewards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The injuries sustained in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu are similar to what you&amp;rsquo;d see in most contact sports. Soreness (which gets much less frequent as you become accustomed to the training) is by far the the most common side effect. But soreness is just your body telling you it wants to rest after a good workout. That&amp;rsquo;s not an injury! Soreness for me is a simple barometer that tells me that I trained hard enough yesterday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-prevention-tips&#34;&gt;Basic Prevention Tips&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the techniques correctly - injuries are very commonly the result of poor training. Learn solid technique at the Austin Jiu-Jitsu BJJ Technique Catalog, and read the warnings there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protection - &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/gear-up-for-class/&#34;&gt;get the right gear for training&lt;/a&gt;. Use equipment such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mouthguard - required of all my students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Earguards - Never wrestle without them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wrestling shoes - if you are nervous about your toes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wraps -  In boxing drills, wrap your hands to protect your hand bones. Your coach can show you how to wrap them. Wraps are cheap and make a big difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;hygiene&#34;&gt;Hygiene&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my experience, risk of infection comes from two sources: untreated scratches and microbes introduced into the training area. Microbes can cause infections and skin conditions like ringworm. The best prevention is cleanliness. Here are some tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your nails short and clean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wash your hands and face before class (I&amp;rsquo;ll assume you all wash up after using the potty room)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only wear clean clothes to class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always leave your shoes outside the mats. Lots of nasty microbes are on the bottoms of your shoes. If they get on the mats, they can cause problems!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shower immediately after class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not come to class if you have any kind of infection (skin rash, common cold, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you see a rash, blister, or sores on your training partner, don&amp;rsquo;t train with them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use skin protectant. Google it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disinfect the mats with an antimicrobial solution at least once per week. We do! We&amp;rsquo;ve never had an outbreak at our gym!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;treatment&#34;&gt;Treatment&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rest, Ice, Compression, and Elevation (RICE)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are very sore, rest. Don&amp;rsquo;t overdo it! Ice your injuries. Elevate them to reduce swelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set Limits with Your Training Partners - If you are nervous about sparring with someone much bigger, stronger, or more capable than you, tell them so. Ask them to be careful and always quit the match if you sense danger. The beauty of BJJ is that you can always &amp;ldquo;tap out&amp;rdquo; and stop immediately. Most advanced students know how to &amp;ldquo;throttle down&amp;rdquo; so this is more commonly an issue with beginners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be a hero. Tap if it hurts, if you are dizzy, or have any reason to suspect you can&amp;rsquo;t continue the match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See a Doctor - If you think you have an injury, see a doctor. Take responsibility for your training and your healthcare. It&amp;rsquo;s your body!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be the source of injuries at your gym - Most gyms have a couple of guys who are a bit dangerous. They are usually beginners and don&amp;rsquo;t know how to safely take someone down or apply technically correct submissions. If your favorite submission is a neck crank, you&amp;rsquo;re probably not making many friends at your gym. Be considerate of your training partners and their skill and fitness levels. Read about disallowed techniques, below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;common-injuries-you-can-expect-every-week-or-two&#34;&gt;Common injuries you can expect every week or two&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my personal observation, the most common injuries in order of prevalence are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bruises - These are most commonly from people grabbing your arms or legs. Most BJJ students will carry their bruises like a badge of honor. The only interesting perspective I can lend to this is that the longer I&amp;rsquo;ve trained the less I see bruises. I have no idea if that is an indication of my capillaries changing or me just getting harder to grab on to!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scratches - If you keep your finger and toenails short, you&amp;rsquo;ll help reduce the scratches. See below for more prevention tips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;less-common-injuries&#34;&gt;Less common injuries&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloody lip - If you don&amp;rsquo;t wear a mouthpiece, a bump against someone&amp;rsquo;s knee, head, or elbow will bloody the inside of your mouth. A mouthpiece will reduce the chances of this significantly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Torn ligaments - I&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of any torn ligaments that required surgery, but plenty of tears occur that require recuperation time. For example, I hurt my elbow in a competition once that required a few weeks off. It took several months for my arm to feel &amp;ldquo;back to normal.&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;ve heard of a couple of students tearing the intercostals between their ribs, which is quite painful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rare-injuries-more-serious-stuff&#34;&gt;Rare Injuries - More Serious Stuff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cauliflower Ear - Over time, ear injuries can cause cauliflower ear to wrestlers and boxers. I recommend all students buy and wear ear guards during wrestling and any drills which put pressure on the ears. As I tell my students, if you see me put mine on, you should be wearing yours too! Google it to learn more. I have never had a student develop this condition, but one student had to be treated by a doctor to prevent it when he had some swelling on his ear. He is now a dedicated ear guard wearer!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toe Drags - This is an injury where you step on your own big toe as it gets caught under your foot while stepping forward on the mats. It sounds hard to imagine, but it has happened to me. It hurts like heck and can really stress out your toe ligament. This took a couple of months to heal. While it healed, I wore wrestling shoes and was able to train at full intensity. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard of another couple of students getting toe drags. It is one of the most frustrating injuries, as it is one of the only &amp;ldquo;self-inflicted&amp;rdquo; injuries you can sustain on the mats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breaks - The most common bone break I&amp;rsquo;ve seen is a pinky toe break. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen at least 10 of those in my years of training. The wrestling mats are not kind to your toes. The solution to this is wrestling shoes. Wear them and you&amp;rsquo;ll probably never get a foot injury. In nearly a decade, I&amp;rsquo;ve only seen one broken bone (an arm) at a competition &amp;ndash; not during regular training. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard about another guy who got his arm broken in the class of another school here in town, but not in mine!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dislocations - I&amp;rsquo;ve seen one dislocated shoulder in training. It popped right back in, but was a very painful experience for the poor student it happened to. I have also seen one dislocated elbow in a competition. Both of these were due to sloppy arm bars. I have seen several dislocated pinky toes (again, wrestling shoes will nearly eliminate the chance of this).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lacerations - I have seen remarkably little blood in my gym. Since we aren&amp;rsquo;t punching each other, it is rare to see split skin. We&amp;rsquo;ve only had one serious cut that required stitches, and in that case it was &amp;ldquo;self-inflicted&amp;rdquo; in that the student who got cut slammed into his opponents knee when trying to take him down. Lesson learned: don&amp;rsquo;t slam your head into someone&amp;rsquo;s knee!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;uncomfortable-situations&#34;&gt;Uncomfortable Situations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the most uncomfortable situations that arise on the mats are not related to injuries. Nevertheless, they are worth mentioning here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choking out - Prevention: TAP OUT! In over a decade of training, I&amp;rsquo;ve witnessed 5 people pass out from a choke in regular training (me being one of them). I can tell you from experience what it was like. In short, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t fun! If you ever ask someone who got choked out in training, their story will sound a lot like this. I was getting choked and thought I could escape. I was wrong. The next thing I knew I was waking up on the mats with a very nervous student standing over me. I had a headache and was very disoriented. It felt like I woke up from a nap with a hangover. I was &amp;ldquo;out&amp;rdquo; for about 5 seconds. It took about a minute or so for me to get my bearings and be able to stand up. Within a few more minutes I was ready to start training again. Although, I was a bit embarrassed for not tapping out. Frankly, seeing someone pass out is far more stressful. A passed out person looks dead. Their eyes are often staring out into space. To minimize risk here, don&amp;rsquo;t let children choke each other in regular sparring. It requires individual adult attention to each match, and without enough sets of eyes on the mats, it&amp;rsquo;s best to only allow chokes in controlled demonstrations.  On my mats, kids are not allowed to choke below the rank of yellow belt, and even then require supervision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tossing your cookies - This is very easy to prevent. Don&amp;rsquo;t train with food in your tummy! 7 people I know have barfed from the intensity of training with too much food in their stomachs. I was one of them, so again, this comes from experience. If you train hard in any sport, you really can&amp;rsquo;t have any food in your stomach. Different people have different windows of time they need to make sure they are safe. I won&amp;rsquo;t eat within 2 hours of training. I know others that won&amp;rsquo;t train for 4 hours. Here&amp;rsquo;s how my barfing experience went. I was set to compete and was assuming that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have my first fight until after noon. At 9:00 in the morning, I ate a huge breakfast thinking it would last me all day. Every other competition I had been to had the advanced belts fighting last. In this one, they fought in parallel on 3 different mats (kids on one, women on another, guys on the third). So, at about 10:30, they called me to fight. I fought like a wildcat for 8 minutes. Immediately after the match was over, I felt awful. I was much more lethargic than I should have been and was pretty dizzy. About 10 minutes later, I puked my brains out in a trashcan outside the gym. It was really nasty. I felt great once I was done, though!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;disallowed-techniques-for-safety&#34;&gt;Disallowed Techniques for Safety&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While all techniques should be fair game for instructors to demonstrate, to prevent injury, some should not be allowed in full speed sparring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any joint manipulation outside the range that is safe for that joint. All techniques have a safe way to apply them that will prevent injury. If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand the way to perform the technique, ask your coach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any move that is done at a speed greater than the ability for your partner to react and submit before injury. In other words, give your partner a chance to tap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The heel hook - Unsafe at any speed above slow. Always avoid sideways torque to the knee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The neck crank - This technique is done from numerous angles, but is never accomplished without unnecessary stress to the vertebrae in the neck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lanyngeal chokes - Any choke that puts pressure on the air passage is unsafe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slams - Takedowns where your opponent is dropped from any height above your knees are unsafe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any takedown or sweep where you cannot guarantee your partner will fall into a safe place on the mats. When throwing your partner, make sure they have plenty of open mat space to land in. Other people may be there!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single finger grabs - BJJ is all about control, which requires lots of grabbing. When you grab and pull on a single digit of your opponent, you risk breaking or straining it. Always grab 3 or more fingers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facial cranks - Not surprisingly, excessive pressure on the face will make someone tap, but they&amp;rsquo;ll label you as unsafe and probably avoid you when sparring in the future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most back cranks, such as the &amp;ldquo;Boston Crab&amp;rdquo; - as in the case of neck cranks, this is an unnecessary risk of serious injury&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;get-out-there-and-have-fun-but-be-safe&#34;&gt;Get out there and have fun, but be safe!&lt;/h5&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gearing Up</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/gear-up-for-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/gear-up-for-class/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This article helps new students get the gear they need to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a checklist for organizing your trip to class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gym bag to store all this stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jiu-jitsu gi for gi classes. The white belt is purchased separately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board shorts and rashguard for no-gi classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mouthpiece&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water bottle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flip flops &amp;ndash; but leave them outside the mat room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A towel for wiping up sweat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out what &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/schedule/&#34;&gt;the schedule&lt;/a&gt; is. Gi versus no-gi training require different gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;gi&#34;&gt;Gi&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good gi will last you years, so don&amp;rsquo;t go for the cheapos. There are no stores that sell good jiu-jitsu gis in Austin, so Google around and get something you like. Colors and patterns are cool. We aren&amp;rsquo;t a traditional school that is stuck with old white kimonos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;no-gi&#34;&gt;No Gi&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A no-gi class looks like a bunch of surfers in board shorts and rash guards. Academy has a great selection of reasonable (and good looking) rash guards for men and women, but their board shorts suck. Head to a surf shop and hit the clearance rack. No need to pay full price for this stuff, since top name brand items are pretty steep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;mouthpiece&#34;&gt;Mouthpiece&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can spend $4 on a boil and bite variety or you can spend $90 and get your dentist or orthodontist to make a really comfortable one. I have always gone with the dentist option since it is way more comfortable: you can breathe, talk, and it never slips off. I usually forget I&amp;rsquo;m even wearing it. You only need protection on the top teeth, not the double variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;ear-guards&#34;&gt;Ear guards&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always wear them, but lots of folks never do. We keep a community pool of this stuff here, so you can check out the variety we have here and decide what brand to look for online if you decide to wear them. They are intended to prevent a relatively rare ear &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/injuries/&#34;&gt;injury&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;ve seen enough in my 13 years on the mats to want to avoid altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;wrestling-shoes&#34;&gt;Wrestling Shoes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only recommend wrestling shoes if you have a foot or toe injury. They are perfect for protecting a hurt foot while you train, but they get in the way for some of the tighter escapes and moves so aren&amp;rsquo;t recommended for regular training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;knee-pads&#34;&gt;Knee Pads&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some folks have sensitive knees that are aggravated by the take-down practice we do. I recommend keeping one handy. If your knees get sensitive or bruised, your technique will suffer if you start to avoid dropping to your knee to correctly perform the take-down.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/brazilian-jiu-jitsu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/brazilian-jiu-jitsu/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-makes-bjj-so-different&#34;&gt;What makes BJJ so different?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu is widely regarded as the world&amp;rsquo;s most effective ground fighting (grappling) system. While it has been evolving since the early 1900s as a martial art, street fighting system, and sport, the last ten years have brought it the most popularity in America and abroad as a result of globally distributed media coverage of victories in numerous challenge matches and mixed martial arts competitions pitting athletes with mastery of various martial arts. It is a safe yet highly effective combat system. It is considered relatively safe because it does not employ striking (kicks, punches, elbows, etc.), yet it is effective because of its ability to respond well to numerous types of realistic situations. As has been said many times about fights: they almost always start standing, but end up quickly on the ground. Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu  (BJJ) provides unlimited avenues to success from standing and ground positions. A hallmark of BJJ is that it is constantly evolving and improving to solve the real problems discovered by the competitors and instructors of the art. Another reason for the popularity and success of BJJ lies in the fact that it does not rely as much on size, strength, or speed as many fighting or self-defense systems. Over and over again, BJJ has proven this in real fight situations. BJJ utilizes take-downs, leverage on joints, and chokes to gain control over opponents. One of many remarkable aspects of this art: it gives students ability to defeat opponents from almost any position, even underneath an opponent. To an untrained eye, it is sometimes difficult to know who is in the best position when a BJJ fighter is involved, until it quickly ends in the defeat of the opponent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-concepts-the-goal-is-control&#34;&gt;Basic Concepts: The Goal is Control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you get overwhelmed with the myriad techniques, positions and submissions of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu, you need to understand the goal: complete control of your opponent. Your goal is not to bloody your opponent or injure them; the goal is control. In most martial arts where your objective is to destroy your opponent, dominating them by annihilation. In BJJ, the goal is to dominate with control. A student with excellent control has the luxury of deciding when, where, and how to apply a submission move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-is-control&#34;&gt;What is Control?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Control = Base + Position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;base-all-your-base-belong-to-us&#34;&gt;Base: &amp;ldquo;All Your Base Belong to Us&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Base simply means stability against loss of balance. A practitioner with good base is very difficult to unbalance. Judo was an innovative martial art, and a direct predecessor sport to Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu, in that it centered around unbalancing the opponent to obtain victory. This notion of unbalancing your opponent is a common aspect shared by wrestling, Submission Grappling, and BJJ. In competition, points are awarded for unbalancing the opponent. The two primary methods of unbalancing your opponent is take downs and sweeps. In both situations, you use technique to put your opponent on the ground and control him afterwards. It&amp;rsquo;s not enough just to trip them up and watch them fall. You must control them through the technique and afterwards to capitalize on your positional advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;submissions&#34;&gt;Submissions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A submission is a &amp;ldquo;finishing move&amp;rdquo; technique applied in order to force your opponent to quit the fight. When you submit, you signal submission by tapping your hand calling out &amp;ldquo;tap!&amp;rdquo; If you make your opponent submit, you win the fight, and must immediately stop whatever finishing move you were applying that caused the tap. Common submissions are chokes and joint locks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-clinch&#34;&gt;The Clinch&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clinch is a position where both opponents are &amp;ldquo;tied up&amp;rdquo; from standing or the knees. Typically your right hand is behind your opponent&amp;rsquo;s neck and your left hand is grabbing his right triceps behind his elbow. Both partners hold each other this way. Many matches start with opponents &amp;ldquo;tying up in the clinch.&amp;rdquo; This move shows an example of a move starting from the clinch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;entering-or-gapping-the-distance&#34;&gt;Entering or Gapping the Distance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Jeet Kune Do, Bruce Lee defined entering as the process of closing the gap between striking and grappling range. Entering is key in BJJ in that the practitioner wants to gap the distance from the standup fight to take the opponent to the ground and leverage BJJ technique. A fight at striking distance (where kicks and punches are employed) must be &amp;ldquo;gapped&amp;rdquo; thereby bringing the fight to grappling distance. There are numerous methods of entering including shoots, pummeling for underhooks, etc. In traditional BJJ, many of the takedowns were pulled directly from the Judo playbook. As the fusion of grappling arts has continued, wrestling takedowns have become more popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-relationship-of-bjj-to-other-martial-arts&#34;&gt;The Relationship of BJJ to Other Martial Arts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world of Combat Sports (&amp;ldquo;External&amp;rdquo; Martial Arts) is divided broadly into 2 groups: grappling (ground fighting) and striking arts. Under the grappling sports, a broad sub-category called &amp;ldquo;submission wrestling&amp;rdquo; indicates a grappling sport that allows an opponent to force submission of another opponent during sparring. When one opponents wants to quit due to pain, exhaustion, fear, injury, etc., they submit, thereby yielding to the winner. Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu is a submission wrestling sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most experts agree that a &amp;ldquo;complete fighter&amp;rdquo; must effectively use grappling and striking systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;sport-or-art&#34;&gt;Sport or Art?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many BJJ and Submission Grappling students have distanced themselves from the traditional martial arts by using modernized and sports-related terminology.  The Training center is referred to as a gym rather than a dojo. The instructor is referred to as a coach, not a sensei*.  The system is highly competition-focused and is just as often referred to as a sport as it is a martial art. While the system primarily originated in Brazil, very few techniques are referred to commonly with Portuguese names. This is not just a reflection of the modernization of the sport. It is also beneficial in taking the system mainstream and attracting audiences outside the pure martial arts crowd. This provides faster absorption across cultures. Rather than having to drag along cultural heritage, the sport simply focuses on the technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese terminology was used here, but Korean, Chinese, or other languages are often used in other systems depending on the origins of the art.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;technique&#34;&gt;Technique&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technique in BJJ is constantly evolving. Unlike &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; martial arts, which have encoded a limited set of techniques within forms for centuries, BJJ changes yearly. Fundamentals don&amp;rsquo;t vary much, but the competitive aspect of the sport forces moves and counters to be improved. Innovation is constant, as is seen from coaches like Eddie Bravo and competitors like Genki Sudo and BJ Penn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;competitive-brazilian-jiu-jitsu&#34;&gt;Competitive Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the popularity of BJJ has grown, the sport of competitive Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu  has exploded with it. Like judo and wrestling, it is seen as a safe, yet effective system for demonstrating command of an opponent. Typical Karate or Tae Kwon Do competitors are required to &amp;ldquo;pull their punches&amp;rdquo; (apply little or no contact) for safety. This reduces the ability to truly test which fighter is in command in closed matches involving these participants. After all, how can a system of battle truly be tested if the participants only shoot blanks? &amp;ldquo;Full contact&amp;rdquo; Karate competitions are typically diminished in esteem by numerous bloody injuries and bruises. In BJJ competitions, competitors can compete at full speed with significantly reduced risk of injury. When an opponent feels too much pressure as a technique is applied, they can &amp;ldquo;tap&amp;rdquo; to instantly end the match. Try that with a full-speed punch! By the time the punch has landed, the damage is done. Not so with BJJ. This is one reason BJJ has kept the root name &amp;ldquo;Jiu-Jitsu .&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Ju&amp;rdquo; literally means &amp;ldquo;gentle&amp;rdquo; in Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;effective-against-larger-stronger-opponents&#34;&gt;Effective Against Larger, Stronger Opponents&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Larger and stronger fighters are universally amazed when they fight a BJJ practitioner. Since they have relied on their physical attributes for past success, they are unprepared for the balance of favor tipping away from them in the face of a smaller opponent! The keys to this &amp;ldquo;sleight of hand&amp;rdquo; are simple. First, chokes and leverage against joints. While on average a larger opponent can hit harder than a smaller one, their joints all bend and respond to pain the same! Second, the ability of the BJJ fighter to close the distance, literally attaching themselves to their opponent thereby reducing the larger opponent&amp;rsquo;s ability to use their advantage. A big guy needs air to their body and blood to their brain just like the rest of us! Take it away, and down goes Goliath!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;great-for-kids-and-women&#34;&gt;Great for Kids and Women&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the lack of violent and dangerous strikes, its ability to give participants advantage over stronger, larger attackers, and its competitive sporting side, BJJ is a fantastic self-defense system for children and women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;great-for-people-with-injuries-and-disabilities&#34;&gt;Great for People with Injuries and Disabilities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a constantly evolving art and sport, BJJ has shown itself to be highly resilient to limitations in the student&amp;rsquo;s abilities. For example, students can &amp;ldquo;adapt their game&amp;rdquo; when training with an injured foot. Visually impaired students have found success in this sport. Could a visually impaired man out-box a visually able boxer? Not a chance. But with the skills of BJJ, the visually impaired person man can attach himself to the boxer like a boa constrictor, and the boxer&amp;rsquo;s best attacks are useless. Read my blog article on blindfolded grappling for some fun training ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;training&#34;&gt;Training&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training in BJJ is traditionally done wearing a gi (a Japanese Judo kimono). Since there is lots of grabbing and pulling, these garments outlast street clothes. BJJ instructors have been diversifying their training to include &amp;ldquo;no-gi&amp;rdquo; training (in street clothes like shorts and a tee shirt), in order to improve the realism of the training. No-gi training is also called Submission Grappling. Competitive BJJ has also embraced this direction, often having separate no-gi divisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike many other martial arts, all BJJ training is done with a partner. Whether drilling techniques or sparring (often called &amp;ldquo;grappling&amp;rdquo;), it takes two to train in BJJ. Most techniques from BJJ are executed from one of the basic positions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guard - you on your back with your legs wrapped around your opponent&amp;rsquo;s hips.
Mount - Your opponent on his back with you straddling their abdomen (essentially &amp;ldquo;sitting&amp;rdquo; on their stomach).
Rear mount or back mount - you on the back of your opponent, with your heels holding around the front of his hips.
Side control or side mount- your opponent on his back with you lying (typically perpendicular) chest-to-chest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a detailed catalog of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu techniques, see Dave&amp;rsquo;s BJJ Technique Catalog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ranking&#34;&gt;Ranking&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adult ranking is designated by colored belt and progresses from white, blue, purple, brown, then black. It can typically takes a student well over 3 years to get blue belt, and up to 6 to get purple belt. Hard, consistent training, successful competition, and most of all consistently challenging upper ranks (and beating them on occasion) is the only way to progress up the ranks. There are typically no formal tests for BJJ rank promotion. This is another distinct feature of BJJ. Most white and blue belts are quite experienced fighters by the time they are ready to reach the next rank. There is no comparing the fighting skills of a senior white belt in BJJ to one from most other martial arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ranking for children progresses from white, orange, to green. At this point the child stays at the rank of green until they are 16 years of age. They are then eligible for promotion to adult blue belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some gyms employ &amp;ldquo;striping&amp;rdquo; to indicate progress between major rank levels. Stripes are not formally recognized nor are they standardized, but they do help students maintain their perspective when holding a rank for a number of years. For example, I was a purple belt for about 4 years. It was nice to get a stripe each year I was training to signify the experience and progress made that year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black belt &amp;ldquo;dan&amp;rdquo; degrees, signified by stripes, are more formal ranks than colored &amp;ldquo;kyu&amp;rdquo; rank belts. While there is generally little agreement about what it takes to get from one black belt level to the next, they are universally recognized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;born-from-judo&#34;&gt;Born from Judo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu is a refined and distant derivative of Japanese Jiu-Jitsu . Jiu-Jitsu  is actually a broad family of systems emanating from Japan in the mid 1800s. In fact, Jiu-Jitsu  is the seminal art of so many systems, it is impossible to define a single &amp;ldquo;way&amp;rdquo; of Jiu-Jitsu . One particular lineage of Jiu-Jitsu  ended up in Karate, another in Judo, etc. The story of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu  begins in 1880s Japan and a man named Jigoro Kano. At his school, originally called Kano-ryu jiu-jitsu (literally &amp;ldquo;Kano&amp;rsquo;s school of gentle techniques&amp;rdquo;), Kano popularized the training style of full-speed sparring, where opponents work at maximum force yet not injure themselves. This system became known as Judo (the &amp;ldquo;gentle way&amp;rdquo;).  One of Kano&amp;rsquo;s top students was Mitsuo Maeda, who was also known as Conde Koma (&amp;ldquo;Count of Combat&amp;rdquo;). Maeda traveled to the United States in 1904 and after a Judo demonstration at West Point, began competitive fighting internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-gracie-family&#34;&gt;The Gracie Family&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1914, Maeda moved to Brazil to help Japanese immigrants. There he met Gastï¿½o Gracie, the son of Scottish immigrant George Gracie. Gracie had assisted Maeda greatly, and in return, Maeda taught Judo to Gracie&amp;rsquo;s son Carlos at Maeda&amp;rsquo;s school in Brazil. Carlos, who was 14 when he started training, almost immediately started adapting the techniques to be more effective in open street fights where anything goes (vale tudo, in Portuguese). Carlos Gracie, like many fighters of his time, continued a tradition of &amp;ldquo;challenge matches&amp;rdquo; against fighters of various styles. He was famous throughout Brazil for his success in these fights. Later, Carlos taught his brothers Oswaldo, Jorge, Gastao and Helio. The first academy was opened in Rio de Janeiro in 1925. Carlos and Helio were responsible for creating the basis upon which Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu  exists today. Helio was small and frail, yet would consistently beat larger opponents. The Gracies began to emigrate to the United States after 1972, where they opened schools and hosted competitions and successful challenge matches. Most Gracie schools use the term &amp;ldquo;Gracie Jiu-Jitsu .&amp;rdquo; This is synonymous with Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;join-us&#34;&gt;Join Us!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit &lt;a href=&#34;http://austinjiujitsu.com&#34;&gt;Austin Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about opportunities to explore Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-head-coach-david-thomas&#34;&gt;About Head Coach David Thomas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/dave-thomas/&#34;&gt;About Coach Dave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sign Up With Us!</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/sign-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/post/sign-up/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-members&#34;&gt;New Members&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes! We are always accepting new students of any experience level!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;follow-these-steps&#34;&gt;Follow These Steps&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Come in and fill out a waiver, and then join us on the mats! First class is always free!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Punched Will Make You a Better Grappler</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/blog-getting-punched/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/blog-getting-punched/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Do your training buddy a favor and smack the shit out of him next time you spar. Will he forgive you? Hell, he should &lt;em&gt;thank you&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/blog-flow&#34;&gt;Flow&lt;/a&gt; is great and technique drilling is absolutely important, but&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you aren&amp;rsquo;t regularly putting yourself into the mindset of a real fight, you aren&amp;rsquo;t preparing yourself for a real fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;The easiest way to do that is to get your grapplers to hit each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ground-rules&#34;&gt;Ground Rules&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partner up with someone you trust in your gym. You need to safely take each other just past the limit of your individual skills, but not too far.
Start from a disadvantaged position: a grab or tackle from behind, on the ground under the mount, or wadded up against the wall under a ground and pound assault.
Work this drill from the attacker and defender positions. Attackers will improve their top game and will learn how to control people from scrambling out of an attack. Defenders will improve their confidence and fight success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use a timer. Start at 1:30 and build every couple of weeks to work your way up to 5 minutes. Then add another round. I’ve found when you have a clock, there are fewer tap-outs from exhaustion or beat-down. When you train against the clock, you will typically try to “survive the round” rather than give up.
Keep the “tap out” escape hatch but understand that a tap-out in a real street fight is equivalent to a hospital or morgue trip: it means you gave up against a bad guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;drill-responses&#34;&gt;Drill Responses&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is to win in a encounter like this, or at least survive and escape. We drill these every week in our MMA class at Austin Jiu-Jitsu. Here are tactics in order of a prioritized “survival timeline,” where those you do first are most important to know and more likely to be successful. If you are going to drill one thing on the mat tonight, drill #1!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrambling out from under an attack. As much as we love BJJ and submission grappling, it’s not smart to stay stuck on the bottom. Drilling scrambling out of ground and pound attacks (from mount, side, half guard, and guard) will help you prepare for this. Scrambling out is different from sweeping in one important respect. In a scramble, you are explosively evading and pushing your opponent off before control position is established.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tying up or slowing an attack. If you can’t scramble out, you’ll need to slow down or stop your opponent’s strikes. Do this to buy yourself time to sweep or scramble out.
Escaping control or sweeping your attacker. Once he gets control position, your ability to scramble is reduced. You will need to work hard to defend and tie up your opponent to buy yourself time to technically escape or sweep. This is a much more technical game than an explosive scramble, and as such presents more risk. You need more skill and often more time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submitting the attacker from the bottom. Statistically, this isn’t a great bet, so I’m putting it at the bottom of the list. Sure, a submission specialist and elite-level MMA fighter like Antônio Rodrigo Nogueira has found submissions in &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of his fights, but you shouldn’t spend a lot of time getting hammered from the top unless you are truly great at tying up your attacker and nailing submissions. Submitting from the top is a great plan, so don’t mistake my point here; maintaining bottom position with a plan of submitting your attacker from the bottom is less likely to be successful than the other approaches described above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you drill each of these, make a note of which ones get you beat up the least. You’ll notice that as you go from 1 to 4, you get hit more and take longer to win or escape. Of course, in a real fight, you’ll employ many of these simultaneously. Chain the drills together and switch attackers based on who is on top. This will improve your ability to survive a real fight. Most MMA guys know this, but a lot of pure BJJ folks lack this experience and may make the mistake of focusing on submissions only. This is the same type of myopia that strikers without grappling experience suffer from. Don’t make their mistake in reverse. Prepare for getting hit by grappling with strikes allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let the Bodies Hit the Flow</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/blog-flow/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.herokuapp.com/blog/blog-flow/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flow rolling is to a grappler what improvisation is to a jazz musician. It&amp;rsquo;s a fun, creative experience that develops your skills and helps you connect with your partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every grappling gym has its own way to get grapplers warmed up and ready for maximum athletic performance and the rigors of the full intensity of ground fighting. I prefer what I call &amp;ldquo;flow rolling&amp;rdquo;: a series of grappling rounds at low intensity with no submissions allowed and an emphasis on constant motion, cooperation, and resilience over static resistance and competitiveness. Since most grappling matches demand explosiveness, strength, and competiveness, flow rolling puts many students off their game, but the benefits can be substantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;here-s-my-pitch-for-why-you-should-flow-roll-every-time-you-warm-up&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my pitch for why you should flow roll every time you warm up&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximize athletic performance. Studies have demonstrated that athletes who warmed up for 20 minutes just before intense athletic activity are actually stronger and have improved muscle flexibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanded creativity due to lack of competitive pressure. When you aren&amp;rsquo;t fighting off submission attempts or stuck inside a tight guard, your mind has more time to work though new moves, alternate routes, and unconventional ideas. You can improve your mindset and patience about working through disadvantaged positions. Creativity is limited when you are under pressure. Relax your mind and let the ideas flow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved mat dexterity and coordination. Watching 2 experienced flow rollers is really impressive. You can develop improved mat dexterity with consistent flow rolling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s fun and develops teamwork. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice change to roll around with your mat partners when you aren&amp;rsquo;t trying to submit them. Put a smile on your face and enjoy the interactive dance. I tell the youngsters in my kids class &amp;ldquo;play like monkeys!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So go ahead, improv like a jazz musician. Play like a monkey. &lt;em&gt;Flow roll&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>