<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</title>
    <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/tags/competition/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>jits</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jitshappens.com/tags/competition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Jenny Thomas, AJJ Hall of Famer</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/jenny-thomas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/jenny-thomas/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;While Jenny is now retired from competitive Jiu-Jitsu, she was an early super-star at Austin Jiu-Jitsu. This page recognizes her accomplishments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jenny Thomas of Austin, Texas began training at the age of 7. She began competing at the age of 9 and coaching kids in ground fighting at 14. She was the Austin Jiu-Jitsu Assistant Coach for Children&amp;rsquo;s Programs. She trained with the Austin Jiu-Jitsu adult competition team and was a competitive swimmer with her high school team, Longhorn Aquatics in Austin, and The University of Chicago&amp;rsquo;s varsity women&amp;rsquo;s team. Jenny graduated with a degree in Economics from The University of Chicago and now works in Austin, Texas in the finance industry. She is an avid fitness junkie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jitshappens.com/img/jenny-thomas.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jenny Thomas&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;highlights&#34;&gt;Highlights&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu Blue Belt - 16 years of training&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State, regional, and national-level competitor in Submission Grappling, Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and wrestling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self defense seminar instructor, targeted at self-defense for girls ages 7-13.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 years coaching of children&amp;rsquo;s grappling programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Seasons of Wrestling (folkstyle), including a 4th-place finish in an all-boys divisions at the HOT Nationals, 2007&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;brief-competition-history&#34;&gt;Brief Competition History&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st, Women&amp;rsquo;s Advanced Grappling Division, Austin Martial Arts Festival 2008&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st, No Gi Women&amp;rsquo;s: North American Grappling (NAGA) Champion - , 134 lbs and under. She was the youngest and lightest competitor. Dallas, 2008&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2nd, Women&amp;rsquo;s gi: BJJ Winter Wars 6. Dallas, 2008. She was the youngest and lightest competitor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2nd, Women&amp;rsquo;s no gi: BJJ Winter Wars 6. Dallas, 2008. She was the youngest and lightest competitor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st, Women&amp;rsquo;s gi: Dallas, 2007. First adult competition at the age of 14.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4th, 110 lb 13 year olds, Div 5 Open.: Heart of Texas Wrestling Nationals, 2007. 4th out of 16 in an all-boys division.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st, 110 lb 13 year olds, Div 5 Open. SW Austin wrestling competition. All wins by pin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st, No gi Kids: Carlson Gracie Open, Dripping Springs, TX, 2005. She was the only girl competing, all wins by submission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st, Gi Kids: Carlson Gracie Open, Dripping Springs, TX, 2005. She was the only girl competing, all wins by submission, all in under 1 minute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2nd, Kids Advanced no gi: Houston Grapplemania, 2005. She got a 15 second triangle submission in round 1. Her one loss was by points to the phenom, Drake Dudley.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st, Kids no gi: Dripping Springs, 2006. She was the only girl competing and won all matches by submission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st, Kids no gi: Dripping Springs, TX 2004. All-boys division, all wins by submission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2nd, Teens gi: Smack-Down In H-Town. Houston, 2004. In a teen division as an 11 year old.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2nd, Kids Beginner Gi, BJJ Winter Wars 1. Dallas, 2002&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See videos of many of Jenny&amp;rsquo;s competition performances &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/budoatemaildotcom/search?query=jenny&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;community&#34;&gt;Community&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jenny was the founder and president of Girl Power of Texas, a non-profit organization providing mentoring for girls in underserved areas of Central Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>