<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</title>
    <link>http://jitshappens.com/tags/bjj/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>jits</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://jitshappens.com/tags/bjj/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What I Do</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/post/services/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 11:43:42 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/post/services/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brazilian-jiu-jitsu&#34;&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-world-s-most-effective-ground-fighting-system&#34;&gt;The world&amp;rsquo;s most effective ground-fighting system!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popularized by the Gracie and UFC and proven in fights world-wide, Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu will give you an edge over larger, stronger opponents. We&amp;rsquo;ll help you gain an advantage through superior technique, leverage, speed, and stamina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/post/brazilian-jiu-jitsu/&#34;&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; Submission Grappling&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strength and Mobility&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-history&#34;&gt;My History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I have been coaching BJJ since 2003&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I founded &lt;a href=&#34;http://austinjiujitsu.com&#34;&gt;Austin Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/a&gt; in 2003 and developed that gym and a great group of students over 14 years. My committed to developing student potential through safe, balanced, and effective self-defense training, leveraging the concepts Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and ground fighting (Submission Grappling) is as strong today as it was when I started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-head-coach-david-thomas&#34;&gt;About Head Coach David Thomas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/post/dave-thomas/&#34;&gt;About Coach Dave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coach Dave Thomas</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/post/dave-thomas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/post/dave-thomas/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is great happiness in the lifelong pursuit of human potential.&amp;rdquo;&lt;cite&gt;-Coach David Thomas&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dave Thomas of Seattle, WA is founding coach at Austin Jiu-Jitsu (Self-Defense Mentor, LLC). While Dave now trains and works out of Seattle, he is proud to have built Austin Jiu-Jitsu from a small group of friends in his garage to a thriving community of dedicated students from 2003 - 2017. He visits the gym when he comes to town to roll with his students and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;some-of-dave-s-contributions-include&#34;&gt;Some of Dave&amp;rsquo;s contributions include&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His student-centric approach, helping them on their personal journey toward mastery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His highly technical skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An unconventional, creative fighting style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Development of a successful women&amp;rsquo;s program, which enjoys a significantly high ratio of women to men &amp;ndash; which is unusual in BJJ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing the talent of his team of coaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His prolific writing on training, coaching, and service toward the student in his blog, &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/blog&#34;&gt;Jits Happens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The creation of &lt;a href=&#34;bjjtech.com&#34;&gt;BJJTech.com&lt;/a&gt;, the largest single-sourced collection of BJJ techniques on the web.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/img/authors/dave-thomas.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Coach Dave&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dave has been has been training, competing, and coaching since January 1985.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;life-off-the-mats&#34;&gt;Life Off the Mats&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he isn&amp;rsquo;t training and coaching, Dave enjoys a great &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/dcthomas&#34;&gt;career&lt;/a&gt; in software product entrepreneurship, where he is a product leader at &lt;a href=&#34;http://indeed.com&#34;&gt;Indeed&lt;/a&gt;. He has two children, &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/blog/jenny-thomas/&#34;&gt;Jenny&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/budoatemaildotcom/search?query=zach&#34;&gt;Zach&lt;/a&gt;, who both grew up on the mats with him at Austin Jiu-Jitsu. Dave&amp;rsquo;s wife Christine previously led the Austin Jiu-Jitsu women&amp;rsquo;s program and has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/christinegthomas&#34;&gt;career&lt;/a&gt; in high-tech finance. Dave and Christine both studied business at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chicagobooth.edu/&#34;&gt;University of Chicago&amp;rsquo;s Booth School of Business&lt;/a&gt; (2016 and 2017 MBA grads).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;accomplishments-and-qualifications&#34;&gt;Accomplishments and Qualifications&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu Black Belt (under Carlos Gracie Jr. Black Belt Travis Tooke). Coaching since 2003, training since 1995.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2008 North American Grappling (NAGA) Champion, Brown and Black belt Division (160 lb and under, Director, Gi)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Black belts, including BJJ, Japanese Karate (AAKF, JKA Shotokan)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State, national, and international-level competition experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certified USA Wrestling Coach for competitive youth wrestling programs. 3 seasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground fighting trainer for law enforcement, EMT, and military personnel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experienced referee in local and state-level BJJ and Submission Grappling competitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MMA instructor 2008 - 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diverse martial arts training background including MMA, Thai Boxing, Jeet Kune Do, Karate, Aikido, and Judo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Licensed by the Texas Department of Public Safety Private Security Bureau (2005)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Licensed by the Texas Combative Sports/Boxing Commission as an MMA Cornerman (2009)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed BJJTech.com, the largest single-sourced collection of BJJ techniques on the web.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;jits-happens&#34;&gt;Jits Happens&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read Dave&amp;rsquo;s blog, &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/blog&#34;&gt;Jits Happens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Injuries</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/injuries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/injuries/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I share my tips on injury prevention, safety in training, and some of the injuries I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in my time training in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu. It is my personal perspective based on my experience. Use it as a reference only. You will certainly experience your own set of injuries if you train long enough or hard enough. Let me repeat that: if you train long enough and hard enough, you will get injured. No training worth the time or money happens without hard work and long duration. If you intend to get good at this, expect to work through discomfort, pain, and injuries. Some prevention is possible, but if you are going to really improve your game, you are going to put yourself in harm&amp;rsquo;s way. Be prepared for the consequences and the rewards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The injuries sustained in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu are similar to what you&amp;rsquo;d see in most contact sports. Soreness (which gets much less frequent as you become accustomed to the training) is by far the the most common side effect. But soreness is just your body telling you it wants to rest after a good workout. That&amp;rsquo;s not an injury! Soreness for me is a simple barometer that tells me that I trained hard enough yesterday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-prevention-tips&#34;&gt;Basic Prevention Tips&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the techniques correctly - injuries are very commonly the result of poor training. Learn solid technique at the Austin Jiu-Jitsu BJJ Technique Catalog, and read the warnings there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protection - &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/blog/gear-up-for-class/&#34;&gt;get the right gear for training&lt;/a&gt;. Use equipment such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mouthguard - required of all my students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Earguards - Never wrestle without them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wrestling shoes - if you are nervous about your toes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wraps -  In boxing drills, wrap your hands to protect your hand bones. Your coach can show you how to wrap them. Wraps are cheap and make a big difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;hygiene&#34;&gt;Hygiene&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my experience, risk of infection comes from two sources: untreated scratches and microbes introduced into the training area. Microbes can cause infections and skin conditions like ringworm. The best prevention is cleanliness. Here are some tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your nails short and clean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wash your hands and face before class (I&amp;rsquo;ll assume you all wash up after using the potty room)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only wear clean clothes to class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always leave your shoes outside the mats. Lots of nasty microbes are on the bottoms of your shoes. If they get on the mats, they can cause problems!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shower immediately after class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not come to class if you have any kind of infection (skin rash, common cold, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you see a rash, blister, or sores on your training partner, don&amp;rsquo;t train with them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use skin protectant. Google it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disinfect the mats with an antimicrobial solution at least once per week. We do! We&amp;rsquo;ve never had an outbreak at our gym!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;treatment&#34;&gt;Treatment&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rest, Ice, Compression, and Elevation (RICE)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are very sore, rest. Don&amp;rsquo;t overdo it! Ice your injuries. Elevate them to reduce swelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set Limits with Your Training Partners - If you are nervous about sparring with someone much bigger, stronger, or more capable than you, tell them so. Ask them to be careful and always quit the match if you sense danger. The beauty of BJJ is that you can always &amp;ldquo;tap out&amp;rdquo; and stop immediately. Most advanced students know how to &amp;ldquo;throttle down&amp;rdquo; so this is more commonly an issue with beginners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be a hero. Tap if it hurts, if you are dizzy, or have any reason to suspect you can&amp;rsquo;t continue the match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See a Doctor - If you think you have an injury, see a doctor. Take responsibility for your training and your healthcare. It&amp;rsquo;s your body!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be the source of injuries at your gym - Most gyms have a couple of guys who are a bit dangerous. They are usually beginners and don&amp;rsquo;t know how to safely take someone down or apply technically correct submissions. If your favorite submission is a neck crank, you&amp;rsquo;re probably not making many friends at your gym. Be considerate of your training partners and their skill and fitness levels. Read about disallowed techniques, below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;common-injuries-you-can-expect-every-week-or-two&#34;&gt;Common injuries you can expect every week or two&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my personal observation, the most common injuries in order of prevalence are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bruises - These are most commonly from people grabbing your arms or legs. Most BJJ students will carry their bruises like a badge of honor. The only interesting perspective I can lend to this is that the longer I&amp;rsquo;ve trained the less I see bruises. I have no idea if that is an indication of my capillaries changing or me just getting harder to grab on to!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scratches - If you keep your finger and toenails short, you&amp;rsquo;ll help reduce the scratches. See below for more prevention tips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;less-common-injuries&#34;&gt;Less common injuries&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloody lip - If you don&amp;rsquo;t wear a mouthpiece, a bump against someone&amp;rsquo;s knee, head, or elbow will bloody the inside of your mouth. A mouthpiece will reduce the chances of this significantly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Torn ligaments - I&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of any torn ligaments that required surgery, but plenty of tears occur that require recuperation time. For example, I hurt my elbow in a competition once that required a few weeks off. It took several months for my arm to feel &amp;ldquo;back to normal.&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;ve heard of a couple of students tearing the intercostals between their ribs, which is quite painful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rare-injuries-more-serious-stuff&#34;&gt;Rare Injuries - More Serious Stuff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cauliflower Ear - Over time, ear injuries can cause cauliflower ear to wrestlers and boxers. I recommend all students buy and wear ear guards during wrestling and any drills which put pressure on the ears. As I tell my students, if you see me put mine on, you should be wearing yours too! Google it to learn more. I have never had a student develop this condition, but one student had to be treated by a doctor to prevent it when he had some swelling on his ear. He is now a dedicated ear guard wearer!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toe Drags - This is an injury where you step on your own big toe as it gets caught under your foot while stepping forward on the mats. It sounds hard to imagine, but it has happened to me. It hurts like heck and can really stress out your toe ligament. This took a couple of months to heal. While it healed, I wore wrestling shoes and was able to train at full intensity. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard of another couple of students getting toe drags. It is one of the most frustrating injuries, as it is one of the only &amp;ldquo;self-inflicted&amp;rdquo; injuries you can sustain on the mats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breaks - The most common bone break I&amp;rsquo;ve seen is a pinky toe break. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen at least 10 of those in my years of training. The wrestling mats are not kind to your toes. The solution to this is wrestling shoes. Wear them and you&amp;rsquo;ll probably never get a foot injury. In nearly a decade, I&amp;rsquo;ve only seen one broken bone (an arm) at a competition &amp;ndash; not during regular training. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard about another guy who got his arm broken in the class of another school here in town, but not in mine!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dislocations - I&amp;rsquo;ve seen one dislocated shoulder in training. It popped right back in, but was a very painful experience for the poor student it happened to. I have also seen one dislocated elbow in a competition. Both of these were due to sloppy arm bars. I have seen several dislocated pinky toes (again, wrestling shoes will nearly eliminate the chance of this).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lacerations - I have seen remarkably little blood in my gym. Since we aren&amp;rsquo;t punching each other, it is rare to see split skin. We&amp;rsquo;ve only had one serious cut that required stitches, and in that case it was &amp;ldquo;self-inflicted&amp;rdquo; in that the student who got cut slammed into his opponents knee when trying to take him down. Lesson learned: don&amp;rsquo;t slam your head into someone&amp;rsquo;s knee!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;uncomfortable-situations&#34;&gt;Uncomfortable Situations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the most uncomfortable situations that arise on the mats are not related to injuries. Nevertheless, they are worth mentioning here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choking out - Prevention: TAP OUT! In over a decade of training, I&amp;rsquo;ve witnessed 5 people pass out from a choke in regular training (me being one of them). I can tell you from experience what it was like. In short, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t fun! If you ever ask someone who got choked out in training, their story will sound a lot like this. I was getting choked and thought I could escape. I was wrong. The next thing I knew I was waking up on the mats with a very nervous student standing over me. I had a headache and was very disoriented. It felt like I woke up from a nap with a hangover. I was &amp;ldquo;out&amp;rdquo; for about 5 seconds. It took about a minute or so for me to get my bearings and be able to stand up. Within a few more minutes I was ready to start training again. Although, I was a bit embarrassed for not tapping out. Frankly, seeing someone pass out is far more stressful. A passed out person looks dead. Their eyes are often staring out into space. To minimize risk here, don&amp;rsquo;t let children choke each other in regular sparring. It requires individual adult attention to each match, and without enough sets of eyes on the mats, it&amp;rsquo;s best to only allow chokes in controlled demonstrations.  On my mats, kids are not allowed to choke below the rank of yellow belt, and even then require supervision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tossing your cookies - This is very easy to prevent. Don&amp;rsquo;t train with food in your tummy! 7 people I know have barfed from the intensity of training with too much food in their stomachs. I was one of them, so again, this comes from experience. If you train hard in any sport, you really can&amp;rsquo;t have any food in your stomach. Different people have different windows of time they need to make sure they are safe. I won&amp;rsquo;t eat within 2 hours of training. I know others that won&amp;rsquo;t train for 4 hours. Here&amp;rsquo;s how my barfing experience went. I was set to compete and was assuming that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have my first fight until after noon. At 9:00 in the morning, I ate a huge breakfast thinking it would last me all day. Every other competition I had been to had the advanced belts fighting last. In this one, they fought in parallel on 3 different mats (kids on one, women on another, guys on the third). So, at about 10:30, they called me to fight. I fought like a wildcat for 8 minutes. Immediately after the match was over, I felt awful. I was much more lethargic than I should have been and was pretty dizzy. About 10 minutes later, I puked my brains out in a trashcan outside the gym. It was really nasty. I felt great once I was done, though!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;disallowed-techniques-for-safety&#34;&gt;Disallowed Techniques for Safety&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While all techniques should be fair game for instructors to demonstrate, to prevent injury, some should not be allowed in full speed sparring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any joint manipulation outside the range that is safe for that joint. All techniques have a safe way to apply them that will prevent injury. If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand the way to perform the technique, ask your coach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any move that is done at a speed greater than the ability for your partner to react and submit before injury. In other words, give your partner a chance to tap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The heel hook - Unsafe at any speed above slow. Always avoid sideways torque to the knee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The neck crank - This technique is done from numerous angles, but is never accomplished without unnecessary stress to the vertebrae in the neck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lanyngeal chokes - Any choke that puts pressure on the air passage is unsafe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slams - Takedowns where your opponent is dropped from any height above your knees are unsafe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any takedown or sweep where you cannot guarantee your partner will fall into a safe place on the mats. When throwing your partner, make sure they have plenty of open mat space to land in. Other people may be there!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single finger grabs - BJJ is all about control, which requires lots of grabbing. When you grab and pull on a single digit of your opponent, you risk breaking or straining it. Always grab 3 or more fingers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facial cranks - Not surprisingly, excessive pressure on the face will make someone tap, but they&amp;rsquo;ll label you as unsafe and probably avoid you when sparring in the future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most back cranks, such as the &amp;ldquo;Boston Crab&amp;rdquo; - as in the case of neck cranks, this is an unnecessary risk of serious injury&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;get-out-there-and-have-fun-but-be-safe&#34;&gt;Get out there and have fun, but be safe!&lt;/h5&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gearing Up</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/gear-up-for-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/gear-up-for-class/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This article helps new students get the gear they need to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a checklist for organizing your trip to class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gym bag to store all this stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jiu-jitsu gi for gi classes. The white belt is purchased separately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board shorts and rashguard for no-gi classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mouthpiece&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water bottle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flip flops &amp;ndash; but leave them outside the mat room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A towel for wiping up sweat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;gi&#34;&gt;Gi&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good gi will last you years, so don&amp;rsquo;t go for the cheapos. There are no stores that sell good jiu-jitsu gis in Austin, so Google around and get something you like. Colors and patterns are cool. We aren&amp;rsquo;t a traditional school that is stuck with old white kimonos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;no-gi&#34;&gt;No Gi&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A no-gi class looks like a bunch of surfers in board shorts and rash guards. Academy has a great selection of reasonable (and good looking) rash guards for men and women, but their board shorts suck. Head to a surf shop and hit the clearance rack. No need to pay full price for this stuff, since top name brand items are pretty steep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;mouthpiece&#34;&gt;Mouthpiece&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can spend $4 on a boil and bite variety or you can spend $90 and get your dentist or orthodontist to make a really comfortable one. I have always gone with the dentist option since it is way more comfortable: you can breathe, talk, and it never slips off. I usually forget I&amp;rsquo;m even wearing it. You only need protection on the top teeth, not the double variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;ear-guards&#34;&gt;Ear guards&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always wear them, but lots of folks never do. We keep a community pool of this stuff here, so you can check out the variety we have here and decide what brand to look for online if you decide to wear them. They are intended to prevent a relatively rare ear &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/blog/injuries/&#34;&gt;injury&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;ve seen enough in my 13 years on the mats to want to avoid altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;wrestling-shoes&#34;&gt;Wrestling Shoes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only recommend wrestling shoes if you have a foot or toe injury. They are perfect for protecting a hurt foot while you train, but they get in the way for some of the tighter escapes and moves so aren&amp;rsquo;t recommended for regular training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;knee-pads&#34;&gt;Knee Pads&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some folks have sensitive knees that are aggravated by the take-down practice we do. I recommend keeping one handy. If your knees get sensitive or bruised, your technique will suffer if you start to avoid dropping to your knee to correctly perform the take-down.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/post/brazilian-jiu-jitsu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/post/brazilian-jiu-jitsu/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-makes-bjj-so-different&#34;&gt;What makes BJJ so different?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu is widely regarded as the world&amp;rsquo;s most effective ground fighting (grappling) system. While it has been evolving since the early 1900s as a martial art, street fighting system, and sport, the last ten years have brought it the most popularity in America and abroad as a result of globally distributed media coverage of victories in numerous challenge matches and mixed martial arts competitions pitting athletes with mastery of various martial arts. It is a safe yet highly effective combat system. It is considered relatively safe because it does not employ striking (kicks, punches, elbows, etc.), yet it is effective because of its ability to respond well to numerous types of realistic situations. As has been said many times about fights: they almost always start standing, but end up quickly on the ground. Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu  (BJJ) provides unlimited avenues to success from standing and ground positions. A hallmark of BJJ is that it is constantly evolving and improving to solve the real problems discovered by the competitors and instructors of the art. Another reason for the popularity and success of BJJ lies in the fact that it does not rely as much on size, strength, or speed as many fighting or self-defense systems. Over and over again, BJJ has proven this in real fight situations. BJJ utilizes take-downs, leverage on joints, and chokes to gain control over opponents. One of many remarkable aspects of this art: it gives students ability to defeat opponents from almost any position, even underneath an opponent. To an untrained eye, it is sometimes difficult to know who is in the best position when a BJJ fighter is involved, until it quickly ends in the defeat of the opponent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-concepts-the-goal-is-control&#34;&gt;Basic Concepts: The Goal is Control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you get overwhelmed with the myriad techniques, positions and submissions of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu, you need to understand the goal: complete control of your opponent. Your goal is not to bloody your opponent or injure them; the goal is control. In most martial arts where your objective is to destroy your opponent, dominating them by annihilation. In BJJ, the goal is to dominate with control. A student with excellent control has the luxury of deciding when, where, and how to apply a submission move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-is-control&#34;&gt;What is Control?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Control = Base + Position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;base-all-your-base-belong-to-us&#34;&gt;Base: &amp;ldquo;All Your Base Belong to Us&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Base simply means stability against loss of balance. A practitioner with good base is very difficult to unbalance. Judo was an innovative martial art, and a direct predecessor sport to Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu, in that it centered around unbalancing the opponent to obtain victory. This notion of unbalancing your opponent is a common aspect shared by wrestling, Submission Grappling, and BJJ. In competition, points are awarded for unbalancing the opponent. The two primary methods of unbalancing your opponent is take downs and sweeps. In both situations, you use technique to put your opponent on the ground and control him afterwards. It&amp;rsquo;s not enough just to trip them up and watch them fall. You must control them through the technique and afterwards to capitalize on your positional advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;submissions&#34;&gt;Submissions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A submission is a &amp;ldquo;finishing move&amp;rdquo; technique applied in order to force your opponent to quit the fight. When you submit, you signal submission by tapping your hand calling out &amp;ldquo;tap!&amp;rdquo; If you make your opponent submit, you win the fight, and must immediately stop whatever finishing move you were applying that caused the tap. Common submissions are chokes and joint locks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-clinch&#34;&gt;The Clinch&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clinch is a position where both opponents are &amp;ldquo;tied up&amp;rdquo; from standing or the knees. Typically your right hand is behind your opponent&amp;rsquo;s neck and your left hand is grabbing his right triceps behind his elbow. Both partners hold each other this way. Many matches start with opponents &amp;ldquo;tying up in the clinch.&amp;rdquo; This move shows an example of a move starting from the clinch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;entering-or-gapping-the-distance&#34;&gt;Entering or Gapping the Distance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Jeet Kune Do, Bruce Lee defined entering as the process of closing the gap between striking and grappling range. Entering is key in BJJ in that the practitioner wants to gap the distance from the standup fight to take the opponent to the ground and leverage BJJ technique. A fight at striking distance (where kicks and punches are employed) must be &amp;ldquo;gapped&amp;rdquo; thereby bringing the fight to grappling distance. There are numerous methods of entering including shoots, pummeling for underhooks, etc. In traditional BJJ, many of the takedowns were pulled directly from the Judo playbook. As the fusion of grappling arts has continued, wrestling takedowns have become more popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-relationship-of-bjj-to-other-martial-arts&#34;&gt;The Relationship of BJJ to Other Martial Arts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world of Combat Sports (&amp;ldquo;External&amp;rdquo; Martial Arts) is divided broadly into 2 groups: grappling (ground fighting) and striking arts. Under the grappling sports, a broad sub-category called &amp;ldquo;submission wrestling&amp;rdquo; indicates a grappling sport that allows an opponent to force submission of another opponent during sparring. When one opponents wants to quit due to pain, exhaustion, fear, injury, etc., they submit, thereby yielding to the winner. Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu is a submission wrestling sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most experts agree that a &amp;ldquo;complete fighter&amp;rdquo; must effectively use grappling and striking systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;sport-or-art&#34;&gt;Sport or Art?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many BJJ and Submission Grappling students have distanced themselves from the traditional martial arts by using modernized and sports-related terminology.  The Training center is referred to as a gym rather than a dojo. The instructor is referred to as a coach, not a sensei*.  The system is highly competition-focused and is just as often referred to as a sport as it is a martial art. While the system primarily originated in Brazil, very few techniques are referred to commonly with Portuguese names. This is not just a reflection of the modernization of the sport. It is also beneficial in taking the system mainstream and attracting audiences outside the pure martial arts crowd. This provides faster absorption across cultures. Rather than having to drag along cultural heritage, the sport simply focuses on the technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese terminology was used here, but Korean, Chinese, or other languages are often used in other systems depending on the origins of the art.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;technique&#34;&gt;Technique&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technique in BJJ is constantly evolving. Unlike &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; martial arts, which have encoded a limited set of techniques within forms for centuries, BJJ changes yearly. Fundamentals don&amp;rsquo;t vary much, but the competitive aspect of the sport forces moves and counters to be improved. Innovation is constant, as is seen from coaches like Eddie Bravo and competitors like Genki Sudo and BJ Penn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;competitive-brazilian-jiu-jitsu&#34;&gt;Competitive Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the popularity of BJJ has grown, the sport of competitive Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu  has exploded with it. Like judo and wrestling, it is seen as a safe, yet effective system for demonstrating command of an opponent. Typical Karate or Tae Kwon Do competitors are required to &amp;ldquo;pull their punches&amp;rdquo; (apply little or no contact) for safety. This reduces the ability to truly test which fighter is in command in closed matches involving these participants. After all, how can a system of battle truly be tested if the participants only shoot blanks? &amp;ldquo;Full contact&amp;rdquo; Karate competitions are typically diminished in esteem by numerous bloody injuries and bruises. In BJJ competitions, competitors can compete at full speed with significantly reduced risk of injury. When an opponent feels too much pressure as a technique is applied, they can &amp;ldquo;tap&amp;rdquo; to instantly end the match. Try that with a full-speed punch! By the time the punch has landed, the damage is done. Not so with BJJ. This is one reason BJJ has kept the root name &amp;ldquo;Jiu-Jitsu .&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Ju&amp;rdquo; literally means &amp;ldquo;gentle&amp;rdquo; in Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;effective-against-larger-stronger-opponents&#34;&gt;Effective Against Larger, Stronger Opponents&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Larger and stronger fighters are universally amazed when they fight a BJJ practitioner. Since they have relied on their physical attributes for past success, they are unprepared for the balance of favor tipping away from them in the face of a smaller opponent! The keys to this &amp;ldquo;sleight of hand&amp;rdquo; are simple. First, chokes and leverage against joints. While on average a larger opponent can hit harder than a smaller one, their joints all bend and respond to pain the same! Second, the ability of the BJJ fighter to close the distance, literally attaching themselves to their opponent thereby reducing the larger opponent&amp;rsquo;s ability to use their advantage. A big guy needs air to their body and blood to their brain just like the rest of us! Take it away, and down goes Goliath!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;great-for-kids-and-women&#34;&gt;Great for Kids and Women&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the lack of violent and dangerous strikes, its ability to give participants advantage over stronger, larger attackers, and its competitive sporting side, BJJ is a fantastic self-defense system for children and women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;great-for-people-with-injuries-and-disabilities&#34;&gt;Great for People with Injuries and Disabilities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a constantly evolving art and sport, BJJ has shown itself to be highly resilient to limitations in the student&amp;rsquo;s abilities. For example, students can &amp;ldquo;adapt their game&amp;rdquo; when training with an injured foot. Visually impaired students have found success in this sport. Could a visually impaired man out-box a visually able boxer? Not a chance. But with the skills of BJJ, the visually impaired person man can attach himself to the boxer like a boa constrictor, and the boxer&amp;rsquo;s best attacks are useless. Read my blog article on blindfolded grappling for some fun training ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;training&#34;&gt;Training&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training in BJJ is traditionally done wearing a gi (a Japanese Judo kimono). Since there is lots of grabbing and pulling, these garments outlast street clothes. BJJ instructors have been diversifying their training to include &amp;ldquo;no-gi&amp;rdquo; training (in street clothes like shorts and a tee shirt), in order to improve the realism of the training. No-gi training is also called Submission Grappling. Competitive BJJ has also embraced this direction, often having separate no-gi divisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike many other martial arts, all BJJ training is done with a partner. Whether drilling techniques or sparring (often called &amp;ldquo;grappling&amp;rdquo;), it takes two to train in BJJ. Most techniques from BJJ are executed from one of the basic positions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guard - you on your back with your legs wrapped around your opponent&amp;rsquo;s hips.
Mount - Your opponent on his back with you straddling their abdomen (essentially &amp;ldquo;sitting&amp;rdquo; on their stomach).
Rear mount or back mount - you on the back of your opponent, with your heels holding around the front of his hips.
Side control or side mount- your opponent on his back with you lying (typically perpendicular) chest-to-chest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a detailed catalog of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu techniques, see Dave&amp;rsquo;s BJJ Technique Catalog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ranking&#34;&gt;Ranking&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adult ranking is designated by colored belt and progresses from white, blue, purple, brown, then black. It can typically takes a student well over 3 years to get blue belt, and up to 6 to get purple belt. Hard, consistent training, successful competition, and most of all consistently challenging upper ranks (and beating them on occasion) is the only way to progress up the ranks. There are typically no formal tests for BJJ rank promotion. This is another distinct feature of BJJ. Most white and blue belts are quite experienced fighters by the time they are ready to reach the next rank. There is no comparing the fighting skills of a senior white belt in BJJ to one from most other martial arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ranking for children progresses from white, orange, to green. At this point the child stays at the rank of green until they are 16 years of age. They are then eligible for promotion to adult blue belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some gyms employ &amp;ldquo;striping&amp;rdquo; to indicate progress between major rank levels. Stripes are not formally recognized nor are they standardized, but they do help students maintain their perspective when holding a rank for a number of years. For example, I was a purple belt for about 4 years. It was nice to get a stripe each year I was training to signify the experience and progress made that year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black belt &amp;ldquo;dan&amp;rdquo; degrees, signified by stripes, are more formal ranks than colored &amp;ldquo;kyu&amp;rdquo; rank belts. While there is generally little agreement about what it takes to get from one black belt level to the next, they are universally recognized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;born-from-judo&#34;&gt;Born from Judo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu is a refined and distant derivative of Japanese Jiu-Jitsu . Jiu-Jitsu  is actually a broad family of systems emanating from Japan in the mid 1800s. In fact, Jiu-Jitsu  is the seminal art of so many systems, it is impossible to define a single &amp;ldquo;way&amp;rdquo; of Jiu-Jitsu . One particular lineage of Jiu-Jitsu  ended up in Karate, another in Judo, etc. The story of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu  begins in 1880s Japan and a man named Jigoro Kano. At his school, originally called Kano-ryu jiu-jitsu (literally &amp;ldquo;Kano&amp;rsquo;s school of gentle techniques&amp;rdquo;), Kano popularized the training style of full-speed sparring, where opponents work at maximum force yet not injure themselves. This system became known as Judo (the &amp;ldquo;gentle way&amp;rdquo;).  One of Kano&amp;rsquo;s top students was Mitsuo Maeda, who was also known as Conde Koma (&amp;ldquo;Count of Combat&amp;rdquo;). Maeda traveled to the United States in 1904 and after a Judo demonstration at West Point, began competitive fighting internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-gracie-family&#34;&gt;The Gracie Family&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1914, Maeda moved to Brazil to help Japanese immigrants. There he met Gastï¿½o Gracie, the son of Scottish immigrant George Gracie. Gracie had assisted Maeda greatly, and in return, Maeda taught Judo to Gracie&amp;rsquo;s son Carlos at Maeda&amp;rsquo;s school in Brazil. Carlos, who was 14 when he started training, almost immediately started adapting the techniques to be more effective in open street fights where anything goes (vale tudo, in Portuguese). Carlos Gracie, like many fighters of his time, continued a tradition of &amp;ldquo;challenge matches&amp;rdquo; against fighters of various styles. He was famous throughout Brazil for his success in these fights. Later, Carlos taught his brothers Oswaldo, Jorge, Gastao and Helio. The first academy was opened in Rio de Janeiro in 1925. Carlos and Helio were responsible for creating the basis upon which Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu  exists today. Helio was small and frail, yet would consistently beat larger opponents. The Gracies began to emigrate to the United States after 1972, where they opened schools and hosted competitions and successful challenge matches. Most Gracie schools use the term &amp;ldquo;Gracie Jiu-Jitsu .&amp;rdquo; This is synonymous with Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-head-coach-david-thomas&#34;&gt;About Head Coach David Thomas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/post/dave-thomas/&#34;&gt;About Coach Dave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Punched Will Make You a Better Grappler</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-getting-punched/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-getting-punched/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Do your training buddy a favor and smack the shit out of him next time you spar. Will he forgive you? Hell, he should &lt;em&gt;thank you&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow&#34;&gt;Flow&lt;/a&gt; is great and technique drilling is absolutely important, but&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you aren&amp;rsquo;t regularly putting yourself into the mindset of a real fight, you aren&amp;rsquo;t preparing yourself for a real fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;The easiest way to do that is to get your grapplers to hit each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ground-rules&#34;&gt;Ground Rules&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partner up with someone you trust in your gym. You need to safely take each other just past the limit of your individual skills, but not too far.
Start from a disadvantaged position: a grab or tackle from behind, on the ground under the mount, or wadded up against the wall under a ground and pound assault.
Work this drill from the attacker and defender positions. Attackers will improve their top game and will learn how to control people from scrambling out of an attack. Defenders will improve their confidence and fight success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use a timer. Start at 1:30 and build every couple of weeks to work your way up to 5 minutes. Then add another round. I’ve found when you have a clock, there are fewer tap-outs from exhaustion or beat-down. When you train against the clock, you will typically try to “survive the round” rather than give up.
Keep the “tap out” escape hatch but understand that a tap-out in a real street fight is equivalent to a hospital or morgue trip: it means you gave up against a bad guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;drill-responses&#34;&gt;Drill Responses&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is to win in a encounter like this, or at least survive and escape. We drill these every week in our MMA class at Austin Jiu-Jitsu. Here are tactics in order of a prioritized “survival timeline,” where those you do first are most important to know and more likely to be successful. If you are going to drill one thing on the mat tonight, drill #1!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrambling out from under an attack. As much as we love BJJ and submission grappling, it’s not smart to stay stuck on the bottom. Drilling scrambling out of ground and pound attacks (from mount, side, half guard, and guard) will help you prepare for this. Scrambling out is different from sweeping in one important respect. In a scramble, you are explosively evading and pushing your opponent off before control position is established.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tying up or slowing an attack. If you can’t scramble out, you’ll need to slow down or stop your opponent’s strikes. Do this to buy yourself time to sweep or scramble out.
Escaping control or sweeping your attacker. Once he gets control position, your ability to scramble is reduced. You will need to work hard to defend and tie up your opponent to buy yourself time to technically escape or sweep. This is a much more technical game than an explosive scramble, and as such presents more risk. You need more skill and often more time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submitting the attacker from the bottom. Statistically, this isn’t a great bet, so I’m putting it at the bottom of the list. Sure, a submission specialist and elite-level MMA fighter like Antônio Rodrigo Nogueira has found submissions in &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of his fights, but you shouldn’t spend a lot of time getting hammered from the top unless you are truly great at tying up your attacker and nailing submissions. Submitting from the top is a great plan, so don’t mistake my point here; maintaining bottom position with a plan of submitting your attacker from the bottom is less likely to be successful than the other approaches described above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you drill each of these, make a note of which ones get you beat up the least. You’ll notice that as you go from 1 to 4, you get hit more and take longer to win or escape. Of course, in a real fight, you’ll employ many of these simultaneously. Chain the drills together and switch attackers based on who is on top. This will improve your ability to survive a real fight. Most MMA guys know this, but a lot of pure BJJ folks lack this experience and may make the mistake of focusing on submissions only. This is the same type of myopia that strikers without grappling experience suffer from. Don’t make their mistake in reverse. Prepare for getting hit by grappling with strikes allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let the Bodies Hit the Flow</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flow rolling is to a grappler what improvisation is to a jazz musician. It&amp;rsquo;s a fun, creative experience that develops your skills and helps you connect with your partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every grappling gym has its own way to get grapplers warmed up and ready for maximum athletic performance and the rigors of the full intensity of ground fighting. I prefer what I call &amp;ldquo;flow rolling&amp;rdquo;: a series of grappling rounds at low intensity with no submissions allowed and an emphasis on constant motion, cooperation, and resilience over static resistance and competitiveness. Since most grappling matches demand explosiveness, strength, and competiveness, flow rolling puts many students off their game, but the benefits can be substantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;here-s-my-pitch-for-why-you-should-flow-roll-every-time-you-warm-up&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my pitch for why you should flow roll every time you warm up&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximize athletic performance. Studies have demonstrated that athletes who warmed up for 20 minutes just before intense athletic activity are actually stronger and have improved muscle flexibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanded creativity due to lack of competitive pressure. When you aren&amp;rsquo;t fighting off submission attempts or stuck inside a tight guard, your mind has more time to work though new moves, alternate routes, and unconventional ideas. You can improve your mindset and patience about working through disadvantaged positions. Creativity is limited when you are under pressure. Relax your mind and let the ideas flow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved mat dexterity and coordination. Watching 2 experienced flow rollers is really impressive. You can develop improved mat dexterity with consistent flow rolling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s fun and develops teamwork. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice change to roll around with your mat partners when you aren&amp;rsquo;t trying to submit them. Put a smile on your face and enjoy the interactive dance. I tell the youngsters in my kids class &amp;ldquo;play like monkeys!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So go ahead, improv like a jazz musician. Play like a monkey. &lt;em&gt;Flow roll&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallax Error</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-dangerous-assumptions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2010 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-dangerous-assumptions/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I remember being a 1st kyu brown belt in Japanese karate back in the late 1980s. I was to be evaluated for my first black belt very soon. I was steeped in the detail of techniques, training intensity, and constant pressure of a student rising to his first dan promotion. I vividly recall my pride in ability. I felt I could fight off any attack, win any fight, and deliver ikken hissatsu: to kill with a single punch. I would talk to my buddies at the dojo and we’d discuss what we’d do in a real fight.
&amp;gt;One of us would say,&amp;ldquo;I’d drive his eyeball into his brain with an ippon nukite uchi!&amp;rdquo;
The other would respond,&amp;ldquo;Yeah? I’d explode his kidney with a yoko geri then smash his nose into his brain with a bear claw strike!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of this years later, it’s almost as funny and unlikely as Brick Tamland stabbing a guy in the heart with a trident in &lt;em&gt;Anchorman&lt;/em&gt;. Was I skilled in fighting or just good at karate? Was I too deep in one system of fighting to understand my general fighting abilities? Of course I couldn’t fend off any attack, win any fight, or deliver a killing blow. The irony is that deep skill in one fighting art and the lack of perspective about what you don’t know can lead to a dangerous general assumption that you are a good fighter. This is called parallax error, or an inability to see the real picture due to the participant’s point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we fast forward to the 2010s, it seems nostalgic and quaint that karate once dominated the self-defense landscape. Today, we are so much more advanced, aren’t we? We know the ground is where all fights end up, or at least that’s what the brochure said. Wake up: the problem with karate students in the 1980s is likely to be present with students of grappling sports today. Are we good fighters, or just good grapplers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I have a successful gym with a bunch of students who love to grapple, obsess over their matches, and count down the hours to their next training session. They are competitive and intense grapplers who are generally moving up the ranks as they make their way toward mastery. The problem is that, like karateka from the ‘80s, most grapplers today really don’t know how to fight. The good ones own the ground, but many aren’t consistently working on rounding out their fighting skills. I’ve wondered why 4 out of 5 grapplers never really learn the full set of skills to call them a fighter. Sure, these grapplers can thrive and enjoy all the beauty there is to find in BJJ, but don’t make the mistake of considering them fighters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;making-a-grappler-into-a-fighter&#34;&gt;Making a Grappler into a Fighter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grapplers that want to know how to fight should find time to work on these skills with their training partners. The list is ordered as a progression from most fundamental (simple) to most advanced (challenging).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foot work, evasion, feinting, guarding, and blocking skills to avoid strikes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working strikes! Punching, kicking, elbows, and knees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take-downs against a resisting opponent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take-downs against an opponent throwing punches and kicks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defending strikes from the clinch (blocks, underhooks, takedowns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completing takedowns against a wall or corner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Controlling and positioning to throw strikes from a variety of ground positions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standup boxing &amp;ldquo;flow&amp;rdquo; work – low intensity at first – to get accustomed to getting hit and get a different type of cardio workout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting against a wall or in a corner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting near obstacles: walls, furniture, people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting to get out from under a ground and pound attack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting 2 attackers from standing: positioning and exit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting to get up from the ground with multiple attackers are standing above you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weapons defense (sticks, knives, guns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that &amp;ldquo;fighting&amp;rdquo; doesn’t show up until the bottom half of the list. In my MMA program at &lt;a href=&#34;http://austinjiujitsu.com&#34;&gt;Austin Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/a&gt;, we spent over a year working on the top half of the list, just to build the basic skills needed to get to the real fighting drills. Yes, the above drills are a part of many established and successful martial arts systems: Muay Thai, Jeet Kune Do, krav maga, kali, escrima, and boxing. But keep in mind the passion grapplers have for grappling. They want to be a part of a Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and submission grappling program. As a by-product of all their hard work, time, and money spent, they also expect to know how to fight. A fight isn’t just a ground battle, and to be a fighter doesn’t just mean you know how to triangle choke someone. You must drill fighting scenarios that put you into a fight mentality and you have to do it often enough and with enough intensity that the training creates correct responses in a real fight situation. Without opportunity to train for real fighting, we aren’t creating real fighters.
I’m happy that many BJJ schools are creating MMA programs to help blend other fighting skills into their students and to finally correct this parallax error. Grappling students: take advantage of these opportunities. Learn how to fight!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being the Smartest Guy in the Room Could Make You Stupid</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/being-smart-can-make-you-stupid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/being-smart-can-make-you-stupid/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, I was a white belt who had just joined a new BJJ school that had moved to the area. Sitting in a circle after a technique was shared with the class, a student raised his hand and asked &amp;ldquo;how do you escape that move?&amp;rdquo; The instructor&amp;rsquo;s answer: &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;ll cost you $90 and take an hour of my time.&amp;rdquo; The joke, which wasn&amp;rsquo;t a joke at all, it turns out, was that the student could only learn that information by paying for a private lesson, and the student group wasn&amp;rsquo;t worthy of the treasured secrets of this genius. The first time I heard that response, I laughed. But my chuckle was cut short when I realized he was serious. Over time, I saw the same pattern that the other students had already seen. The student would feel like an idiot for asking the question, the private lesson would never happen, and the answer to the question never spoken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would you do if you asked the question? Would you be likely to raise your hand next time? Over time, the intended effect unfolded at the gym: people rarely asked questions of the head instructor. Since questions often shape curriculum, an absence of inquiry left the instructor to teach only what he wanted to teach. Students with questions would seek each other out for information. The questions didn&amp;rsquo;t go away, they were redirected to less qualified, but more helpful people. This was in the age before YouTube. This instructor had a stranglehold on information. Hearing him respond to a question with such an absurd evasion reminded me of working with an IT helpdesk guy who acts like his knowing how to install Microsoft Office was a birthright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a more recent example, a friend training at another gym had been keeping a nifty online technique notebook. Not a lot of detail, but very helpful perspective intended to feed the hungry Jiu-Jitsu diaspora. Their instructor caught wind of the website and was uncomfortable. The concern was that it might help competitors. The web site no longer discusses Jiu-Jitsu technique. Let&amp;rsquo;s say the web page was discussing what this student learned about executing a take-down. Can you imagine some morsel of information being divulged that would somehow alter the competitive landscape? Google &amp;ldquo;double leg take-down.&amp;rdquo; Tell me there could have been something truly original in the web site&amp;rsquo;s description of this technique that will harm this coach&amp;rsquo;s business. No, and that wasn&amp;rsquo;t the point of the website. Learning and communicating is a personal process that takes the student beyond the boundaries of the mats. This student was stuck in a stranglehold of censorship.
These two situtions, separated by a decade of time and completely different instructor lineage, illustrates what is commonplace in this sport. Some instructors treat information like a valuable commodity in a world where it is already free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information isn&amp;rsquo;t power. In the information-connected economy, the kinds of businesses that can get away with treating information as a valuable commodity are rapidly becoming as old as your Dad&amp;rsquo;s Wall Street Journal curbside dropoff. And don&amp;rsquo;t get me into an ad revenue argument since it&amp;rsquo;s so far off the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years on the mats, I&amp;rsquo;ve come up with some really sweet moves. I can find dozens of videos on the Internet of guys who have come up with the same moves on their own. They&amp;rsquo;ve given them their own silly names like &amp;ldquo;De-goitering the Goat&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Feed the baby&amp;rdquo; but the moves are the same. This is a healthy sign of a exploding system with a spirit of innovation, expansion, and sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;coaches-hide-your-secrets-at-your-own-peril&#34;&gt;Coaches: hide your secrets at your own peril.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students are passionate about this sport and hungry for information. They&amp;rsquo;ll go get the answers with or without you. Be the leader and coach you are supposed to be and teach them what you know. By keeping secret techniques, you won&amp;rsquo;t be forced to learn anything new. Holding back your techniques makes you stale and dumb, not smarter than the rest of the crowd. Teach your students everything you know so they can challenge you to come up with new ideas. You were the smarty pants who figured those old secrets out to begin with, right? So, go make up some new ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love witnessing the process in action. Every few months, I drop some new technique on my students that usually starts with all of them tapping and freaking out about &amp;ldquo;what the hell was that?&amp;rdquo; We cover it in class, repeatedly. A month later, some of them are starting to figure it out and execute it on their own. After 6 months, the technique is old hat: we&amp;rsquo;ve figured out 6 variations, mastered a few of them, and know 10 ways to shut it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being the only person who knows how to execute the Biggie Slicer is as boring as playing Quake III in God mode. The splatter and spray of guts are fun for a while, but you are left wanting someone who can scare you into getting better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time I get a visiting instructor on my mats, I make it a point to teach something I don&amp;rsquo;t expect him to know. By &amp;ldquo;liberating this technique into the wild,&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;m sure to have to get much better at executing it, discovering defenses, and variations. That&amp;rsquo;s how this sport keeps moving, and that&amp;rsquo;s how the best athletes in the sport keep growing.
The smartest guy in the room is only as smart as the information he&amp;rsquo;s capable of teaching the group. Prove you&amp;rsquo;re smart: give it away, now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Small Milestone on a Long Path</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/a-small-milestone/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/a-small-milestone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like most long-term endeavors, there are few significant milestones. In a sport like Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu, where the journey from white to black belt only has 3 intermediate steps, the milestones are literally &amp;ldquo;few and far between.&amp;rdquo; In my case, with 13 years in the making of 2008 black belt promotion, simple math will tell you just how far those milestones were set apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of our time working though intense athletic effort is filled with small challenges, victories, incremental growth, and setbacks. Even if you train 4 times per week, go to every seminar and open mat available, and compete regularly, you will find long periods of time where getting over the smallest obstacle will challenge your resolve to continue the journey ahead. The harder you train, the more likely you will get injured. The more you cross-train with others, the more likely you will find someone who will kick your butt so regularly and with such domination, that you will likely wonder if you can ever get past them. I remember being a white belt, completely sore and beaten up from my previous training day, afraid to face the mats again, wondering if I should return for another brutal work-out. Of course, I returned, but was faced with this constant question for months. The sport is insanely challenging. Everyone you meet on the mats sees you as fresh meat. The target is on your back every single day. As your rank progresses, this target gets bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu rewards people who can get past these big obstacles. The rewards are not just rank, but a knowledge base of skills that are broad and deep.
I remember a karate sensei of mine 20 years ago, in a moment of self-absorption, was boasting about how at his skill level, he could simply toy with his opponents &amp;ldquo;like a cat playing with a mouse.&amp;rdquo; I was simultaneously disappointed that he shared this with his students and intrigued that a level of skill that advanced was attainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than boast that I&amp;rsquo;m the biggest cat in the jungle, this promotion is a time to remember how many phenomenally talented athletes are in this amazing sport; many of them commanding a skill level that I can only hope to attain in my lifetime. I also hope that I have the ability to translate this wonderful sport into words capable of inspiring my students to stay on the long road. Don&amp;rsquo;t focus on the milestones. Focus on the gifts that come from the hard work, every day you are on the mats: friendship, fitness, and the skills of a cat just a little bit bigger than it was yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Unsolvable Problem</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/the-unsolvable-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/the-unsolvable-problem/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is a key lesson to learn in battle of any kind and is particularly appropriate to the way I approach application of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu technique to a fight or sparring match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve success in battle, you must present a dazzling flexibility to both respond to attack and counterattack with a level of speed and complexity that off-balance your opponent in a way that prevents them from ever gaining stable ground to continue the fight. A good example of this is the concept of “overwhelming display of force” that Special Forces military units specialize in. They create a problem that off-balances the enemy to such a degree that they are too busy running for cover to ever successfully form an offensive. Another example of this is a skilled debater who subtly changes their verbal attacks faster than their opponent can respond to the logical twists of reason that they are presented with. In both cases, the victorious has presented an &lt;em&gt;unsolvable problem&lt;/em&gt; for their opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The details of this concept of an unsolvable problem need to be considered in terms of the parameters present, which includes the timeframe and other “characteristics of the battlefield problem.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;timeframe&#34;&gt;Timeframe&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your opponent represents the enemy if you extend the concept of martial arts sparring to real battle. Each position your opponent presents and each attack they launch poses a specific problem for you that is framed in time. This timeframe can be split into a series of discrete moments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;initiation&#34;&gt;Initiation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the attack is launched or position is established. This is a moment of transition which can either be in the form of an initial attack or a new position in a series of maneuvers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;response&#34;&gt;Response&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you detect the attack or position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mental reflex: How your detection of this affects your mental state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical reflex: What your physical reaction is to this attack before it impacts you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;continuation-or-termination&#34;&gt;Continuation or termination&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impact of damage on you if the attack succeeds, or impact on your opponent if your response (evasion or counterattack) succeeds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And so on… Unless your response terminates the attack, your response will create a problem for your opponent to solve (a counterattack or new position).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;parameters-characteristics-of-the-problem&#34;&gt;Parameters: Characteristics of the Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each problem has a number of parameters, or components, that need to be understood to solve the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time do you have to solve the problem? As described above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has the advantage? In other words, who is in position to do the most damage, assuming there are no impediments to continuous attack from both sides?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is in control of the movement or balance of the position? Are you in a position to control their balance or restrict their movement? For example, even if your opponent is on top, where they have the positional advantage, if you are in a position to sweep or reverse them you may have more control of the movement than your opponent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is your opponent solving the problem you have posed them? Turn the tables. Just as you are trying to confound their attempts to better you, they are doing the same to you. For example, if you are controlling them in a position of advantage yet they are quickly getting control by setting up an escape, they are solving your problem and will soon be giving you a new problem of your own!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has psychological control? This is a key concept that deserves an entire article of its own. We&amp;rsquo;ll focus on this continually.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the physical state of your opponent? Are they injured? Winded? Have you noticed them losing their energy level?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental issues around the fight (walls, chairs, debris, other people &amp;ndash; friendly or unfriendly). Many of these can work to your advantage or disadvantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these factors needs continuous monitoring for you to understand what the next move is for you in a fight. The more experienced a fighter is, the faster they can assess these factors and act or make corrections to their advantage in a fight. If you sense your opponent is solving the problem, you must change position to create a new problem for your opponent. The faster you change the parameters of the problem, the less likely they will be able to solve this. This creates a huge psychological advantage and accelerates physical exhaustion for your opponent as they struggle to solve these problems. In effect, you are creating an unsolvable problem by changing the problem faster than your opponent can solve it. As we practice flow on the mats, you should concentrate on this concept, since it requires a high level of skill on position transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;training-for-the-unsolvable-problem&#34;&gt;Training for the Unsolvable Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;question-and-answer&#34;&gt;Question and Answer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a way to take baby steps to &amp;ldquo;the unsolvable problem.&amp;rdquo; We break down the rapid-fire problem and response into a slow paced &amp;ldquo;dialog.&amp;rdquo; Starting with these positions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pass guard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escape side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escape mount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;we pose a question in the form of a position, physically asking &amp;ldquo;How would you escape from this?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your partner responds by attempting to escape in one motion. Your partner must resist the compulsion to start fighting your way out. They will make a single move, then let you ask a new question. By allowing them to respond (not resisting the response), you allow the dialog to continue. After they respond, you change your position to present a new problem. And so on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rapid-conversation&#34;&gt;Rapid Conversation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fast, 3 second exchange of &amp;ldquo;questions and answers&amp;rdquo; (a set of 4 or 5 positions flowing into each other as your partner responds). As a quick sequence of questions and answers, it becomes like a very quick match where you stop after 3 seconds and assess your position, awaiting your partner to start another &amp;ldquo;burst of conversation.&amp;rdquo; Let the person who started &amp;ldquo;lead.&amp;rdquo; Switch lead after a few &amp;ldquo;conversations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Sense on Training</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/common-sense/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/common-sense/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-students&#34;&gt;For Students&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life isn&amp;rsquo;t fair; distinguish yourself with intense training. Remember when your coach told you size and strength don&amp;rsquo;t matter? He was wrong: strength matters. When all else is equal between opponents, whoever has the edge in the smallest way will distinguish themselves in victory. Oh, and size matters too. A big guy with like skills will crush a little guy. Sorry little guys. Coming from a featherweight, I share your pain. Literally. On the other hand, technique, stamina, and aggression can imbalance a much greater differential in size and strength. I have beaten much bigger guys than me, but there was always a reason: no magic, just training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cross Train - If you want to be a good martial artist, you need to be a good athlete. I don&amp;rsquo;t care what you choose to do, but cross train in something. Swim, lift weights, run, bike, rock climb, play soccer. It will help your strength and endurance. It&amp;rsquo;s also fun. Don&amp;rsquo;t be a martial arts nerd: get outside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a Good Student; Take notes. Good students take notes. Committing your training to personal notes is an important step in memorizing your training, and recording a permanent document of what you may end up spending a lifetime acquiring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test yourself. Good students test themselves to get a fair measurement of how they stack up against others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things Need to Change: Keep an Open Mind. Don&amp;rsquo;t get stuck in the same old habits. Find new positions to fight from. Take off your gi and fight. Put on a blindfold and fight. Don&amp;rsquo;t ever ask permission to try something new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question all assumptions made by students and teachers. Any teacher that can&amp;rsquo;t deal with curiosity is in the wrong business. The only dumb question is the one you didn&amp;rsquo;t ask.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust your experience. Have faith in your accumulated mat time and experience in fights. Clear your head and go with your reflexes. If you can&amp;rsquo;t do this, get back on the mats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let yourself heal. Don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to be a hero if you have an injury. Take time off from training, and don&amp;rsquo;t let anyone talk you back until you are better. But, know when it is time to get back on the mats. The longer you are gone, the harder it is to get back out there. [Read more about injuries here]().&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break the rules, and don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid of (or surprised by) the consequences. Non-conformists drive people nuts, so be prepared to go it alone if you have to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-instructors&#34;&gt;For Instructors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward the most curious. Be prepared to learn something from your students. Support an atmosphere of creativity and openness, so everyone feels comfortable asking questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t beat your dog and don&amp;rsquo;t beat your students with your dogma. Never ask your students to have faith in you or &amp;ldquo;just trust&amp;rdquo; you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody has all the answers. Admit when you don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer, but be ready to get in there and figure it out with sweat and hard work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have fun. If you can&amp;rsquo;t have fun and make fun of yourself every day, you&amp;rsquo;ve lost yourself in your own self-importance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge is wealth; Share it with others. If you don&amp;rsquo;t spend at least 51% of your time coaching others in something, you are adding no net value to your time on Earth. Don&amp;rsquo;t get self-absorbed. Give it away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your students aren&amp;rsquo;t your property. Don&amp;rsquo;t whine if they go to another school. [Read more about this]().&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compete, or don&amp;rsquo;t push your students into competition. If you can&amp;rsquo;t be a positive role model for the courage required to step on the mats and potentially lose in front of them, then don&amp;rsquo;t be a hypocrite and encourage them to compete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn from other sports. Develop training tools. Drill, drill, drill. Videotape student fights and analyze them with your students. Introduce circuit training. Get your students into shape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t expect respect; earn it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Train For Yourself</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/train-for-yourself/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/train-for-yourself/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your instructor is human. Don&amp;rsquo;t let yourself get sucked into a cult of personality.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental and nearly universal aspects of martial arts training is the intense loyalty students feel to their instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe you should be loyal to those who are loyal to you, meaning you should devote your loyalty where it is earned. In some circumstances the loyalty I have seen students devote to instructors borders on blind zeal. Over the years, I have fallen into this trap from time-to-time.  It is all too easy to carelessly fantasize that your instructor is the toughest martial artist in the planet and that everything he does should be followed with biblical devotion. That&amp;rsquo;s not my viewpoint. While I feel that within a specific school you should respect the authority of an instructor, the instructor is providing a paid service, not unlike a personal trainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;news-flash-self-defense-instruction-is-a-service&#34;&gt;News Flash! Self-Defense Instruction is a Service&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most prevalent problem in martial arts today. Martial arts instructors place their ego before the customer. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it over and over again. Most martial arts instructors will talk the talk of your personal growth, but when push comes to shove, they forget it and put their goals squarely in your path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a service industry. You, the customer (the student), hold the reins. Your instructor may help you navigate, should help you motivate, and will pick you up and redirect you when you crash. But everything you learn belongs to you. You paid for it with sweat, time, and money. It&amp;rsquo;s yours. While you may credit your 4th grade reading teacher for your love of fiction novels, the stories you have read are yours alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;know-when-it-s-time-to-leave&#34;&gt;Know when it&amp;rsquo;s time to leave&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen a pattern in many martial arts schools. As students advance through the ranks, one of three things happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students get &amp;ldquo;fat and complacent&amp;rdquo; and start to mimic the head instructor, barking orders at the new students and taking every opportunity to beat them senseless. They are completely in tune with each others&amp;rsquo; techniques and habits. They rarely, if ever, challenge themselves in competition or against unknown (experienced) opponents. They have a stature they have worked far too hard on to have someone knock them off their pedestal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Others begin to see the weaknesses in their instructor, whether these are moral, political, or physical weaknesses. These students tend to leave, either establishing their own schools or joining a &amp;ldquo;competing&amp;rdquo; school. In this case, an &amp;ldquo;exodus of the awakened&amp;rdquo; sometimes follows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The senior students begin to assist instruction and the head instructor works on diplomacy with other schools, associations, and bridge building to promote growth in the sport. This is the optimal arrangement, but is unfortunately rare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think it is a natural, and even beneficial process that advanced students with an open mind and true passion for experiencing personal growth will either desire to begin to instruct, thus allowing the head instructor to focus on outward-facing activities or fly away from the nest. The only unfortunate thing about this is that, due to the lifelong loyalty expected, a bridge is often burned by leaving. If your instructor has the correct attitude toward growing students, you will be welcomed back for training and you will indeed have a lifelong coach, even after you open your own school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, having the ability to fly doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you should leave the nest. Know when it&amp;rsquo;s time.  There are many schools with solid curriculum, fantastic coaching, and great facilities that can satisfy a decade of martial arts training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;building-bridges-and-fresh-meat&#34;&gt;Building Bridges and Fresh Meat&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of training for yourself involves seeking relationships with other students and instructors in other schools in the area. This helps in many ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gives you access to numerous new training partners, a term I call &amp;ldquo;eating fresh meat.&amp;rdquo; The ones you train with at your primary school are like your brothers. You love them and have fun with them, but when you wrestle with your brothers, there is often times nothing new to learn. Sure, any mat time is better than none at all, but there is either a permanent pecking order in place, or dull and predictable stalemates are the norm.
It allows you to test the waters to make sure that the quality of instruction you are getting really is the best for the money and time you commit to this most important endeavor. Gasp! Did I say money and time are more important than the deep relationship of loyalty you owe to your instructor? Why, yes I did. Remember the topic? &amp;ldquo;Train for yourself, not your instructor.&amp;rdquo;
If the school is training in a different style, it provides valuable cross-training. This may lead to a deeper exploration of the new style if you decide it is right for you. Jiu-Jitsu students should wrestle with wrestlers, play with judoka and samboka, and prepare to learn something new. I have learned wonderful new ideas by shutting my mouth and listening to a wrestling coach instruct a class.
Challenge your instructor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are training at the right school, this may seem like suicide. Most instructors really are much tougher than you. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to imply you want to actually somehow destroy your instructor, but I want to make an important point. After training in traditional Karate and Aikido schools for well over 13 years, I&amp;rsquo;m allowed to make this observation: most students don&amp;rsquo;t try hard enough when testing technique on their instructors, or sparring with them. This is once again the &amp;ldquo;larger than life&amp;rdquo; problem. If an instructor asks you to throw a punch at him and you actually hit him (his demonstration fails), would you feel really bad? Should you? No. When you spar with your instructor, would you feel bad if you beat him? You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t. In reality, if his technique doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, you don&amp;rsquo;t want to walk around with some false sense of security do you? The first time I beat one of my instructors sparring, I experienced mixed emotions. I certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like celebrating. It was a bit awkward, he didn&amp;rsquo;t congratulate me, and I was left wondering what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is a form of dishonesty to not challenge your instructor with your greatest effort and technique. Challenging him will keep you both sharp. I encourage my students to fight to win, and many of them are quite a handful!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bane of Freedom</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/the-bane-of-freedom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/the-bane-of-freedom/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;a-warning-about-instructors-who-put-themselves-before-you&#34;&gt;A warning about instructors who put themselves before you.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many instructors treat their knowledge as a treasure that is only bestowed upon those in their inner circle: their most trusted students who have shown loyalty, their knights. All the other students are serfs who have not yet proven their worth to the king. All live within his kingdom. No bonds are made or allowed with other neighboring kingdoms. You can join the king, but you must move within the walls, and never leave again. Anyone who strays outside the walls of the kingdom are banished forever. They are suspected as spies who may have sold the keys of the castle to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the kingdom-building realities of an egomaniacal instructor with a distorted world-view of the purpose of knowledge. Knowledge is to be set free. Allow your students to seek it anywhere they may. The borders must be porous to allow for great relationships with your neighbors, sharing of knowledge, and creation of new knowledge from old. Encourage cross training anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sign of kingdom-building is the treatment of questions from the students. I have seen instructors who don&amp;rsquo;t answer questions or do so in such an oblique fashion that over time, questions stop from the students. I have had one instructor who would answer some questions with &amp;ldquo;That will cost $100 and one hour of your time,&amp;rdquo; meaning the student could get an answer only if they paid for a private lesson with the high-priced black belt. When a new student joins, they wonder why nobody else is asking questions. They soon learn their lesson with a belittling experience in front of the class. Why create secrets, mystery, and intrigue? In doing this, the knowledge instructors hold is locked in the castle tower. Foster innovation, research, exploration, and inquisitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build a school that is about building students, not about building a kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-the-lesson-from-another-service&#34;&gt;Learning the Lesson From Another Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try a simple analogy. Forget martial arts for a minute. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you want to be a doctor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You pick the best medical school around, because you want to be the best doctor you can be. You want to save lives and you believe you can be a success. After doing a great job in pre-med, you have envisioned a dream of opening a small medical clinic where you can better the lives of a small community. Your friends and family believe in you. But more than anything, you feel compelled by your principles to pursue this dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You go to the medical school and do a great job, year after year. You expand your knowledge and arm yourself with the tools to save lives. The dean of the college counsels you, shares with you his profound knowledge, and treats you like family. Your professors are top notch. You take an internship with a small clinic to diversify and deepen your experience. It turns out that this is more fulfilling than your class work because it demonstrates you understand real world application of what you have learned. You take other internships.  As you come closer to the end of med school, you organize opening your own clinic. You have imagined this whole time how this would work, and now it is becoming real. You excitedly share with others around you the slow process of creating this clinic as it unfolds. Your family, friends, and other students are happy for you and wish you the best. Your college dean and professors are proud. You embark on the greatest dream of your life and are blessed to actually love your job and the benefits your work bestows upon those you touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During your years of practice, other doctors join you. You share your knowledge freely, discover new methods, and publish these for all to learn from. Years later, a young doctor joins you. You mentor this doctor until he knows enough to go out and open a clinic of his own. You are sad to see him go. But much more than this, you are proud of their accomplishment and bless him as he makes his way onward. This young doctor considers you their lifelong friend and mentor. Their successes transitively become your successes. You unlocked the door for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instructors-unlock-the-door&#34;&gt;Instructors: Unlock the Door&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the dream of many martial artists to know enough to teach someday: to give back what they have been given. It is a shame that some martial arts instructors put more focus on protecting their knowledge than creating an environment of limitless growth. Instructors: know what your students seek. Put their goals before you or get out of the business. &lt;a href=&#34;(http://jitshappens.com/blog/train-for-yourself/)&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s what service is all about&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Students are customers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow on the Path to Mastery</title>
      <link>http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow-and-mastery/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow-and-mastery/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;What drives us to train in this sport with such never-ending passion, spending a small fortune on training toward your black belt, burning thousands of precious hours away from work and family, at substantial risk to life and limb?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the math. A black belt could easily cost you $12,000 (10 years at $100 per month), not including travel and equipment costs. Getting there will take over 3300 hours on the mats, travelling to seminars, and competing. The math will invariably include a dozen injuries and bills from more doctors than you will care to recall. Of course, a black belt is by no means a master, really just a glorified beginner in the grand scheme of things. If you believe Malcolm Gladwell in Outliers: The Story of Success, this is a little over 30% of the way toward mastery. At nearly 15 years in the sport I’m about halfway &amp;ldquo;there.&amp;rdquo; Wherever &amp;ldquo;there&amp;rdquo; is…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-motivates-us-to-drive-drive-drive&#34;&gt;What motivates us to drive, drive, drive?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize, we spend a ton of money and time to get ourselves beaten to a pulp for a level of mastery which may never happen. What motivates us to drive, drive, drive?
The payoff is mastery, which as I hint at above, is ironically something that is only asymptotically attainable. We can get close, but really never get there. But we keep driving anyway, getting our butts kicked by guys and gals who we can only dream of &lt;em&gt;powning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does motivation come from? How can we get past the plateaus and walls that invariably block our path over and over again?
I have previously discussed the importance of flow as a means of unleashing creativity, advancing new ideas, and physically preparing your body for full-out battle. Flow continues to be at the center of some of the most important growth moments for me in the sport. A book called &lt;em&gt;Drive: The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us&lt;/em&gt;, by an author with a downright Reservoir Dogs-esque name, Daniel Pink, illuminates this subject further with the help of solid research and engaging style. Pink, intrigued by the intrinsic and extrinsic roots of motivation, thoroughly covers the topic and ends up distilling the essential drivers for motivation along three lines: autonomy, mastery, and purpose. Mastery is a huge motivator for those of us in this sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slow march towards mastery includes moments where your growth, energy, and motivation are at their greatest. Coincidentally with my discussions on this topic, Pink calls this &amp;ldquo;flow.&amp;rdquo; He equates flow with play, in that the labors and efforts of the work you are engaged in become effervescent and lost in the moment of unconscious progress you enjoy in flow. How can you find your flow and how can you make this a means to accelerate growth and enjoyment? How do we work to get lost in the moment? Translated as a Zen kōan, we should concentrate maximum effort to release effortless play. The more you flow, the more you grow, and the more fun you have on the path. Having fun is a great counter balance to the pain of training hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read my article on &lt;a href=&#34;(http://jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow/)&#34;&gt;flow&lt;/a&gt;. Think about how you experience flow on the mats. Relax, be patient, have fun, and flow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>