<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</title>
    <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/tags/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jits Happens - Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>jits</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jitshappens.com/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Punched Will Make You a Better Grappler</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-getting-punched/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-getting-punched/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Do your training buddy a favor and smack the shit out of him next time you spar. Will he forgive you? Hell, he should &lt;em&gt;thank you&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow&#34;&gt;Flow&lt;/a&gt; is great and technique drilling is absolutely important, but&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you aren&amp;rsquo;t regularly putting yourself into the mindset of a real fight, you aren&amp;rsquo;t preparing yourself for a real fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;The easiest way to do that is to get your grapplers to hit each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ground-rules&#34;&gt;Ground Rules&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partner up with someone you trust in your gym. You need to safely take each other just past the limit of your individual skills, but not too far.
Start from a disadvantaged position: a grab or tackle from behind, on the ground under the mount, or wadded up against the wall under a ground and pound assault.
Work this drill from the attacker and defender positions. Attackers will improve their top game and will learn how to control people from scrambling out of an attack. Defenders will improve their confidence and fight success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use a timer. Start at 1:30 and build every couple of weeks to work your way up to 5 minutes. Then add another round. I’ve found when you have a clock, there are fewer tap-outs from exhaustion or beat-down. When you train against the clock, you will typically try to “survive the round” rather than give up.
Keep the “tap out” escape hatch but understand that a tap-out in a real street fight is equivalent to a hospital or morgue trip: it means you gave up against a bad guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;drill-responses&#34;&gt;Drill Responses&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is to win in a encounter like this, or at least survive and escape. We drill these every week in our MMA class at Austin Jiu-Jitsu. Here are tactics in order of a prioritized “survival timeline,” where those you do first are most important to know and more likely to be successful. If you are going to drill one thing on the mat tonight, drill #1!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrambling out from under an attack. As much as we love BJJ and submission grappling, it’s not smart to stay stuck on the bottom. Drilling scrambling out of ground and pound attacks (from mount, side, half guard, and guard) will help you prepare for this. Scrambling out is different from sweeping in one important respect. In a scramble, you are explosively evading and pushing your opponent off before control position is established.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tying up or slowing an attack. If you can’t scramble out, you’ll need to slow down or stop your opponent’s strikes. Do this to buy yourself time to sweep or scramble out.
Escaping control or sweeping your attacker. Once he gets control position, your ability to scramble is reduced. You will need to work hard to defend and tie up your opponent to buy yourself time to technically escape or sweep. This is a much more technical game than an explosive scramble, and as such presents more risk. You need more skill and often more time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submitting the attacker from the bottom. Statistically, this isn’t a great bet, so I’m putting it at the bottom of the list. Sure, a submission specialist and elite-level MMA fighter like Antônio Rodrigo Nogueira has found submissions in &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of his fights, but you shouldn’t spend a lot of time getting hammered from the top unless you are truly great at tying up your attacker and nailing submissions. Submitting from the top is a great plan, so don’t mistake my point here; maintaining bottom position with a plan of submitting your attacker from the bottom is less likely to be successful than the other approaches described above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you drill each of these, make a note of which ones get you beat up the least. You’ll notice that as you go from 1 to 4, you get hit more and take longer to win or escape. Of course, in a real fight, you’ll employ many of these simultaneously. Chain the drills together and switch attackers based on who is on top. This will improve your ability to survive a real fight. Most MMA guys know this, but a lot of pure BJJ folks lack this experience and may make the mistake of focusing on submissions only. This is the same type of myopia that strikers without grappling experience suffer from. Don’t make their mistake in reverse. Prepare for getting hit by grappling with strikes allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let the Bodies Hit the Flow</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flow rolling is to a grappler what improvisation is to a jazz musician. It&amp;rsquo;s a fun, creative experience that develops your skills and helps you connect with your partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every grappling gym has its own way to get grapplers warmed up and ready for maximum athletic performance and the rigors of the full intensity of ground fighting. I prefer what I call &amp;ldquo;flow rolling&amp;rdquo;: a series of grappling rounds at low intensity with no submissions allowed and an emphasis on constant motion, cooperation, and resilience over static resistance and competitiveness. Since most grappling matches demand explosiveness, strength, and competiveness, flow rolling puts many students off their game, but the benefits can be substantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;here-s-my-pitch-for-why-you-should-flow-roll-every-time-you-warm-up&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my pitch for why you should flow roll every time you warm up&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximize athletic performance. Studies have demonstrated that athletes who warmed up for 20 minutes just before intense athletic activity are actually stronger and have improved muscle flexibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanded creativity due to lack of competitive pressure. When you aren&amp;rsquo;t fighting off submission attempts or stuck inside a tight guard, your mind has more time to work though new moves, alternate routes, and unconventional ideas. You can improve your mindset and patience about working through disadvantaged positions. Creativity is limited when you are under pressure. Relax your mind and let the ideas flow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved mat dexterity and coordination. Watching 2 experienced flow rollers is really impressive. You can develop improved mat dexterity with consistent flow rolling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s fun and develops teamwork. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice change to roll around with your mat partners when you aren&amp;rsquo;t trying to submit them. Put a smile on your face and enjoy the interactive dance. I tell the youngsters in my kids class &amp;ldquo;play like monkeys!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So go ahead, improv like a jazz musician. Play like a monkey. &lt;em&gt;Flow roll&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallax Error</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-dangerous-assumptions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2010 15:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-dangerous-assumptions/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I remember being a 1st kyu brown belt in Japanese karate back in the late 1980s. I was to be evaluated for my first black belt very soon. I was steeped in the detail of techniques, training intensity, and constant pressure of a student rising to his first dan promotion. I vividly recall my pride in ability. I felt I could fight off any attack, win any fight, and deliver ikken hissatsu: to kill with a single punch. I would talk to my buddies at the dojo and we’d discuss what we’d do in a real fight.
&amp;gt;One of us would say,&amp;ldquo;I’d drive his eyeball into his brain with an ippon nukite uchi!&amp;rdquo;
The other would respond,&amp;ldquo;Yeah? I’d explode his kidney with a yoko geri then smash his nose into his brain with a bear claw strike!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of this years later, it’s almost as funny and unlikely as Brick Tamland stabbing a guy in the heart with a trident in &lt;em&gt;Anchorman&lt;/em&gt;. Was I skilled in fighting or just good at karate? Was I too deep in one system of fighting to understand my general fighting abilities? Of course I couldn’t fend off any attack, win any fight, or deliver a killing blow. The irony is that deep skill in one fighting art and the lack of perspective about what you don’t know can lead to a dangerous general assumption that you are a good fighter. This is called parallax error, or an inability to see the real picture due to the participant’s point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we fast forward to the 2010s, it seems nostalgic and quaint that karate once dominated the self-defense landscape. Today, we are so much more advanced, aren’t we? We know the ground is where all fights end up, or at least that’s what the brochure said. Wake up: the problem with karate students in the 1980s is likely to be present with students of grappling sports today. Are we good fighters, or just good grapplers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I have a successful gym with a bunch of students who love to grapple, obsess over their matches, and count down the hours to their next training session. They are competitive and intense grapplers who are generally moving up the ranks as they make their way toward mastery. The problem is that, like karateka from the ‘80s, most grapplers today really don’t know how to fight. The good ones own the ground, but many aren’t consistently working on rounding out their fighting skills. I’ve wondered why 4 out of 5 grapplers never really learn the full set of skills to call them a fighter. Sure, these grapplers can thrive and enjoy all the beauty there is to find in BJJ, but don’t make the mistake of considering them fighters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;making-a-grappler-into-a-fighter&#34;&gt;Making a Grappler into a Fighter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grapplers that want to know how to fight should find time to work on these skills with their training partners. The list is ordered as a progression from most fundamental (simple) to most advanced (challenging).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foot work, evasion, feinting, guarding, and blocking skills to avoid strikes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working strikes! Punching, kicking, elbows, and knees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take-downs against a resisting opponent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take-downs against an opponent throwing punches and kicks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defending strikes from the clinch (blocks, underhooks, takedowns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completing takedowns against a wall or corner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Controlling and positioning to throw strikes from a variety of ground positions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standup boxing &amp;ldquo;flow&amp;rdquo; work – low intensity at first – to get accustomed to getting hit and get a different type of cardio workout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting against a wall or in a corner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting near obstacles: walls, furniture, people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting to get out from under a ground and pound attack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting 2 attackers from standing: positioning and exit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fighting to get up from the ground with multiple attackers are standing above you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weapons defense (sticks, knives, guns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that &amp;ldquo;fighting&amp;rdquo; doesn’t show up until the bottom half of the list. In my MMA program at &lt;a href=&#34;http://austinjiujitsu.com&#34;&gt;Austin Jiu-Jitsu&lt;/a&gt;, we spent over a year working on the top half of the list, just to build the basic skills needed to get to the real fighting drills. Yes, the above drills are a part of many established and successful martial arts systems: Muay Thai, Jeet Kune Do, krav maga, kali, escrima, and boxing. But keep in mind the passion grapplers have for grappling. They want to be a part of a Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and submission grappling program. As a by-product of all their hard work, time, and money spent, they also expect to know how to fight. A fight isn’t just a ground battle, and to be a fighter doesn’t just mean you know how to triangle choke someone. You must drill fighting scenarios that put you into a fight mentality and you have to do it often enough and with enough intensity that the training creates correct responses in a real fight situation. Without opportunity to train for real fighting, we aren’t creating real fighters.
I’m happy that many BJJ schools are creating MMA programs to help blend other fighting skills into their students and to finally correct this parallax error. Grappling students: take advantage of these opportunities. Learn how to fight!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being the Smartest Guy in the Room Could Make You Stupid</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/being-smart-can-make-you-stupid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/being-smart-can-make-you-stupid/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, I was a white belt who had just joined a new BJJ school that had moved to the area. Sitting in a circle after a technique was shared with the class, a student raised his hand and asked &amp;ldquo;how do you escape that move?&amp;rdquo; The instructor&amp;rsquo;s answer: &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;ll cost you $90 and take an hour of my time.&amp;rdquo; The joke, which wasn&amp;rsquo;t a joke at all, it turns out, was that the student could only learn that information by paying for a private lesson, and the student group wasn&amp;rsquo;t worthy of the treasured secrets of this genius. The first time I heard that response, I laughed. But my chuckle was cut short when I realized he was serious. Over time, I saw the same pattern that the other students had already seen. The student would feel like an idiot for asking the question, the private lesson would never happen, and the answer to the question never spoken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would you do if you asked the question? Would you be likely to raise your hand next time? Over time, the intended effect unfolded at the gym: people rarely asked questions of the head instructor. Since questions often shape curriculum, an absence of inquiry left the instructor to teach only what he wanted to teach. Students with questions would seek each other out for information. The questions didn&amp;rsquo;t go away, they were redirected to less qualified, but more helpful people. This was in the age before YouTube. This instructor had a stranglehold on information. Hearing him respond to a question with such an absurd evasion reminded me of working with an IT helpdesk guy who acts like his knowing how to install Microsoft Office was a birthright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a more recent example, a friend training at another gym had been keeping a nifty online technique notebook. Not a lot of detail, but very helpful perspective intended to feed the hungry Jiu-Jitsu diaspora. Their instructor caught wind of the website and was uncomfortable. The concern was that it might help competitors. The web site no longer discusses Jiu-Jitsu technique. Let&amp;rsquo;s say the web page was discussing what this student learned about executing a take-down. Can you imagine some morsel of information being divulged that would somehow alter the competitive landscape? Google &amp;ldquo;double leg take-down.&amp;rdquo; Tell me there could have been something truly original in the web site&amp;rsquo;s description of this technique that will harm this coach&amp;rsquo;s business. No, and that wasn&amp;rsquo;t the point of the website. Learning and communicating is a personal process that takes the student beyond the boundaries of the mats. This student was stuck in a stranglehold of censorship.
These two situtions, separated by a decade of time and completely different instructor lineage, illustrates what is commonplace in this sport. Some instructors treat information like a valuable commodity in a world where it is already free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information isn&amp;rsquo;t power. In the information-connected economy, the kinds of businesses that can get away with treating information as a valuable commodity are rapidly becoming as old as your Dad&amp;rsquo;s Wall Street Journal curbside dropoff. And don&amp;rsquo;t get me into an ad revenue argument since it&amp;rsquo;s so far off the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years on the mats, I&amp;rsquo;ve come up with some really sweet moves. I can find dozens of videos on the Internet of guys who have come up with the same moves on their own. They&amp;rsquo;ve given them their own silly names like &amp;ldquo;De-goitering the Goat&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Feed the baby&amp;rdquo; but the moves are the same. This is a healthy sign of a exploding system with a spirit of innovation, expansion, and sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;coaches-hide-your-secrets-at-your-own-peril&#34;&gt;Coaches: hide your secrets at your own peril.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students are passionate about this sport and hungry for information. They&amp;rsquo;ll go get the answers with or without you. Be the leader and coach you are supposed to be and teach them what you know. By keeping secret techniques, you won&amp;rsquo;t be forced to learn anything new. Holding back your techniques makes you stale and dumb, not smarter than the rest of the crowd. Teach your students everything you know so they can challenge you to come up with new ideas. You were the smarty pants who figured those old secrets out to begin with, right? So, go make up some new ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love witnessing the process in action. Every few months, I drop some new technique on my students that usually starts with all of them tapping and freaking out about &amp;ldquo;what the hell was that?&amp;rdquo; We cover it in class, repeatedly. A month later, some of them are starting to figure it out and execute it on their own. After 6 months, the technique is old hat: we&amp;rsquo;ve figured out 6 variations, mastered a few of them, and know 10 ways to shut it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being the only person who knows how to execute the Biggie Slicer is as boring as playing Quake III in God mode. The splatter and spray of guts are fun for a while, but you are left wanting someone who can scare you into getting better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time I get a visiting instructor on my mats, I make it a point to teach something I don&amp;rsquo;t expect him to know. By &amp;ldquo;liberating this technique into the wild,&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;m sure to have to get much better at executing it, discovering defenses, and variations. That&amp;rsquo;s how this sport keeps moving, and that&amp;rsquo;s how the best athletes in the sport keep growing.
The smartest guy in the room is only as smart as the information he&amp;rsquo;s capable of teaching the group. Prove you&amp;rsquo;re smart: give it away, now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Small Milestone on a Long Path</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/a-small-milestone/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/a-small-milestone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like most long-term endeavors, there are few significant milestones. In a sport like Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu, where the journey from white to black belt only has 3 intermediate steps, the milestones are literally &amp;ldquo;few and far between.&amp;rdquo; In my case, with 13 years in the making of 2008 black belt promotion, simple math will tell you just how far those milestones were set apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of our time working though intense athletic effort is filled with small challenges, victories, incremental growth, and setbacks. Even if you train 4 times per week, go to every seminar and open mat available, and compete regularly, you will find long periods of time where getting over the smallest obstacle will challenge your resolve to continue the journey ahead. The harder you train, the more likely you will get injured. The more you cross-train with others, the more likely you will find someone who will kick your butt so regularly and with such domination, that you will likely wonder if you can ever get past them. I remember being a white belt, completely sore and beaten up from my previous training day, afraid to face the mats again, wondering if I should return for another brutal work-out. Of course, I returned, but was faced with this constant question for months. The sport is insanely challenging. Everyone you meet on the mats sees you as fresh meat. The target is on your back every single day. As your rank progresses, this target gets bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu rewards people who can get past these big obstacles. The rewards are not just rank, but a knowledge base of skills that are broad and deep.
I remember a karate sensei of mine 20 years ago, in a moment of self-absorption, was boasting about how at his skill level, he could simply toy with his opponents &amp;ldquo;like a cat playing with a mouse.&amp;rdquo; I was simultaneously disappointed that he shared this with his students and intrigued that a level of skill that advanced was attainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than boast that I&amp;rsquo;m the biggest cat in the jungle, this promotion is a time to remember how many phenomenally talented athletes are in this amazing sport; many of them commanding a skill level that I can only hope to attain in my lifetime. I also hope that I have the ability to translate this wonderful sport into words capable of inspiring my students to stay on the long road. Don&amp;rsquo;t focus on the milestones. Focus on the gifts that come from the hard work, every day you are on the mats: friendship, fitness, and the skills of a cat just a little bit bigger than it was yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Unsolvable Problem</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-unsolvable-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-unsolvable-problem/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is a key lesson to learn in battle of any kind and is particularly appropriate to the way I approach application of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu technique to a fight or sparring match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve success in battle, you must present a dazzling flexibility to both respond to attack and counterattack with a level of speed and complexity that off-balance your opponent in a way that prevents them from ever gaining stable ground to continue the fight. A good example of this is the concept of “overwhelming display of force” that Special Forces military units specialize in. They create a problem that off-balances the enemy to such a degree that they are too busy running for cover to ever successfully form an offensive. Another example of this is a skilled debater who subtly changes their verbal attacks faster than their opponent can respond to the logical twists of reason that they are presented with. In both cases, the victorious has presented an &lt;em&gt;unsolvable problem&lt;/em&gt; for their opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The details of this concept of an unsolvable problem need to be considered in terms of the parameters present, which includes the timeframe and other “characteristics of the battlefield problem.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;timeframe&#34;&gt;Timeframe&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your opponent represents the enemy if you extend the concept of martial arts sparring to real battle. Each position your opponent presents and each attack they launch poses a specific problem for you that is framed in time. This timeframe can be split into a series of discrete moments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;initiation&#34;&gt;Initiation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the attack is launched or position is established. This is a moment of transition which can either be in the form of an initial attack or a new position in a series of maneuvers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;response&#34;&gt;Response&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you detect the attack or position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mental reflex: How your detection of this affects your mental state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical reflex: What your physical reaction is to this attack before it impacts you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;continuation-or-termination&#34;&gt;Continuation or termination&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impact of damage on you if the attack succeeds, or impact on your opponent if your response (evasion or counterattack) succeeds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And so on… Unless your response terminates the attack, your response will create a problem for your opponent to solve (a counterattack or new position).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;parameters-characteristics-of-the-problem&#34;&gt;Parameters: Characteristics of the Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each problem has a number of parameters, or components, that need to be understood to solve the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time do you have to solve the problem? As described above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has the advantage? In other words, who is in position to do the most damage, assuming there are no impediments to continuous attack from both sides?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is in control of the movement or balance of the position? Are you in a position to control their balance or restrict their movement? For example, even if your opponent is on top, where they have the positional advantage, if you are in a position to sweep or reverse them you may have more control of the movement than your opponent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is your opponent solving the problem you have posed them? Turn the tables. Just as you are trying to confound their attempts to better you, they are doing the same to you. For example, if you are controlling them in a position of advantage yet they are quickly getting control by setting up an escape, they are solving your problem and will soon be giving you a new problem of your own!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has psychological control? This is a key concept that deserves an entire article of its own. We&amp;rsquo;ll focus on this continually.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the physical state of your opponent? Are they injured? Winded? Have you noticed them losing their energy level?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental issues around the fight (walls, chairs, debris, other people &amp;ndash; friendly or unfriendly). Many of these can work to your advantage or disadvantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these factors needs continuous monitoring for you to understand what the next move is for you in a fight. The more experienced a fighter is, the faster they can assess these factors and act or make corrections to their advantage in a fight. If you sense your opponent is solving the problem, you must change position to create a new problem for your opponent. The faster you change the parameters of the problem, the less likely they will be able to solve this. This creates a huge psychological advantage and accelerates physical exhaustion for your opponent as they struggle to solve these problems. In effect, you are creating an unsolvable problem by changing the problem faster than your opponent can solve it. As we practice flow on the mats, you should concentrate on this concept, since it requires a high level of skill on position transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;training-for-the-unsolvable-problem&#34;&gt;Training for the Unsolvable Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;question-and-answer&#34;&gt;Question and Answer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a way to take baby steps to &amp;ldquo;the unsolvable problem.&amp;rdquo; We break down the rapid-fire problem and response into a slow paced &amp;ldquo;dialog.&amp;rdquo; Starting with these positions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pass guard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escape side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escape mount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;we pose a question in the form of a position, physically asking &amp;ldquo;How would you escape from this?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your partner responds by attempting to escape in one motion. Your partner must resist the compulsion to start fighting your way out. They will make a single move, then let you ask a new question. By allowing them to respond (not resisting the response), you allow the dialog to continue. After they respond, you change your position to present a new problem. And so on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rapid-conversation&#34;&gt;Rapid Conversation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fast, 3 second exchange of &amp;ldquo;questions and answers&amp;rdquo; (a set of 4 or 5 positions flowing into each other as your partner responds). As a quick sequence of questions and answers, it becomes like a very quick match where you stop after 3 seconds and assess your position, awaiting your partner to start another &amp;ldquo;burst of conversation.&amp;rdquo; Let the person who started &amp;ldquo;lead.&amp;rdquo; Switch lead after a few &amp;ldquo;conversations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Sense on Training</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/common-sense/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/common-sense/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-students&#34;&gt;For Students&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life isn&amp;rsquo;t fair; distinguish yourself with intense training. Remember when your coach told you size and strength don&amp;rsquo;t matter? He was wrong: strength matters. When all else is equal between opponents, whoever has the edge in the smallest way will distinguish themselves in victory. Oh, and size matters too. A big guy with like skills will crush a little guy. Sorry little guys. Coming from a featherweight, I share your pain. Literally. On the other hand, technique, stamina, and aggression can imbalance a much greater differential in size and strength. I have beaten much bigger guys than me, but there was always a reason: no magic, just training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cross Train - If you want to be a good martial artist, you need to be a good athlete. I don&amp;rsquo;t care what you choose to do, but cross train in something. Swim, lift weights, run, bike, rock climb, play soccer. It will help your strength and endurance. It&amp;rsquo;s also fun. Don&amp;rsquo;t be a martial arts nerd: get outside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a Good Student; Take notes. Good students take notes. Committing your training to personal notes is an important step in memorizing your training, and recording a permanent document of what you may end up spending a lifetime acquiring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test yourself. Good students test themselves to get a fair measurement of how they stack up against others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things Need to Change: Keep an Open Mind. Don&amp;rsquo;t get stuck in the same old habits. Find new positions to fight from. Take off your gi and fight. Put on a blindfold and fight. Don&amp;rsquo;t ever ask permission to try something new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question all assumptions made by students and teachers. Any teacher that can&amp;rsquo;t deal with curiosity is in the wrong business. The only dumb question is the one you didn&amp;rsquo;t ask.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust your experience. Have faith in your accumulated mat time and experience in fights. Clear your head and go with your reflexes. If you can&amp;rsquo;t do this, get back on the mats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let yourself heal. Don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to be a hero if you have an injury. Take time off from training, and don&amp;rsquo;t let anyone talk you back until you are better. But, know when it is time to get back on the mats. The longer you are gone, the harder it is to get back out there. [Read more about injuries here]().&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break the rules, and don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid of (or surprised by) the consequences. Non-conformists drive people nuts, so be prepared to go it alone if you have to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-instructors&#34;&gt;For Instructors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward the most curious. Be prepared to learn something from your students. Support an atmosphere of creativity and openness, so everyone feels comfortable asking questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t beat your dog and don&amp;rsquo;t beat your students with your dogma. Never ask your students to have faith in you or &amp;ldquo;just trust&amp;rdquo; you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody has all the answers. Admit when you don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer, but be ready to get in there and figure it out with sweat and hard work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have fun. If you can&amp;rsquo;t have fun and make fun of yourself every day, you&amp;rsquo;ve lost yourself in your own self-importance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge is wealth; Share it with others. If you don&amp;rsquo;t spend at least 51% of your time coaching others in something, you are adding no net value to your time on Earth. Don&amp;rsquo;t get self-absorbed. Give it away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your students aren&amp;rsquo;t your property. Don&amp;rsquo;t whine if they go to another school. [Read more about this]().&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compete, or don&amp;rsquo;t push your students into competition. If you can&amp;rsquo;t be a positive role model for the courage required to step on the mats and potentially lose in front of them, then don&amp;rsquo;t be a hypocrite and encourage them to compete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn from other sports. Develop training tools. Drill, drill, drill. Videotape student fights and analyze them with your students. Introduce circuit training. Get your students into shape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t expect respect; earn it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Train For Yourself</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/train-for-yourself/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/train-for-yourself/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your instructor is human. Don&amp;rsquo;t let yourself get sucked into a cult of personality.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental and nearly universal aspects of martial arts training is the intense loyalty students feel to their instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe you should be loyal to those who are loyal to you, meaning you should devote your loyalty where it is earned. In some circumstances the loyalty I have seen students devote to instructors borders on blind zeal. Over the years, I have fallen into this trap from time-to-time.  It is all too easy to carelessly fantasize that your instructor is the toughest martial artist in the planet and that everything he does should be followed with biblical devotion. That&amp;rsquo;s not my viewpoint. While I feel that within a specific school you should respect the authority of an instructor, the instructor is providing a paid service, not unlike a personal trainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;news-flash-self-defense-instruction-is-a-service&#34;&gt;News Flash! Self-Defense Instruction is a Service&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most prevalent problem in martial arts today. Martial arts instructors place their ego before the customer. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it over and over again. Most martial arts instructors will talk the talk of your personal growth, but when push comes to shove, they forget it and put their goals squarely in your path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a service industry. You, the customer (the student), hold the reins. Your instructor may help you navigate, should help you motivate, and will pick you up and redirect you when you crash. But everything you learn belongs to you. You paid for it with sweat, time, and money. It&amp;rsquo;s yours. While you may credit your 4th grade reading teacher for your love of fiction novels, the stories you have read are yours alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;know-when-it-s-time-to-leave&#34;&gt;Know when it&amp;rsquo;s time to leave&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen a pattern in many martial arts schools. As students advance through the ranks, one of three things happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students get &amp;ldquo;fat and complacent&amp;rdquo; and start to mimic the head instructor, barking orders at the new students and taking every opportunity to beat them senseless. They are completely in tune with each others&amp;rsquo; techniques and habits. They rarely, if ever, challenge themselves in competition or against unknown (experienced) opponents. They have a stature they have worked far too hard on to have someone knock them off their pedestal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Others begin to see the weaknesses in their instructor, whether these are moral, political, or physical weaknesses. These students tend to leave, either establishing their own schools or joining a &amp;ldquo;competing&amp;rdquo; school. In this case, an &amp;ldquo;exodus of the awakened&amp;rdquo; sometimes follows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The senior students begin to assist instruction and the head instructor works on diplomacy with other schools, associations, and bridge building to promote growth in the sport. This is the optimal arrangement, but is unfortunately rare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think it is a natural, and even beneficial process that advanced students with an open mind and true passion for experiencing personal growth will either desire to begin to instruct, thus allowing the head instructor to focus on outward-facing activities or fly away from the nest. The only unfortunate thing about this is that, due to the lifelong loyalty expected, a bridge is often burned by leaving. If your instructor has the correct attitude toward growing students, you will be welcomed back for training and you will indeed have a lifelong coach, even after you open your own school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, having the ability to fly doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you should leave the nest. Know when it&amp;rsquo;s time.  There are many schools with solid curriculum, fantastic coaching, and great facilities that can satisfy a decade of martial arts training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;building-bridges-and-fresh-meat&#34;&gt;Building Bridges and Fresh Meat&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of training for yourself involves seeking relationships with other students and instructors in other schools in the area. This helps in many ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gives you access to numerous new training partners, a term I call &amp;ldquo;eating fresh meat.&amp;rdquo; The ones you train with at your primary school are like your brothers. You love them and have fun with them, but when you wrestle with your brothers, there is often times nothing new to learn. Sure, any mat time is better than none at all, but there is either a permanent pecking order in place, or dull and predictable stalemates are the norm.
It allows you to test the waters to make sure that the quality of instruction you are getting really is the best for the money and time you commit to this most important endeavor. Gasp! Did I say money and time are more important than the deep relationship of loyalty you owe to your instructor? Why, yes I did. Remember the topic? &amp;ldquo;Train for yourself, not your instructor.&amp;rdquo;
If the school is training in a different style, it provides valuable cross-training. This may lead to a deeper exploration of the new style if you decide it is right for you. Jiu-Jitsu students should wrestle with wrestlers, play with judoka and samboka, and prepare to learn something new. I have learned wonderful new ideas by shutting my mouth and listening to a wrestling coach instruct a class.
Challenge your instructor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are training at the right school, this may seem like suicide. Most instructors really are much tougher than you. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to imply you want to actually somehow destroy your instructor, but I want to make an important point. After training in traditional Karate and Aikido schools for well over 13 years, I&amp;rsquo;m allowed to make this observation: most students don&amp;rsquo;t try hard enough when testing technique on their instructors, or sparring with them. This is once again the &amp;ldquo;larger than life&amp;rdquo; problem. If an instructor asks you to throw a punch at him and you actually hit him (his demonstration fails), would you feel really bad? Should you? No. When you spar with your instructor, would you feel bad if you beat him? You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t. In reality, if his technique doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, you don&amp;rsquo;t want to walk around with some false sense of security do you? The first time I beat one of my instructors sparring, I experienced mixed emotions. I certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like celebrating. It was a bit awkward, he didn&amp;rsquo;t congratulate me, and I was left wondering what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is a form of dishonesty to not challenge your instructor with your greatest effort and technique. Challenging him will keep you both sharp. I encourage my students to fight to win, and many of them are quite a handful!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bane of Freedom</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-bane-of-freedom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-bane-of-freedom/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;a-warning-about-instructors-who-put-themselves-before-you&#34;&gt;A warning about instructors who put themselves before you.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many instructors treat their knowledge as a treasure that is only bestowed upon those in their inner circle: their most trusted students who have shown loyalty, their knights. All the other students are serfs who have not yet proven their worth to the king. All live within his kingdom. No bonds are made or allowed with other neighboring kingdoms. You can join the king, but you must move within the walls, and never leave again. Anyone who strays outside the walls of the kingdom are banished forever. They are suspected as spies who may have sold the keys of the castle to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the kingdom-building realities of an egomaniacal instructor with a distorted world-view of the purpose of knowledge. Knowledge is to be set free. Allow your students to seek it anywhere they may. The borders must be porous to allow for great relationships with your neighbors, sharing of knowledge, and creation of new knowledge from old. Encourage cross training anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sign of kingdom-building is the treatment of questions from the students. I have seen instructors who don&amp;rsquo;t answer questions or do so in such an oblique fashion that over time, questions stop from the students. I have had one instructor who would answer some questions with &amp;ldquo;That will cost $100 and one hour of your time,&amp;rdquo; meaning the student could get an answer only if they paid for a private lesson with the high-priced black belt. When a new student joins, they wonder why nobody else is asking questions. They soon learn their lesson with a belittling experience in front of the class. Why create secrets, mystery, and intrigue? In doing this, the knowledge instructors hold is locked in the castle tower. Foster innovation, research, exploration, and inquisitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build a school that is about building students, not about building a kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-the-lesson-from-another-service&#34;&gt;Learning the Lesson From Another Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try a simple analogy. Forget martial arts for a minute. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you want to be a doctor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You pick the best medical school around, because you want to be the best doctor you can be. You want to save lives and you believe you can be a success. After doing a great job in pre-med, you have envisioned a dream of opening a small medical clinic where you can better the lives of a small community. Your friends and family believe in you. But more than anything, you feel compelled by your principles to pursue this dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You go to the medical school and do a great job, year after year. You expand your knowledge and arm yourself with the tools to save lives. The dean of the college counsels you, shares with you his profound knowledge, and treats you like family. Your professors are top notch. You take an internship with a small clinic to diversify and deepen your experience. It turns out that this is more fulfilling than your class work because it demonstrates you understand real world application of what you have learned. You take other internships.  As you come closer to the end of med school, you organize opening your own clinic. You have imagined this whole time how this would work, and now it is becoming real. You excitedly share with others around you the slow process of creating this clinic as it unfolds. Your family, friends, and other students are happy for you and wish you the best. Your college dean and professors are proud. You embark on the greatest dream of your life and are blessed to actually love your job and the benefits your work bestows upon those you touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During your years of practice, other doctors join you. You share your knowledge freely, discover new methods, and publish these for all to learn from. Years later, a young doctor joins you. You mentor this doctor until he knows enough to go out and open a clinic of his own. You are sad to see him go. But much more than this, you are proud of their accomplishment and bless him as he makes his way onward. This young doctor considers you their lifelong friend and mentor. Their successes transitively become your successes. You unlocked the door for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instructors-unlock-the-door&#34;&gt;Instructors: Unlock the Door&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the dream of many martial artists to know enough to teach someday: to give back what they have been given. It is a shame that some martial arts instructors put more focus on protecting their knowledge than creating an environment of limitless growth. Instructors: know what your students seek. Put their goals before you or get out of the business. &lt;a href=&#34;(http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/train-for-yourself/)&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s what service is all about&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Students are customers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow on the Path to Mastery</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow-and-mastery/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow-and-mastery/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;What drives us to train in this sport with such never-ending passion, spending a small fortune on training toward your black belt, burning thousands of precious hours away from work and family, at substantial risk to life and limb?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the math. A black belt could easily cost you $12,000 (10 years at $100 per month), not including travel and equipment costs. Getting there will take over 3300 hours on the mats, travelling to seminars, and competing. The math will invariably include a dozen injuries and bills from more doctors than you will care to recall. Of course, a black belt is by no means a master, really just a glorified beginner in the grand scheme of things. If you believe Malcolm Gladwell in Outliers: The Story of Success, this is a little over 30% of the way toward mastery. At nearly 15 years in the sport I’m about halfway &amp;ldquo;there.&amp;rdquo; Wherever &amp;ldquo;there&amp;rdquo; is…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-motivates-us-to-drive-drive-drive&#34;&gt;What motivates us to drive, drive, drive?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize, we spend a ton of money and time to get ourselves beaten to a pulp for a level of mastery which may never happen. What motivates us to drive, drive, drive?
The payoff is mastery, which as I hint at above, is ironically something that is only asymptotically attainable. We can get close, but really never get there. But we keep driving anyway, getting our butts kicked by guys and gals who we can only dream of &lt;em&gt;powning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does motivation come from? How can we get past the plateaus and walls that invariably block our path over and over again?
I have previously discussed the importance of flow as a means of unleashing creativity, advancing new ideas, and physically preparing your body for full-out battle. Flow continues to be at the center of some of the most important growth moments for me in the sport. A book called &lt;em&gt;Drive: The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us&lt;/em&gt;, by an author with a downright Reservoir Dogs-esque name, Daniel Pink, illuminates this subject further with the help of solid research and engaging style. Pink, intrigued by the intrinsic and extrinsic roots of motivation, thoroughly covers the topic and ends up distilling the essential drivers for motivation along three lines: autonomy, mastery, and purpose. Mastery is a huge motivator for those of us in this sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slow march towards mastery includes moments where your growth, energy, and motivation are at their greatest. Coincidentally with my discussions on this topic, Pink calls this &amp;ldquo;flow.&amp;rdquo; He equates flow with play, in that the labors and efforts of the work you are engaged in become effervescent and lost in the moment of unconscious progress you enjoy in flow. How can you find your flow and how can you make this a means to accelerate growth and enjoyment? How do we work to get lost in the moment? Translated as a Zen kōan, we should concentrate maximum effort to release effortless play. The more you flow, the more you grow, and the more fun you have on the path. Having fun is a great counter balance to the pain of training hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read my article on &lt;a href=&#34;(http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/blog-flow/)&#34;&gt;flow&lt;/a&gt;. Think about how you experience flow on the mats. Relax, be patient, have fun, and flow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Many-Faceted Fighter</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-faceted-fighter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/the-faceted-fighter/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do You Have What it Takes to Succeed in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and Submission Grappling?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;for-students-new-to-the-sport&#34;&gt;For Students New to The Sport&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are asking yourself: &amp;ldquo;Do I have what it takes to train in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and Submission Grappling?&amp;rdquo; you are not alone. It&amp;rsquo;s a daunting sport to enter. Watching your first class from the sidelines will give you a mixture of excitement and dread. You will be questioning every aspect of yourself as you make a decision. In short, you will discover that for every aspect of skill required in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu, there are people who persevere in the sport due to strengths in a variety of areas. Be prepared for something completely different, but understand that despite your best efforts, it may not work out. Here are some characteristics to consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fitness and Weight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strength&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aggression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical Skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fearlessness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Competitiveness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical Intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical Creativity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of your Opponent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of Yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Showmanship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;characteristics-that-define-the-fighter&#34;&gt;Characteristics that Define the Fighter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these characteristics can be improved upon with work, such as strength, fitness level, and technical skill. Others can be changed slightly with substantial work, such as competitiveness. Others are difficult to change or control, such as aggression, agility, and physical creativity. I just scratch the surface of each of these characteristics. One could dedicate chapters and books on these subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;fitness-level-and-weight&#34;&gt;Fitness Level and Weight*&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It almost always starts here. People who are &amp;ldquo;out of shape&amp;rdquo; often think they need to get into shape before joining. I suggest that you really are never going to be in shape enough to start grappling unless you are already grappling. Paradoxical, but it&amp;rsquo;s the same in every sport. Until you use the muscles and move in the way the sport demands, you won&amp;rsquo;t discover them though some other cross-training regimen. Get on the mats and get in shape there. Regarding weight control, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen more pounds shed on these mats than I can count. It&amp;rsquo;s hard work, but it can be done. And why not learn how to fight while you go through the hard labor of weight loss?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our mats, the overweight train side by side with the super-fit. We&amp;rsquo;re all in it together. Fitness as a way of life, practiced through the sport of submission grappling. In the professional fighting context, mixed martial artists are well regarded as some of the most well rounded athletes out there. It is rare to find a successful fighter who doesn&amp;rsquo;t have an incredible fitness level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As great as fighters Ken Shamrock and BJ Penn are, they have both lost fights because their opponent was better conditioned, not more technical. Ortiz did it to Shamrock and Matt Hughes did it to Penn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;strength&#34;&gt;Strength&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount strength matters depends on the situation. If two opponents of similar skill faced off, strength would matter and would absolutely define the victor. Since it is rarely the case that two people are that closely matched in a fight, especially an unplanned street altercation, strength really doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the lion&amp;rsquo;s share of consideration. In training for competition, anything an athlete can do to legally improve their ability to win should be focused on. There is no doubt that strength training improves the overall athlete. If you are not naturally strong, you should weight train, use kettle bells, etc. If you are naturally strong, you can put it off, but eventually, you should consider resistance training to improve your game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;size&#34;&gt;Size&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve said in other articles, size matters. While many proponents of this sport will point to great champions who overcame larger opponents, they neglect to say that those larger opponents had less skill, agility, or stamina than the smaller opponent. Taking a single factor into play against a like opponent in all other aspects, size matters. Like strength, the happy news is that most large guys out there don&amp;rsquo;t know a lot about fighting. Paradoxically, larger (or stronger) guys tent to learn the finer points of ground fighting slower than smaller guys since they can rely on their other assets. Technique comes later, and only when their size (or strength) is neutralized by an opponent of greater skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While nobody denies that MFS fighter Tim Sylvia is great, his size has clearly contributed to his success. Holland&amp;rsquo;s Semmy Schilt has experienced almost as much fame as Sylvia (from my biased North American perspective), with less talent and much more height. Bob Sapp is perhaps the most hyperbolically huge person with surprisingly little technical skill, stamina, fearlessness, or agility on the K-1 scene. His sheer size draws crowds as if to a freak show and help him smash unwitting opponents to pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;aggressiveness&#34;&gt;Aggressiveness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggression is an interesting quality, and one that surprisingly doesn&amp;rsquo;t help a refined fighter much. Aggression, simply stated, is the ease with which a fighter is willing to be violent or harmful. It is completely different from the desire to win, or more accurately, the complete distain for defeat. This attribute is the competitiveness, or the Desire to Win. Don&amp;rsquo;t confuse the two. An aggressive man may lose all desire to win at the slightest sign of pain, loss of position, or exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t need to be a naturally aggressive person to love the challenge of competition. I&amp;rsquo;m a very passive individual. I would never fight unless cornered or defending a loved one. Yet I love the combination of competition and challenge that comes when grappling on the mats. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to overstate my case, but there may actually be a negative correlation. Overly aggressive guys generally clumsily hurt people. When this happens, they get ostracized (other guys don&amp;rsquo;t want to train with them) or even physically beaten by the senior students repeatedly to scare them off. It is rare that someone with the singular skill of aggression distinguishes themselves in the sport. On the other hand, a nice dose of controlled aggression combined with several other factors can make for a great fighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;technical-skill&#34;&gt;Technical Skill&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical skill is the accumulated knowledge of a student and their ability to draw upon it when needed, with appropriate speed, strength, distancing, and precision. The sports of submission grappling and Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu celebrate technical skill like most martial arts and sports. Those with the most technical skill tend to be those who have accumulated the most realistic mat time against strong opponents and have been lucky enough to have solid coaching. Clearly being able to demonstrate technical skill requires significant agility, technical intelligence, and usually requires flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical skill is by far the most important of the characteristics that make a fighter great. When Randy Couture wore out Gonzaga against the fence in UFC 74, it was his technical skill that kept Gonzaga at bay. Sure, other aspects of the fighter helped (strength, fitness, fearlessness, desire to win), but it was Couture&amp;rsquo;s skill that allowed his much heralded body lock to disable Gonzaga. By far the most spectacularly technical fighters out there is Marcelo Garcia. Garcia has won the pinnacle competition, the ADCC, in his 66-76 kg weight division three times in a row. He has only lost against much larger opponents in the absolute division, generally in the finals. How Garcia wins is important: he almost always wins by submission rather than points, this is a key indicator of technical advantage over his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;fearlessness&#34;&gt;Fearlessness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a bit of bravery to face off with an opponent on the mats. It takes even more bravery to come back to class after getting your butt whooped a few times. I recall my early days as a white belt. I&amp;rsquo;d miss a couple of classes and think how easy it would be to never go back. I knew if I went back in, I&amp;rsquo;d get obliterated by the more advanced students. I think the pure excitement of learning such an effective fighting system kept me coming back. It overcame the fear. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be fearless to be great. In fact, there is a fine line between bravado and stupidity. Knowing when to tap and when to back down in an unwinnable match will keep the injuries at bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically skilled students may become more fearless, simply because fear is all about the unknown. An advanced student knows what every submission feels like and knows their limits. An advanced student has a greater chance of winning a fight. Both of these greatly diminish fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearlessness is closely related to Desire to Win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;flexibility&#34;&gt;Flexibility&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flexibility is completely independent of all the other factors. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen overweight, physically unfit people with incredible flexibility. Conversely, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen some amazing fighters with significant limits to their range of motion in various limbs. Some people are naturally inflexible in certain parts. No amount of stretching, yoga, or conditioning will improve this more than a few percentage points. More flexible people can get out of tighter jams and can stay calm in very nasty physical situations. But I&amp;rsquo;ve got some very good fighters who are very tight. It matters, but won&amp;rsquo;t make or break your game on the mats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eddie Bravo&amp;rsquo;s flexibility has helped him redefine the sport of submission grappling. I also credit Eddie&amp;rsquo;s physical creativity in creating scores of new moves. Not everyone can succeed with the rubber guard. More flexible fighters have more options to put their body into shapes that help them succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;agility-and-balance&#34;&gt;Agility and Balance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agility is by far the most important characteristic of this sport. Agility, in context with this sport, is defined as the ability to move your body smoothly and precisely on command, from a multitude of angles, both with or without the full weight and strength of your opponent borne upon you. That&amp;rsquo;s a tall order for many students. Prospective students who ask me if they have what it takes to succeed on the mats are often times answered with this question: &amp;ldquo;Can you dance?&amp;rdquo; This is a good indication of agility, balance, physical creativity, and physical intelligence. After training over a hundred students at Austin Jiu-Jitsu, it is quite clear that the most agile students bubble quickly to the top of the stack of the group. Agile students fly past awkward ones. In the end, gyms that train in fighting sports have a pecking order. The most agile are often on top. It is rare that someone without agility will dominate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diego Sanchez&amp;rsquo; balance and agility have helped him become one of the most successful fighters in his weight class. He outclassed Karo Parisyan, one of the most dangerous fighters in the world, in UFC Fight Night 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;desire-to-win&#34;&gt;Desire to Win&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(i.e. Will, Competitiveness, Confidence, Mental Strength, Mind Game)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be very afraid of an opponent with copious amounts of competitiveness. An overly competitive personality in a poorly skilled opponent is dangerous to himself. These are they guys who never know when to tap and end up getting hurt and emotional when they lose an unwinnable fight. Conversely, a competitive personality in a highly skilled opponent is a treacherous opponent indeed. A desire to win is an outstanding quality that absolutely makes the difference between chumps and world champions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of the desire to win is the mental strength that allows a fighter to stare into the eyes of another. While some may call it an act, this display of confidence tests the will of the opponent. It&amp;rsquo;s not just a show when Vanderlei Silva stares down his opponent before a fight. It is Silva beginning to impose his will on the opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;physical-intelligence&#34;&gt;Physical Intelligence&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Right-Brained Fighter has Muscle Memory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical intelligence is defined by a rapid ability to recall physical motion. Some people learn physical motion with fewer repetitions than others. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen this as completely independent of other forms intelligence. &amp;ldquo;Book smart&amp;rdquo; intelligent people don&amp;rsquo;t learn physical motion any faster and certainly can&amp;rsquo;t tap into that muscle memory any faster. The difference is how quickly muscle memory latches on and if it can be tapped when needed. If it&amp;rsquo;s not there when you need it, in an instant, you don&amp;rsquo;t have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People with greater muscle memory certainly learn faster in physical sports like Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu. If you don&amp;rsquo;t remember techniques well, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to &amp;ldquo;rep&amp;rdquo; techniques more. In the end, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn it if you commit the time to practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;physical-creativity&#34;&gt;Physical Creativity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Left Brained Fighters define their own moves&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical creativity is the ability to work out new situations with the movement of your body. For example, a physically creative person can discover new submissions or escapes quickly by untangling the numerous positional relationships between the fighter and the opponent. These are the guys who advance the sport and define the fighting system in terms of their own body, rather than simply mimicking the movements of others independent of consideration of the physical aspects of the differences of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The left brained fighter isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily artistic off the mats, but on the mats they take the often times clumsy movements of fighting into something graceful and beautiful. Generally, a physically creative person is highly agile, but an agile person may not be physically creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question to ask is why advanced fighters so often end up making up their own moves? Is it primarily because advanced fighters have so much mat time to have successfully, through trial and error, created new moves? Or is it because only physically creative people make it to the advanced levels of this sport? It is very unusual to see a brown or black belt in the sport of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu who hasn&amp;rsquo;t defined their own special sub-species of the sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;knowledge-of-the-opponent&#34;&gt;Knowledge of the Opponent&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sun Tzu summed it up best &amp;ldquo;If you know the enemy and know yourself, you need not fear the result of a hundred battles.&amp;rdquo; Beyond simple knowledge, you need to know how to adapt your fight. You may know someone has great take-downs, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t work the sprawl, you&amp;rsquo;ll still end up on your back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Randy Couture beat Tim Silvia in UFC 68, he won the fight by knowing how to avoid the punching power of Sylvia. A new Randy Couture emerged at this fight: someone who bobbed and weaved like an experienced boxer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;knowledge-of-your-own-limits&#34;&gt;Knowledge of your Own Limits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t get pulled into a fight you can&amp;rsquo;t possibly win. Fighting an opponent out of your league isn&amp;rsquo;t smart. Of course, the prerequisite to this decision is knowing your opponent. Unless this is a friendly sparring match, if you can compare your skills and you can&amp;rsquo;t win, don&amp;rsquo;t fight. Unfortunately, cornered on the street, you have no choice. No matter what the odds, fight to survive, even if outgunned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Royce Gracie bravely stepped on the mats against Matt Hughes in UFC 60, he dramatically underestimated Hughes, but more significantly, overestimated himself. Royce shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have taken that fight. I&amp;rsquo;d guess it was about the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;showmanship&#34;&gt;Showmanship&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem surprising to hear that showmanship in any way applies to the ability to fight, but showmanship is a mental game designed to get the crowd on your side and to get inside the head of your opponent. Nick Diaz is great at at goading his opponents. He&amp;rsquo;s so good at it, he even confused referee Steve Mazzaggati into mistakenly declaring that Diaz was somehow breaking the rules in the UFC. Nick knows how to piss people off. A pissed off opponent isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily more dangerous, just distracted. Kazushi Sakuraba&amp;rsquo;s showmanship gets the crowd behind him almost every time. When he spanked Ryan Gracie in Pride, it created such a buzz, the media attention alone elevated Sakuraba&amp;rsquo;s stature as a &amp;ldquo;Gracie Killer.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During matches, a fighter&amp;rsquo;s ability to conceal pain, pretend they are less challenged than they really are, and generally show no concern, is generally a successful approach. This poker face tactic prevents the easy &amp;ldquo;read.&amp;rdquo; If you know your opponent is in pain, tired, or afraid, you will pick up the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Close Your Eyes</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/close-your-eyes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/close-your-eyes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow, how&amp;rsquo;d we get here?&amp;rdquo; Wonders one of my students aloud as he pulls off his blindfold following fighting a match that took the grapplers, via a circuitous route, clear across the gym floor. &amp;ldquo;I thought we were still over there. That was disorienting! Cool!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disorienting, yes, but only visually so. Blindfolded grappling is a liberating experience. It&amp;rsquo;s unusual to think of your visual reference as a crutch, but as a primary sense, it necessarily dulls the others from contributing to your responses during a match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We keep a stack of tee shirts in my gym for these special occasions. When paired with a pair of ear guards, they make great blindfolds. I have yet to discover a blindfolding process that survives more than a half round of grappling, but the tee shirt and ear guards matchup is tight, light-proof, and cheap. At some point in the match, the honor system is invariably brought to bear, since the arrangement invariably loosens a bit. The match starts differently, of course. We have to pair up and kneel close to each other before putting on our blindfolds, or else hilarity will ensue as you seek out your opponent. Imagine the results shooting a single leg only to eat the wall behind them instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these limits, blindfolded grappling allows you to tap into your senses for a more creative roll than you&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed in a long time. When we roll blindfolded, you hear the usual grunts and umphs that accompany typical matches, but you also hear a lot of laughing and awe-inspired comments about the techniques which spring forth, unleashed by the creative release that seems to come with darkness. A complete lack of vision on the mats reveals more useful information about your surroundings, balance, and partner than you might find with the full use of your eyes. I have personally discovered, utterly surprised, brand new techniques that I wonder where they have been hiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiding in plain sight, you might say.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ready for Battle</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/ready-for-battle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/ready-for-battle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are some thoughts to help everyone get ready for battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay hydrated. Keep taking small drinks all day. You’ll need to use the restroom continually, but it will keep your body ready to go. Avoid soda and caffeine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Food. Eat a good meal the night before. Carb load, but don’t eat a huge breakfast. Starting with breakfast on the day of the competition you should be having very small snack-sized meals. Once I get to the competition, I won’t put more than a bite of a protein bar or half a banana in my belly every 2 hours. Before breakfast starts wearing off, start eating small, healthy snacks. I like dried fruit, yogurt, trail mix, and nibbles of protein bars. Power Gel is one of the best ways of getting quick replacement without putting “pukables” in your belly. If you eat or drink too much, you will puke.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare to wait. The waiting puts a huge strain on your brain and your body during a competition. Bring a good chair and entertainment. The bleachers are the pits. Not every venue will have space for you to set up a cozy folding chair, but bring them just in case. iPods, games, books, cards, …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch your competition. This is a crucial intelligence gathering opportunity. Where are they strongest? Weakest? What is their coach telling them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warm up. Don’t fight with cold muscles. You will tire much faster, be much weaker, less flexible, and less in the “fighting mindset” if you don’t warm up. Warm up and get psyched for your match. The first match is always the hardest. Trust me on this. You’ll be very tired after your first match and you’ll think “I can’t do that again.” But you can. As your body gets into “battle mode” it becomes easier to fight later matches. Flow rolling is great for warming up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know the rules. We’ve discussed them in class. If you have any questions, ask. There will be a rules review before the competition. You can ask questions of the head referee then.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kids: stay close. It may seem like fun running around a big venue space on a weekend, but don’t roam far, and don’t get in the way of the other competitors or officials. Always tell a parent where you are going if you leave the mat area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fight intelligently:

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tips to managing your match intelligently&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the time to get your points on your way through the match.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember the 3 second rule: stay in position for 3 seconds to get your points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are down on points, you must work hard to overcome this. If your opponent is winning, you may notice he starts to stall (he stops working and holds his position). It is crucial that you do your best to turn up the heat on a staller. Even though it is officially against the rules, most refs don’t take action against stalling (unfortunately).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember the knee on belly position. It is the easiest 2 points to get that most people never take advantage of.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always defend yourself aggressively when you are in a bad spot. Kids: If your opponent puts a submission move on you (like starts an armbar), you must show the referee that you are working to escape it or he will stop the match even before you tap. This is especially the case for chokes. I’m glad refs do this, since it is the best way to be safe with kids on the mat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be technical, not sloppy. Set up a submission as technically as you know how to. Pass the guard the way your coach taught you. People tend to go a little too fast in competition; often this speed outstrips their technical ability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The mind game. It is absolutely true that 80% of your fight is mental. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter how tough your opponent looks. They all tap if you put the right moves on them. Trust your training and believe in yourself. Never let your opponent know you are nervous or tired. If the ref stops the match to restart you, jump up and show the opponent and his coach that you have enough juice left for 1000 fights (especially if you are just about out of gas!). It is especially fun if you stand up first and offer your opponent a hand standing up. It sends 2 great messages: you are a great sport, and you have more juice left than your opponent. Never groan or yell during the match. It may end the match immediately (a yell is a tap to most referees).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring cameras. There is nothing more valuable than getting your matches on video.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cheer on your team. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t on deck for a match, you should be at mat side when a team mate is competing. Give them words of encouragement, but don’t disrupt my coaching. If your coach is saying something, keep your cheers in check for a moment. We are a team in a sport of individual competitors. One of the only ways you have to show team unity is being there for your teammate&amp;rsquo;s matches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your coach in the loop. If you are going to compete in the next 10 minutes or so, get word to your coach. If your coach is busy with another match when yours is called, tell the table officials (each mat has a separate table) that your coach is busy elsewhere. They will almost always delay a match (they&amp;rsquo;ll bring the next match on) to allow for the coach to get there. Don&amp;rsquo;t stress out about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a good sport. Shake your opponent&amp;rsquo;s hand before and after the match. Also shake the hand of your opponent&amp;rsquo;s coach after the match. Even if you’re upset about a loss or exhausted, crawl over and shake their hand and tell them “good match.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show up clean. Make sure your nails are cut and your gi is clean. A good ref won&amp;rsquo;t let you compete otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be on time, but don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised if they don&amp;rsquo;t start on time. They never start on time, but you should be ready anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t worry about winning. Of course you want to win, but if this is your first competition, you will learn valuable lessons regardless if you win or lose. Enjoy yourself and try your best. You will make mistakes but you&amp;rsquo;ll get them corrected over time. Tap if it hurts. No biggie.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre-register. Don&amp;rsquo;t ever register the day of the competition. The reason these things never start on time is that too many people procrastinate getting themselves registered. This creates impossible problems for bracketing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Train hard and get ready. Cross train for better cardio and strength.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Your Eyes</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/open-your-eyes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/open-your-eyes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are sitting in a circle, with 2 of my students grappling in the center. &amp;ldquo;Watch closely. We&amp;rsquo;ll talk about what happened when they&amp;rsquo;re done.&amp;rdquo; As the two grapple, the students watch intently. After about a minute of hard work, there is a furious scramble through a twisting maze of positions, and one student suddenly taps. &amp;ldquo;Good match! Ok, what happened? What did you see?&amp;rdquo; I ask the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a brief pause, one of the more eager students proclaims, &amp;ldquo;armbar.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ok, start at the beginning. Take us through the match.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blank stares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Umm. They started standing. Then there was a takedown. Then he passed the guard, I think.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Slow down. What about the details? What did they do when they were standing? How did the takedown get set up?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line of questioning continues until there is a clear timeline. With students around the edge of the mats, we have a good set of &amp;ldquo;camera angles&amp;rdquo; to replay the events, but their recollections are only as helpful as their perception. We work thorough the details and each transition is covered. We figure out where mistakes were made, how advantage was won and lost, and picked apart the match to my satisfaction. We dissect each moment of the match where an advantage is won or lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several more matches, the students are getting the hang of it. They are doing much more than watching. They are seeing. &amp;ldquo;Great work! Now, everyone find a partner.&amp;rdquo; People pair up, eager to use their newfound optics and awareness. In every match, there are turning points: moments where a subtle mistake is made, an opportunity taken, and the tide turns in favor of the victor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your memory is a good coach, but only if you have a good memory. Win or lose, remember the successes and failures that caused the outcome. The details of these memories can provide you with clues to success next time. Watch and feel the details of your matches. Talk about them with your partners and coaches afterwards. Get a camcorder on a tripod and record your matches. If someone gets a great move on you, ask them to take you through it again so you can burn it into your memory. I record every class at my gym. If there is a particularly interesting match, I&amp;rsquo;ll load it up and watch it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing the big moves is easy. An understanding of subtleties, details and nuances separates the good from the great. &lt;em&gt;Open your eyes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our System Does Not Coddle Weak Technique</title>
      <link>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/discard-what-doesnt-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jitshappens.com/blog/discard-what-doesnt-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Never use the closed guard,&amp;rdquo; I tell my students, &amp;ldquo;unless you are stalling or waiting to die.&amp;rdquo; As I state this, I wonder about how this position became so fundamental only to be eventually thrown away so unceremoniously. Then I consider the never-ending stream of new techniques, positions, attacks, counter-attacks, and defenses generated in Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu and submission grappling over time. I think about some amazing technique I learned years ago as a blue belt and how it has been rendered ineffective and obsolete by the withering juggernaut of a thousand athletes pounding from all angles like velociraptors probing the electrical containment fences in Jurassic Park. I recall some fundamental progenitor move, originally defined in utterly simple steps, that have evolved into a broad category of richly varied options (e.g. the Rubber Guard). I reflect on certain positions, once considered inescapable by all but the most advanced, which are now easily thrown off by less experienced fighters. What&amp;rsquo;s happening here? Is this natural acceleration or the result of a slow evolutionary process? And where are all these great new moves coming from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weak techniques will not survive. We know intuitively that techniques are successful only when they help win fights. Winning techniques are constantly studied by students of the sport. We adopt them, tweak them, make them work for their bodies, and transmit them to others. That&amp;rsquo;s how we spend the bulk of our time on the mats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fighting sport evolves by the influences of social interaction and information theory. In his 1979 Pulitzer Prize-winning novel &lt;em&gt;Gödel. Escher. Bach: An Eternal Golden Braid&lt;/em&gt;, author Douglas R. Hofstadter put a human spin on the mathematical concept of recursive enumeration. People come up with new ideas by watching the results of previous work and adapting. Repeat for a few generations, and some cool things start to happen. All of human civilization has developed using this process, gaining new insights from existing concepts. Over time, systems slowly evolve into more complexity and subtlety. Complexity is increased because past information and existing rules are applied to new situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the mats, we take old ideas and challenge them repeatedly. The weak techniques die off or morph into variations that are more successful in different situations. The media, usually blamed for dumbing down the masses, expands our information horizon and accelerates the speed of ideas flowing through what I call the Jiu-Jitsu diaspora. As it flows through, it is interpreted, tuned, adapted, mutated, then reflected slightly improved, back out the global information channel. New ideas are literally created from old information. Like an infinite tapestry, we weave the fabric of Jiu-Jitsu every time we step on the mats.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>